<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-05T16:44:35+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Where are Arathi and Kevin?</title><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><entry><title type="html">World Chess Championship: Singapore</title><link href="/world-chess-championship-singapore" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="World Chess Championship: Singapore" /><published>2025-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/world-chess-championship-singapore</id><content type="html" xml:base="/world-chess-championship-singapore"><![CDATA[<p>I procrastinated on writing these blog posts for so long partially due to the photos from Singapore. Over the course of last year, the time I spent on photography and especially post-processing dramatically increased. I was that crazy person trying to squat in weird angles to capture the perfect lighting on the spiky stalagmites in a cramped cave messing with my ISO and aperture settings to try to get the least grainy photo possible while having a shutter speed fast enough that my unsteady hands wouldn’t blur the photo. This meant that I would take tens, if not hundreds of photos in a day and then the process of sorting through them became so overwhelming that I just put it off. Occasionally I would get discouraged altogether because even after I sorted through the photos, I would end up thinking that not a single one captured the wondrousness that I was trying to snapshot forever. I have a great admiration for photographers who do this professionally and create masterpieces that manage to make me feel like I’m right there in the scene they’ve captured, feeling the same emotions that they did.</p>

<p>But as they say, perfect is the enemy of good and here we are about two months post-traveling, a few posts behind schedule. I got inspired again to write as we left Grenoble and while on the plane from Lyon to London, I started writing that post. It’s not finished, but just the act of writing reminded me of how much I like to write. I also did manage to finally sort through the Singapore photos and so felt like it was time. So here I am, four days into moving to London, fondly remembering our phenomenal time in Singapore.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/20241124_205100.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Singapore Flyer at night.

</figcaption>

<p>When we have traveled in the past, we usually go to a place to visit the location itself. As in: “I want to go to Botswana because there are cool safaris there and I want to see a safari.” Or “let’s plan a trip to Fiji because we want a beach vacation and I’d like to visit a place other than Hawaii and oooh, there’s a direct flight from San Francisco.” What this year has afforded us is the ability to travel to places because there is a cool thing happening there and the goal is to see the cool thing and maybe something else but not always. We did this with seeing the Nomad Games in Astana, Kazakhstan. Again with Diwali in Mumbai, India. Euros in Munich. And we did it again with visiting Singapore for the World Chess Championship (WCC) that happened to perfectly time itself with our Asian leg of our trip. </p>

<p>I don’t play much chess at all. I played a bit when I was in elementary school, wolfing down my lunches every Wednesday at top speeds so that I could hang out with the other “Chess Club” kids, playing a few games behind the school’s stage area that had been set up with small cheap foldable plastic tables and chairs. I can’t remember how long I did that, but it wasn’t very long. Kevin, on the other hand, loves to play online chess and pretty regularly catches up on the chess world “happenings.” He mentioned that the championship was happening in Singapore and we were already sort of planning on visiting the city so it was easy to say, let’s do it, and time our visit so that it landed so that we’d be able to watch the first match. </p>

<p>In preparation for the match, I asked ten billion questions about chess to Kevin, especially while hiking in Bhutan. Even though I knew I wouldn’t be able to totally understand everything going on, watching the best of the best play in any sport is a special and inspiring experience so my enthusiasm was high. I downloaded a chess app and started to work through some puzzles. I played some online chess where I magically won my first game and then proceeded to lose pretty much everything else. Perhaps it was futile anyways because there’s no way I was going to understand the strategies that the two grandmasters who were playing: defending champion Ding Liren and the young eighteen year old, Gukesh Dommaraju, who was vying to be the youngest ever winner of the WCC (there’s an asterisk here which is that he’s the <em>undisputed</em> youngest world champion for reasons that are too in-the-weeds/historical for me to describe or dig into). At least by the end of my own preparation, I could understand the meaning of the double exclamation mark, !!, that was the icon for the WCC and I could read what moves had been played and I learned the names (note: not the exact moves) of a few openings and their relative advantages and disadvantages. Not bad for a couple weeks of small time spent!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/PXL_20241124_062117349.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The famous Merlion of Singapore.

</figcaption>

<p>But first food. Singapore Hawker Fare. Look, I had quite a few people tell me that Singapore was a city worth visiting for maybe a day or two and that’s about it. Did you eat at the hawker stalls?! Singapore hawker stalls are these giant areas, packed with small stalls serving dirt cheap food that blow your taste buds away. Being vegetarian isn’t a problem at all. And with Singapore being one of the few countries out in this part of the world where English is the official language, the food is multicultural, just like the people. You can find authentic laksa, satay, Thai curries, Malaysian specialities, sushi, cronuts (why not), and so many other dishes that I had no idea even existed. I envied the people who worked close to Lau Pa Sat, strategically positioned in the midst of many skyscrapers filled with probably finance people. They all wore dress pants creased down the front and all tailored to exactly the right length which I associate with finance people. Those people probably justifiably get their Monday to Friday lunches at a stall. It’s like a food court on steroids. I kid you not, a couple of the hawker fare stalls have a Michelin star. It’s probably the cheapest Michelin star meal you could get in the whole world. Kevin got it and he thinks it’s deserved. Maybe eventually you want to be looking out for your sodium levels but hey, if you’re wearing dress pants and long sleeves in that crazy humidity, you probably need that sodium anyways, sweating it all out. All of the above to say, “street” food in Singapore is awesome.</p>

<p>Anyways, back to chess. One does not normally think of chess as a spectator sport. Let me enlighten you: watching the World Chess Championship in Singapore is like watching the Euros but everyone is panic-whispering rather than yelling when the games get close. There’s spicy drama. There’s endless strategy predictions by the pundits. There’s the post-match withering reviews by the scrutinizing Grandmasters. The Reddit memes. The random appearance of tech tycoons. It’s got it all.</p>

<p>We got tickets for the first two days of the championship which is played over 14 games in two and a half weeks. The event was held at a five star hotel situated on an island, Sentosa Island, which is sort of like an island full of theme parks. Normally when people visit the island, I believe the experience is supposed to be like visiting a resort where you stay on the island and everything is included with your stay: the theme park entries, food, sleeping arrangements, etc. Funny enough, there were absolutely no good food options while we were there but I became an expert at hiding some protein bars in my bag so that we could take breaks from games and eat them outside the venue. </p>

<p>We arrived at the hall the first day, panting and completely drenched because the taxi couldn’t drive us all the way to the venue (cars had to pay extra fees to drive on the island if not part of the resort) and we got lost and of course, it started to pour and we started running. We entered the hall and Kevin exclaimed, “did we just crash an AI conference?!” Smack in the middle, dominating the entire lobby was a giant Google AI display, full of Google employees, including Demis Hassabis, talking to people about their latest release called <a href="https://labs.google/genchess">GenChess</a> where you could create a virtual chess set using any theme you set as the creative inspiration. Actually their setup was super fun: they had big screens where you could play around with their AI to create a chess set and then you could pick one to print. We had some fun building cute potato chess pieces but unfortunately I clicked “regenerate” and we lost our cutest potato pawn. Oh well. </p>

<p>The venue was divided into roughly three areas. One was the main lobby area with the huge Google display and also a tiny FIDE shop tucked in the back. People would largely socialize here with cups of the unlimited tea and coffee the organization provided. Then there was the fan zone. The fan zone was an area where TVs were set up with the game running with commentary that was being recorded live in a room nearby. Periodically, grandmasters would hang out in the fan zone, maybe do a Q&amp;A. There were also tons of chess boards set up around the room for people to play; Kevin played a few rounds of chess with people here. It was really fun to see such a mix of kids and adults playing chess, even against each other. Some of these kids are so incredibly talented! I also appreciated the bean bags tossed around the room to lounge in. These were definitely popular.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/singapore_world_chess_championship_day_1_1-Enhanced-NR.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Playing chess in the fan zone.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/singapore_world_chess_championship_day_1_41-Enhanced-NR.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Watching the live chess commentary.

</figcaption>

<p>Finally, the playing room. I was curious how they would maintain silence for the players. The playing room is essentially fitted with a glass box in which Ding and Gukesh would play. There were also judges and referees in the box and at the very beginning of the game, photographers and videographers as well. All of the spectators were in the same ballroom, but outside the box. I’m sure the glass box was not entirely soundproof, but there were very strict requirements around being quiet in the spectator room (thus why no food: you aren’t allowed to crinkle anything) so it was probably pretty quiet in there. For the first thirty minutes of every game, they would allow photos to be taken and then afterwards, they would shoo everyone out to lock away all electronics including phones before they could come back inside. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/singapore_world_chess_championship_day_1_13-Enhanced-NR.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>It’s pretty awesome to watch inside the spectator room. You can immediately feel some of the tension and people on the edge of their seats. The first game was particularly intense. Gukesh started with white pieces (usually an advantage to be able to try to win outright) and Ding had spent a long time on a very early move which was quite unusual because the first moves are usually played memorized. Suddenly in mid-game, Ding started busting out a series of moves that had Gukesh on the backfoot and by the end, people in the audience room were madly whispering various moves to each other to see whether Gukesh could even scrape a draw. He could not. With just seconds on the clock, Ding managed to win outright with black pieces on the first game. The room erupted with applause. I thought about half the room would walk out with a good chunk of their hair missing from all the tense yanking.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/singapore_world_chess_championship_day_1_34-Enhanced-NR.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>We watched a second game as well the following day though this one ended up as a draw and was much less intense than the first one as both players seemed to be pretty ready to draw early on. Even though we only saw two matches live, we continued to keep up with the matches online and two and a half weeks later, Gukesh became the youngest FIDE world champion just eking out a win 7.5 to 6.5. Lots of memes were borne from videos of Ding eating bananas and walnuts and not having ice cream. Both players were easy to root for. Both players graciously acknowledged each other’s strengths and prowesses during interviews. When press conferences would occasionally ask spicy questions, they both answered maturely, sidestepping controversy. It was nice to see Ding play very solidly throughout the game as many had doubted his form after a period of mental struggles and taking a break from chess. Neither Kevin nor I were rooting strongly for one or the other so it was just a really enjoyable championship to watch with some great, intense chess being played. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/singapore_world_chess_championship_day_2_14.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I should remember to seek out more experiences like this in the future. I really loved spending a few weeks diving so deeply into chess and watching some of the best players play. One of my favorite things in the world is talking to anyone who cares so deeply about whatever the context is and there’s so much of that at the top level competitions of anything. It reminds me of watching a cobbler I used to visit in Toronto carefully peering at a pair of fancy shoes I needed to repair and remark how beautiful they were and eagerly advise me on how to take care of them without prompting. He really likes shoes and he was probably the best cobbler in all of Toronto. Or even today when I went to a gym class and the trainer carefully watched me, hawk eyed, to make sure the barbell was exactly perpendicular before I lifted. Even just a few degrees askew and he would quickly jump in to adjust. His love for training and teaching people so easily came through. Watching the best, the most passionate people do what they do is infectious and I suppose as I start hunting for a new job, it’s something I think about quite often as something to aspire for. I’ll find it in good time!</p>

<p>I’ll drop a few photos below of more things we did in Singapore besides eat food and watch chess! We definitely filled our days by visiting gorgeous gardens and museums as well!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/PXL_20241127_082110444.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

We saw this exhibit at the Asian Civilizations Museum. These bowls were excavated from the Tang shipwreck from 830AD. There was some interesting commentary about the method of excavating, including the use of private companies to do the excavation. Interestingly, the commentary at the museum was about how not much would have been done if private companies hadn’t been used (not enough bandwidth) and so a compromise was required.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/PXL_20241127_081834431.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

This vase from the shipwreck is so gorgeous with its crawling coral.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/20241124_183945.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Some classic Chihuly at the Botanical gardens.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/PXL_20241124_114125390.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

These “super trees” are actually quite cool. They have solar panels and also collect rainwater and between the two, help to cool down the nearby conservatories. Also they light up in a cool music-synchronized show in the evenings.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/singapore/20241124_211455.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The famous Marine Bay Sands hotel from the Crazy Rich Asians movie, all lit up at night. It really does look like a giant boat on stilts.

</figcaption>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I procrastinated on writing these blog posts for so long partially due to the photos from Singapore. Over the course of last year, the time I spent on photography and especially post-processing dramatically increased. I was that crazy person trying to squat in weird angles to capture the perfect lighting on the spiky stalagmites in a cramped cave messing with my ISO and aperture settings to try to get the least grainy photo possible while having a shutter speed fast enough that my unsteady hands wouldn’t blur the photo. This meant that I would take tens, if not hundreds of photos in a day and then the process of sorting through them became so overwhelming that I just put it off. Occasionally I would get discouraged altogether because even after I sorted through the photos, I would end up thinking that not a single one captured the wondrousness that I was trying to snapshot forever. I have a great admiration for photographers who do this professionally and create masterpieces that manage to make me feel like I’m right there in the scene they’ve captured, feeling the same emotions that they did.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/singapore/singapore_world_chess_championship_day_1_47-Enhanced-NR.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/singapore/singapore_world_chess_championship_day_1_47-Enhanced-NR.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hong Kong and Macau</title><link href="/hong-kong-and-macau" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hong Kong and Macau" /><published>2024-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/hong-kong-and-macau</id><content type="html" xml:base="/hong-kong-and-macau"><![CDATA[<p>It’s hard to believe but the number of posts remaining on this blog is now down to three, including this one. Or four if I decide to split our time in Tasmania in two. As of the day that I am starting this post, we have ten remaining days of our official “year of travel” which is really hard to believe. But it’s not time to dwell too much on that yet; I’ll save the sobbing for the final post.</p>

<p>We really did a whiplash-like change when we hopped from Mumbai to Bhutan to Hong Kong. City -&gt; rural -&gt; city. After a changeover in Kolkata, we landed in a tiny country (erm, “special administrative region of China”) where English is the main spoken language, I could get a haircut from a hair salon run by British expats, and where we spent an entire day at Disneyland. Perhaps surprisingly, we also ended up doing a good amount of hiking as well, where we proceeded to feel superhuman as we charged up hills at breakneck speed, passing by all the other hikers, because we were now at sea level. It was really fun to magically feel extra strong simply because we went down a few thousand meters in altitude. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/hong-kong-and-macau/20241118_124626.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Gorgeous teapots at the Museum of Tea Ware. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p>Hong Kong definitely had a bit of strangeness to it because of its current tense relationship with China. In many ways, being in Hong Kong felt like we were back in London. Hong Kong used to be a British colony after the Chinese Qing dynasty handed it over as part of losing the First Opium War. It was “returned” to China in 1997 but under the specific governing system of “one country, two systems” whereby Hong Kong would have its own governing system except for foreign and defense related policies. China agreed that that system would remain in effect for a period of fifty years, which is coming to an end in 2047. Hong Kong is just past halfway to that deadline and we got the sense that China is definitely prepared for it with the amount of propaganda we saw throughout the country. For one, almost all the museums in Hong Kong are free because China essentially pays for them so in most museums, we see a large amount of praise and highlighting of specifically <em>mainland Chinese</em> art and history. One museum we went to, hilariously called the Hong Kong Museum of History, had been completely re-curated to be an extensive history on mainland China’s history, how great its innovations had been, highlighting its might in the Olympics (we saw a lot of pride in the country’s performance at international level sports events generally), and most interestingly, how Hong Kong’s protests and riots in 2019 were caused by evil Western influences that corrupted the minds of the young people of Hong Kong. That last exhibit was on a separate level from the others and it was the only exhibit that had no English translation, but Google Translate exists so we were able to read what the panels said. In most museums, China would be referred to as “the Motherland” and throughout the country we saw zero flags, neither the flag of Hong Kong nor the flag of China. It will be interesting to see what happens to Hong Kong in another decade or so and perhaps it’s a good thing that we visited Hong Kong now. My impression of the country was that it was sort of like boiling a frog. The propaganda is obviously there. I can see how China can slowly start imposing their culture, one piece at a time. Even while we were there, China <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/18/world/asia/hong-kong-democrats-sentenced.html">sentenced 45 pro-democracy politicians and activists to prison</a>. China now effectively runs the judicial branch of the Hong Kong government (a consequence of 2019), even though that was one that was supposed to be independent, at least until 2047. Visiting Macau was perhaps a sort of preview of what was to come. Macau was a spotlessly pristine “special administrative region of China” that felt significantly more Chinese than Hong Kong, with far fewer expats, many more people who originated from the mainland, and a very condensed area isolating the previous Portuguese influences.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/hong-kong-and-macau/20241118_201734.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Hong Kong skyline. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p>Beyond the politics of Hong Kong and Macau, we really did have an amazing time in both regions. The museums are really well done and we both loved how interactive the museums were, without overpowering us with too much dense material to read. We visited a gorgeous Museum of Tea Ware where Kevin had to shepherd me through to avoid me buying every teapot and teacup in the gift shop. I drank a lot of green and oolong tea in Hong Kong. There was always at least one bottle in my bag that we drank in lieu of water. Did you know that tea drinking has been a thing for over two thousand years?! I thought I was obsessed with tea, but after reading excerpts of the poetry that Lu Tong wrote about tea, I have realized that there are even stronger attachments to the beverage. “The fourth bowl raises a slight perspiration, and all life’s inequities disperse through my pores.”</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/hong-kong-and-macau/PXL_20241119_061317854.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A huge collection of snuff bottles at the Hong Kong Museum of Art.

</figcaption>

<p>The Palace Museum was also a really beautiful museum with a stunning collection of artifacts, including intricately carved jade and lacquer, beautiful landscape scenes painted on scrolls, calligraphy, painted fans, and even someone’s personal collection of hundreds of snuff bottles that his wife donated to the museum. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/hong-kong-and-macau/PXL_20241119_045517250.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Gorgeous carved red lacquer from China from the Hong Kong Museum of Art.

</figcaption>

<p>Pretty much every meal in Hong Kong was fantastic. We had everything from Indian dosas, to dim sum, to Italian appetizers at the <a href="https://www.theworlds50best.com/bars/asia/list/1-50">best bar in Asia</a> (we had drinks too, which were yummy, but not as good as the ones Albert makes at <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/kb8C9J4faS7i7hVu5">C Suite</a>), to a tasting menu at Mora where the entire menu had some element made from soy imported from Canada. Apparently Canada has the tastiest soy beans in the whole world which we can now attest to because I don’t particularly like soy milk but the pure soy milk they had us taste at the beginning of the meal was genuinely and shockingly amazing. Vegetarian food was plentiful and the vegan ramen we had at a tiny upstairs nook was some of the best ramen I’ve ever had. While we were waiting for our spot at Bar Leone, we hopped over to a tiny Mexican restaurant that was mostly serving out large quantities of beer, but we had some amazing elote and even the plain old chips and salsa took us back to our San Francisco days. Even the food at Hong Kong Disneyland was pretty good which I was not expecting!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/hong-kong-and-macau/PXL_20241120_112221772.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Chrysanthemum soy strands in a mushroom broth at Mora.

</figcaption>

<p>And yes, we spent an entire day at Disneyland. We both had a great time being kids at a themepark and we rode almost every ride in the park over the course of the entire day. We rode our favorite “Runaway Mine Cars” rollercoaster twice. We saw Moana and Lion King mini-shows that were surprisingly good spectacles and the fireworks showering over the Disney castle to cap off our fun day! It was nice to do something quite different from almost every other thing we’ve done this year. A theme park day every now and again is good fun!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/hong-kong-and-macau/PXL_20241121_122510151.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Hong Kong Disneyland!

</figcaption>

<p>After our Disneyland day, we spent the following day in Macau, which is certainly a spectacle in its own right. It’s essentially just the Las Vegas of China with tons of casinos all with different city themes like Paris or London or Venice. The Eiffel Tower in front of the Paris casino is actually a half-scale of the real one in Paris. We didn’t end up spending much time at the casinos besides walking through a couple and eating at one of the restaurants but we did have a phenomenal time at the Giant Panda Pavilion. We watched those pandas rolling around and eating bamboo for <em>ages</em> (see the video below). The pavilion had some other cool animals like lemurs and macaws, but let’s be honest, we were there for the pandas.</p>

<p>Pandas!</p>

<p>After lavishing our meager time in Macau with the pandas, we rushed through the Portuguese area of Macau on the northern part of the island. We visited the Walls of St Paul’s church, where only the façade and some of the foundations are left. We visited a nearby fortress that also had some nice views of the city. It was sort of funny being in an area that had a lot of Portuguese language around, although I’m not sure I heard too much of the language being spoken. It sounded more like an abundance of Chinese due to the high volume of tourists in the area. We took a ferry between Hong Kong and Macau so we had to rush back to the ferry terminal after visiting the fortress to catch our ride back. We had to wear a <em>seatbelt</em> on the ferry which blew my mind. I got really hungry on the boat ride and the boat was swaying around a bit due to some waves, but nothing I couldn’t handle as I waddled over to the bar to try to get something to eat. I promptly got yelled at for not wearing my seatbelt and roaming around the boat and was shooed back into my seat. That’s a first!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/hong-kong-and-macau/PXL_20241122_092445090.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Saint Paul’s church façade in Macau.

</figcaption>

<p>Our last day in Hong Kong was spent heading over to Lantau Island. We had a flight out that evening to Singapore but the airport was also conveniently located on Lantau so we dropped off our stuff at a storage locker in another big mall that was just a few subway stops from the airport. We continued onwards to the Ngong Ping Big Buddha sat serenely on top of a hill, surrounded by monasteries, and is that a cow?! Yep, just a couple cows just wandering around, standing patiently as everyone took photos with them. It almost felt like we were back in Bhutan except the decorations of the monasteries were noticeably more “gold” and there were far fewer people who actually prayed at the temples. We did observe one ritual in progress in one of the rooms where some monks were chanting which was interesting to watch for some time. It was nice showing up to this monastery after visiting Bhutan as we had some knowledge about what we were seeing and acceptable behavior like making sure to always circle the room in a clockwise fashion. As with the Bhutanese monastery insides, we were also not allowed to take photos inside the Hong Kong temples.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/hong-kong-and-macau/20241123_152249.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Big Buddha. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p>Getting to the Big Buddha was quite fun as well. We took a huge gondola ride from the end of the subway line up and over the island’s mountains, past the airport where we watched planes taking off below us to get to the Big Buddha area. Watching the sun drop down below the horizon and see the bottoms of the clouds turn a fiery pink-red was a perfect way to end our time in Hong Kong as we got ferried back past the airport in the other direction. We grabbed our stuff and in not too long, we were inside another metal tube, shooting across the runway we had just watched from above, disappearing into the night sky towards Singapore.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/hong-kong-and-macau/20241123_174950.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Going down the gondola with the airport insight. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s hard to believe but the number of posts remaining on this blog is now down to three, including this one. Or four if I decide to split our time in Tasmania in two. As of the day that I am starting this post, we have ten remaining days of our official “year of travel” which is really hard to believe. But it’s not time to dwell too much on that yet; I’ll save the sobbing for the final post.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/hong-kong-and-macau/PXL_20241118_120221579.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/hong-kong-and-macau/PXL_20241118_120221579.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bhutan</title><link href="/bhutan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bhutan" /><published>2024-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/bhutan</id><content type="html" xml:base="/bhutan"><![CDATA[<p>Among the countries that we’ve visited to date, Bhutan was quite an unusual one. Bhutan is known for publicly saying that they prioritize their country’s “gross national happiness” and prefer to have “high value, low impact” tourism which means that all tourists (except those with an Indian passport) are required to pay a steep daily tariff of one hundred dollars on top of daily fees that cover a guide, driver, food, accommodation, and sightseeing fees. Over the years, the visa price has varied between fifty to two-hundred fifty dollars per day with the government deciding that fifty dollars per day ended up with too many tourists and two-hundred fifty was too steep and curbed tourism too much. I don’t know about any other country in the world that has this kind of tourism congestion pricing and it seems to be something the people of the country are proud of and also desire to keep long term. Because of this model of tourism, one thing that was sort of nice about planning for Bhutan is that the extent of planning on our end was very little; all we needed to do was message a few companies that are accredited by the Bhutan government for ten-day itineraries and pick which one we liked best. We decided to split our time in Bhutan into two parts: one part to visit more cultural aspects of the country and the other to do a trek in the Bhutanese Himalayas. It was nice to have a bit of a break from planning and be able to not worry about opening times of points of interest or where to eat or where to stay during our visit. Occasionally it’s nice to have everything just sorted out, even though we both like to explore things on our own generally.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_8.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Tiger’s Nest Monastery, tucked into the mountains. It’s quite a steep trek to get here and both the inside and outside of the monastery are beautiful and intricately designed. Unfortunately we have no pictures from the inside of any monastery because it is not permitted to take photos inside any religious areas.

</figcaption>

<p>The Bhutanese Himalayas were the real draw for us to spend some time in the country. I had also previously seen some pictures of the gorgeous Buddhist monasteries tucked away in the mountain nooks and crannies that I was also eager to see. The tricky thing about trekking in the Bhutanese Himalayas is that the window for clear weather is fairly small, either between October and November or in early spring; during this small window, one has a high chance of viewing the tips of the peaks that tower more than six or seven thousand meters. Other times of the year, the summits of those mountains are typically shrouded in cloud cover, as was true during my last visit to Nepal. However, those windows also pose a challenge because the temperature can be quite cold as it transitions to or from winter with chances of snowfall that can make hiking difficult. We originally wanted to do the Jomolhari trek that would take us to the base of Jomolhari mountain (which rises to 7300+ meters) but a few companies dissuaded us from doing the trek because it could start snowing in mid November which would shut down the mountain passes and force us to turn back. Ultimately we did the Druk Path trek instead of Jomolhari over five days and four nights. While the trek was overall quite easy for us, the nights were very cold, dropping around -5 to -10 degrees (celcius) and we didn’t have very good quality sleeping bags (we had to borrow the company’s) so sleeping was rough at night and because of that, I’m glad we didn’t end up doing the Jomolhari trek since it would have been even colder. One day, I’d love to return to do the Jomolhari trek, this time with my own sleeping bag and better winter clothes. Bhutan has the highest mountains in the world that are still unclimbed because the Bhutanese believe that the summits are where the gods live and intruding on their homes would unleash bad things upon the country. That said, I found it hilarious that they don’t bother to name any peaks that are in the six thousand meter range – there are simply too many of them and aren’t special enough to warrant a specific name! Seven thousands get names. Comparatively, the famed Kilimanjaro is not even six thousand meters!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/PXL_20241115_062745095.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

We got a stunning view of Kangchenjunga above the clouds on the way out of Bhutan, flying from Paro to Kolkata. Kangchenjunga is the third tallest mountain in the world (after Everest and K2) and towers at more than 8500 meters.

</figcaption>

<p>Flying to Bhutan is a special experience. We flew from Delhi to Paro which flies right over Everest but unfortunately it was cloudy so we didn’t get a view. Our agency specially booked us seats on the left side of the plane which usually allows for a view if the weather is clear. Alas! We’ve resolved to hike Everest Base Camp sometime within the next few years so we’ll have our chance to see her soon enough. Flying in the area in general is always a special experience: I remember my first flight over the Himalayas when I flew to Kathmandu and the pilot at that time also came on the intercom to let us know when we were flying over Everest. I don’t think I saw it at that time either but I can’t remember the reason why. Besides flying over the tallest mountains in the world, landing into Paro is quite the adventure. Apparently there are fewer than fifty pilots in the world that are trained to fly in and out of Paro as the city is tucked in a valley with tall mountains literally flanking all sides. This flight is the first time that a pilot has come on the intercom to warn passengers that if you look out the window, it will feel like we are very (read: too) close to the mountain tops but don’t worry, that’s just how you land into Paro. The circuit pattern to land is very similar to the one I learned in flight training but the difference is that you need to aim each leg of the circuit to cross over a saddle point in a mountain ridge line, each one progressively lower than the last until you drop the last of your altitude on the final leg. Each leg requires dropping significant amounts of altitude and each turn, after crossing the saddle point, is very sharp/steep. I also learned that Paro Airport operates with no radar so all the pilots land using VFR (visual flight rules) meaning that they are navigating using landmarks and their own visual assessment of the terrain. The runway is also shorter than normal so it was quite impressive to feel the pilot expertly and <em>gently</em> set the bird down when they have to take into account a higher descent rate and not being able to see the runway until crossing the last mountain ridge and doing all this without any radar assistance. It’s impressive flying. Our first couple nights in Paro were spent at a hotel that was nestled into the mountains right above one of the long ends of the runway so I had a great time watching flights land and take off.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_49.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Paro.

</figcaption>

<p>We really started with a bang in Bhutan. Because our flight got delayed into Paro, we weren’t able to visit the Paro Dzong (a “dzong” is a fortress) or the National Museum as planned after we arrived. Our guide Sangay and driver Jigme met us at the airport and took us for an evening coffee. We retired to our lodging pretty much right afterwards. However the next day, we squeezed in a hike to the famous Tiger’s Nest Monastery, the museum, the fortress, a hot stone bath (very welcome after all the other activities) and a farmhouse dinner all in one day. The Tiger’s Nest Monastery hike was easily the highlight of the day; the hike winds spectacularly through the mountains until you reach the last steep set of the stairs to the monastery which sits on the cliff like a port-a-ledge. Pretty much all the monasteries in Bhutan are active, even one as popular as Tiger’s Nest which all the tourists visit, though I believe more of the rituals happen during the mornings and evenings when visitors aren’t there. We have no pictures of the idols and murals that are inside the monastery because across the country, there is a rule: “no shoes, no photos.” That is, if you’re entering a sacred religious area of the temple and need to remove your shoes, then you cannot take a photo. The insides of the temples are really something though. Usually a monastery has several rooms, each as its own “temple.” In the center will be one large idol, often covered in gold, flanked by several other idols. The idols are typically adorned in vibrant colors of cloth and in front, will be lamps filled with ghee, money that people have stashed in the nooks as a donation, and other religious objects like wax sculptures, food offerings and stupas. The structures are usually wood (and yes, this means many a monastery have been burned down by the ghee fueled flames, including Tiger’s Nest) and the interior is usually as ornate, sometimes even more so, carved and painted as the exterior of the building. The ceilings are draped with more colorful, embroidered cloths and the walls are usually covered in either detailed paintings that represent various stories or beliefs about Buddhism or tiny idols of either Bodhisattvas (these are humans that have become “enlightened” but have chosen to stay within the human “realm” or lifecycle rather than escaping infinite reincarnation as they’ve earned) or Buddha himself. Sangay was really quite knowledgeable and passionate about explaining various parts of Buddhism, but I’ll be honest, a lot of it escaped mine and Kevin’s understanding. Kevin at one point tried to read the Buddhism Wikipedia article to try to understand a bit better all the symbolism in the monasteries but it quickly went into the deep end and with so many variations and interpretations, it was a bit challenging to understand everything. We asked Sangay about these different variations at one point and he said something that made sense. He said Buddhism’s ultimate goal is simple, which is “eternal peace” or <em>Nirvana</em>. The variations are simply different sets of instructions or paths on how to get there.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_46.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Inside the Paro Rinpung Dzong (fortress).

</figcaption>

<p>We have lots of photos of the exteriors of the many monasteries we visited though. Every single one was beautifully decorated and covered in symbolic art and typically strung with prayer flags around the property and the path to get there. Almost always, getting to the monastery required a bit of a trek to get there. We visited one in the village of Sopsokha after our trek that was out of the ordinary because it was one that was built by the “Divine Madman;” a monk who shunned the typical modest way of living by monks and instead used outrageous and unconventional behavior to demonstrate to the common people that the path to “enlightenment” need not be the same for all. He also apparently “subdued evils” using the phallus because the phallus represents “the flaming thunderbolt of wisdom” (I have made a choice here to remain in ignorance and not figure out what on earth this means) and now the entire town is filled with shops that sell phalluses. The outside of buildings are also commonly painted with phalluses with varying levels of luridity. His temple is well known in Bhutan as a place to receive a fertility blessing and there’s a cute scrapbook inside the temple with all sorts of pictures and notes from parents who prayed at the temple and were blessed with a child. It took me a while to notice, but hanging on the rearview mirror of our driver’s car was also a tiny phallus. It’s quite a common artifact to have in Bhutanese homes as a way to ward off evil, like hanging chilies in the doorway (common in India but also other parts of Southeast Asia and the Mediterranean).</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/PXL_20241112_084047954.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Phalluses for sale near the Divine Madman’s monastery, Chhimi Lhakhang.

</figcaption>

<p>About half of our time in Bhutan was spent on the trek though. We started the trek in Paro and ended in Thimphu, which is the capital and largest city of Bhutan. We met our entourage on our first day which included a lunch boy, a horseman, a cook, and six mules. Plus Kevin, myself, and Sangay. About a kilometer or two into the first day of the hike, we passed by a fancy five-star hotel that was under construction and there, we met a cute white and beige stray dog. The dog started following us and we figured that he would probably turn back after a half hour or so. Nope. I kid you not, this stray dog stayed with us for the <em>entire fifty five kilometers all the way to Thimphu</em> and decided to act as our guard dog for our camp. I still wonder what happened to him afterwards. Did he perhaps find another trekking group going in the opposite direction back to Paro? Is he just hanging out in Thimphu now? Kevin and I started calling him “Squiggles” or “Squigs” for short. The Bhutanese crew called him “Katu” which means “white” in Bhutanese because of the color of his coat. He brought a lot of joy to us all and would wait patiently every morning and evening until after we all ate to eat all the leftover food. Sometimes, if I didn’t like something much (there were some egg pancakes that I couldn’t manage for breakfast one day), I would sneak him food under the table. He was such a joy; he loved leaping onto Kevin, would run to our tent and wag his tail vigorously and clamor onto us when we emerged from the tent in the mornings (as long as he wasn’t out on his guarding duties) and just generally was a very happy doggo. He would usually trek with the horseman and his horses though often go off on his own adventures, adding on more mileage than any of us. He didn’t like the camp fires much, though would sit close to us occasionally if we were seated far enough away from a roaring hot fire. He didn’t like other dogs as well, scaring off any dog that dared to approach us even from many meters away. Squigs definitely made the trek special for us all.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/PXL_20241110_021748946.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A first person view of Squigs jumping on Kevin one morning. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/20241109_151233.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Sleepy Squiggles. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p>Oh look who it is catching up on the trail!</p>

<p>The trek itself was really wonderful. We passed through beautiful forests and even on the first day, started getting views of the snow-capped mountains that Bhutan is known for. We saw Jomolhari from afar almost daily. Days three and four were especially spectacular. On day three, we were about to get to our camp super early so we decided to do a little extra hike up to the top of a nearby mountain that was only maybe one hundred meters or so further up. There wasn’t really a trail so we bushwhacked our way up, scrambling up some of the rocks, testing out the solidity with our hiking poles and carefully stepping to avoid any hidden holes. The views were really amazing and Sangay looked back at us and pointed to another peak further ahead and said, “one more?” So we climbed up one more peak and this was even more beautiful with us being able to see over the other side of the ridge to another lake that Sangay had never seen before. There was a tiny semi-permanent tent as well where a shepherd must be living, tucked in the valley of some very tall mountains. There were some plants that we were bushwhacking that Sangay mentioned not to touch too much because the smell can sometimes induce altitude sickness/vomiting but but the end of our bonus climb and descent, we had definitely touched it plenty and also gotten quite a bit higher in altitude so I was very happy that no altitude sickness kicked in. Ooh, there were some thorny plants that definitely gave us a few scratches and pierced through our pants though – oww! With our additional climbs, we ended up at camp at a respectable four o’clock which gave us enough time to do a quite wet wipe “bath,” change into our camp clothes and get warmed up by the fire. Staying in valleys meant that we were shielded by the winds but it also meant that the sun set very early over the tops of the mountains and also rose pretty late. Each morning, we would wake up to a white sheet of frost across everything, including Squiggles. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/20241107_140700.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The view of Jomolhari near our campsite on our first day.

</figcaption>

<p>Day four is when we reached the peak of our hike. We passed through our highest pass of our trek around 4300 meters and had some beautiful views of the tallest mountain in Bhutan: Gangkar Puensam. The weather wasn’t as clear as some of the previous days, but we were definitely able to see the expanse of snow-capped mountains across the horizon from the pass. Sometimes it takes a moment for my eyes to distinguish between what’s a cloud and what’s the top of a mountain – they’re all at the same height! I really enjoyed watching the colorful prayer flags that were strung across all the mountain passes flap around in the wind, but this one definitely had a lot more flags and structures constructed from the flags. It was clear that we had reached the highest point of the trek. It’s funny how easily we ran out of breath during ascents on this trek; even a small climb had me panting in just a couple minutes so I would try to take it slowly and at a constant pace. I remember one of the first treks we did in Hong Kong (the next place we went after Bhutan) at nearly sea level and both Kevin and I were lapping the other hikers, nearly sprinting up steps to the top of the hike. It felt like we had superpowers at sea level and like I was completely out of shape for the Druk Path. In reality, Kevin and I apparently completed the trek in the quickest amount of time that Sangay had done with clients and we took both him and our travel agent by surprise by how quickly we finished hikes. Based on the other clientele we met, it seemed like the average age was quite a bit older than us and very few did trekking. Sangay was in fact, the only trekking guide that the travel agency employed and all others were just cultural guides. I guess trekking isn’t very common even though the Himalayas on the Bhutanese side are also stunning and even more untouched than the Nepalese Himalayas. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_141.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Kevin and Sangay trying to figure out a path through the bushes.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_158.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Kevin on a ledge!

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_182.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Bhutanese Himalayas, from the last mountain pass on our fourth day.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_203.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A stupa, along the Druk Path trail.

</figcaption>

<p>Camp locations were often quite unique. Our first night, we camped close to a monastery that looked pretty empty, but I was told it still was active. It was perched on top of a hill with a view of Jomolhari and Kevin managed to find a small ledge just below the “summit” that was shielded from the wind where we shared a beer and watched the sunset. Our second night was spent on a yak farm and we met a lovely English lady who was also hiking the Druk Path and camping in the same place for the evening. The whole area was full of yaks which seemed to get along fine with our mules but we did have to be careful where we stepped as there was yak and horse poo everywhere. While I was napping in the tent, Kevin and the English lady were chatting when one of the yaks decided to try to scare them and started charging towards them before stopping. Then it ran a bit closer and stopped again. They figured it was time to get out of there at that point so Kevin returned back to our tent. We were careful to keep a large distance between ourselves and that yak afterwards; I think it was a female yak that had babies which would explain that behavior. It was definitely a unique experience to camp there and watch the yak herder milk the yaks in the morning. Yak milk is not very commonly drunk in Bhutanese because it is expensive but people believe that yak milk is medicinal because the yak’s primary diet is mountain herbs so if you’re ill, people will either drink yak milk then or chew on some dried yak cheese. Kevin and I tried some dried yak cheese when we later visited a market in Thimphu and I felt like I nearly dislocated my jaw trying to chew on the yak cheese. I need to work my jaw muscles!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_80.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Our horses getting fed in the morning.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_97.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Our tents erected in yak territory.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_152.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

This lake was our campsite for the third night.

</figcaption>

<p>We were extremely pampered with amazing food throughout the trek (and also throughout the trip in general). On the trek, typically we would have cereal and something hot for breakfast along with milk and tea. The something hot would sometimes be toast or eggy toast or scrambled eggs or eggy pancakes (we obviously had some extra eggs in our food supply by the end of our trek). Lunch would be a luxurious meal set of rice, two vegetable dishes, and a meat dish for the carnivores. Dinner would be rice, three vegetables dishes and usually a meat dish or a fourth vegetable dish. One of our favorite dishes was called <em>datshi</em> which was a vegetable (often mushrooms) in a cheesy white sauce with shredded chilis. Bhutanese people usually eat rice for all three meals but thankfully we did not have to eat rice for breakfast which would have been a bit too much rice for us. All the meals were served with lots of tea; in Bhutan, people drink plain black tea though very lightly brewed. We ended up switching to just drinking hot water in the evenings to give us our best chance of sleeping at night.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_144.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

We passed by this old wall in the mountains where some monk used to sit and meditate for a long time.

</figcaption>

<p>Our third night was spent near a very still lake that had a perfect reflection of the surrounding mountains and whose edges were lined with perfectly flat stones. Kevin did some of his best stone skipping here with the perfect stones and lake. We saw some other folks camping on the other side of the lake that Sangay told us were likely some local students. We didn’t see them at all on our walk so they probably came from Thimphu and were going towards Paro, so trekking in the opposite direction as us. From night two onwards, we had huge fires going in our camp; making campfires is technically illegal in the Bhutanese parks but the cold pretty much forces everyone to make fires. I’m not sure how it’s possible to have such a law in place, especially since there are shepherds and herders who live in semi-permanent tents in the area who probably need the fires to stay warm. In any case, this particular night, Sangay made sure that the folks on the opposite side were not rangers and once confirmed, made the fire. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_136.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The views!!

</figcaption>

<p>Our last night of the trek was quite eventful. We arrived at our camp and Sangay went to work chopping down a <em>huge</em> amount of firewood to build the biggest bonfire yet. As we were sitting by the fire, and the last of the light started to fade, we saw a tiny light up in the mountain, continuing along what looked like the trail to Thimphu. Sangay was a bit worried that the light might be from the students we saw earlier across the lake on the previous night and that they were trying to reach Thimphu within the same evening which was still another ten to twelve kilometers away. He said that it wasn’t uncommon that students would try to do the trek underprepared without proper equipment or even headlamps, instead using a cell phone to light the way. We watched as the light disappeared and reappeared and Sangay whistled loudly to attract attention. The huge bonfire as well hopefully acted as a beacon in case they were in trouble. But eventually the light disappeared for good and the next day, Sangay speculated that it could have been some local shepherd who sells some of the mountain herbs in Thimphu who definitely know their way around. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/20241109_063346.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The first speck of sunlight during sunrise. Look at the clouds settled below us in the valley!

</figcaption>

<p>After we finished up dinner, as we were huddling around the fire, our horseman went to go and grab his horses who were roaming around on the property and tie them up for the night. Sangay told us that usually, once a horse is done grazing, his instinct will be to start walking back home (towards Paro) and if they aren’t tied close by, by morning, there will be zero horses left. There was another horse herder nearby who lived in a semi-permanent tent close to where we were camping who was doing the same and counting his horses. We realized that there was some commotion going on and our camp staff all started roaming around the area with strong flashlights: one of the horses was missing. At the time, we thought it was one of our horses, but later on we found out it was the local herder’s horse. After some time, they found the horse laying sideways in the creek that was between our camp and the herder’s dwellings. The horse had been in a tussle with a loose yak that we had earlier seen roaming around close to where we had started our descent into our camping area. The yak belonged to a herder who actually hadn’t arrived in the area yet. They were scheduled to arrive within the next couple days and had left some material for the semi-permanent tent that would be set up but I guess one yak got there early. The horse had been on the losing side and had been stabbed in the belly by the yak’s horns. Our staff tried to help and hold down the horse while his owner tried to push the organs that were now on the outside of the horse back in and stitch it up but the extent of damage was too much. It was really traumatic to see (the trekking staff had nerves of steel as they tried as hard as they could to help) and I was heartbroken when we saw him try to cross the creek to be with the other horses who had been rounded up for the night. Horrible, horrible. It was really impossible to save the horse because of how much distance there was to the city where there was a vet and also the extreme nature of the injury. We were nervous about Katu overnight (he is a dog after all) but after sniffing the horse, he came back to our camp, got some stern words in Bhutanese from the trekking staff, and sat down and didn’t leave our camp all night.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_118.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A close up of Jomolhari that I took with my zoom lens. We would love to do the Jomolhari base camp trek one day!

</figcaption>

<p>A few yaks passing by us on the trail.</p>

<p>As we made our final descent into Thimphu, we started seeing signs of civilization again. We passed by a very isolated monastery that had signs around to please trek quietly. This monastery is where people who wish to become monks spend three years, three months, and three days meditating. They don’t leave the property at all during this time and are completely cut off from the rest of the world. We were taking quite a speedy pace down the hill, gaining superpowers as the oxygen increased and Sangay had to call Jigme three times, each time to give him an earlier estimated arrival time. It was really nice to be greeted by not only Jigme, but also the English lady that we had met at the start of the trek since we had slightly different campsites for the latter half of the trek. We all celebrated with wine and beer and Sangay arranged a stunning lunch for us that was the best meal of our trip: tempura mushrooms, paneer masala, chicken, fish, the best chili cheese, and tons more. We ate, took extremely long hot showers, and napped and enjoyed chilling out in a beautiful room because we got upgraded to a lovely four star hotel that was actually owned by our travel agency. I don’t think we realized how pooped we were from not sleeping very well in the cold. We slept very well this and every subsequent night of our time in Bhutan. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_86.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Hiking through some prayer flag areas. The tall white ones are erected in memory of someone who has passed away.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/bhutan/bhutan_168.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

More beautiful high alpine lakes.

</figcaption>

<p>After our trek, we had three days remaining in Bhutan. We spent two of the days in Punakha and the surrounding areas. We visited a mountain pass by car that unfortunately was fully clouded, but the view was very pretty from the top of a monastery nearby regardless. We visited the Divine Madman’s monastery that I mentioned earlier, a nunnery for female monks, another fortress, a lovely long suspension bridge crossing over a turquoise river fed by the melting snow of a nearby glacier, and a third monastery that passed through a field of rice paddies that were being cleaned up for the season. Our last day was a whirlwind in Thimphu. We were outfitted with traditional Bhutanese dresses in the morning; for me a <em>kira</em> that consisted of a blouse and skirt with the blouse sleeves folded up to represent hospitality and compassion. Kevin was outfitted in a <em>gho</em> which was a single piece that normally would be worn pantless with tall socks but Kevin wore jeans underneath. The comfort of the dresses wasn’t too bad actually, though I couldn’t take long strides so after visiting the largest sitting Buddha in the world in the morning, we took them off. We spent the remainder of the day visiting other small sights including an art school, a takin reserve (the takin in the national animal of Bhutan), an archery match, a farmer’s market, and watched the flag lowering at the Tashichho Dzong which is the sort of “White House” of Bhutan where the king does his work and where the Chief Abbot lives. The archery match was especially really entertaining to watch. The targets are set 150 meters away (in contrast, the Olympic target is set 70 meters away) which means that the archers frequently miss, but when they do hit the target, the entire team performs a dance. The teams would constantly be shouting at each other and waving the flags next to the target to point out the target. 150 meters is a lot! I could barely keep my eyes focused on the arrow as it flew through the air. Kevin and I had some fun trying out archery after our hot stone bath early on in the trip but the target was way closer. Sangay told us that the competition we were watching was some sort of national event between teams from the different villages and towns of Bhutan and one of the teams came from his village out in east Bhutan. Archery is the national sport of Bhutan and he said that pretty much all the men learn to do some archery at some point in their childhood.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_225.jpg" alt="108 stupas at Dochula Pass." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_225.jpg" alt="108 stupas at Dochula Pass." /></p>

<p>108 stupas at Dochula Pass.</p>

<p>Dochula Pass is a mountain pass that is driven over between Thimphu and Punakha cities.</p>

<p><img src="images/20241112_111124.jpg" alt="A Tibitan Mastiff, napping in front of a monastery." /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241112_111124.jpg" alt="A Tibitan Mastiff, napping in front of a monastery." /></p>

<p>A Tibitan Mastiff, napping in front of a monastery.</p>

<p><img src="images/20241113_130416.jpg" alt="View of Punakha Dzong." /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241113_130416.jpg" alt="View of Punakha Dzong." /></p>

<p>View of Punakha Dzong.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_282.jpg" alt="The exterior of one of the monasteries we visited." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_282.jpg" alt="The exterior of one of the monasteries we visited." /></p>

<p>The exterior of one of the monasteries we visited.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_265.jpg" alt="River that runs through Punakha." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_265.jpg" alt="River that runs through Punakha." /></p>

<p>River that runs through Punakha.</p>

<p>The water is turquoise due to the water coming from the glaciers in the mountains, similar to Patagonia.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_263.jpg" alt="A random store." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_263.jpg" alt="A random store." /></p>

<p>A random store.</p>

<p>Even the stores are intricately designed and painted! There’s an art school we visited in Thimphu where our guide’s brother even works and most of the artists that graduate have good job prospects in the country.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_245.jpg" alt="Paddy fields in Thimphu, getting cleaned up." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_245.jpg" alt="Paddy fields in Thimphu, getting cleaned up." /></p>

<p>Paddy fields in Thimphu, getting cleaned up.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_330.jpg" alt="Takins!" /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_330.jpg" alt="Takins!" /></p>

<p>Takins!</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_375.jpg" alt="Carrying the flag down after lowering." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_375.jpg" alt="Carrying the flag down after lowering." /></p>

<p>Carrying the flag down after lowering.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_374.jpg" alt="Flag lowering ceremony." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_374.jpg" alt="Flag lowering ceremony." /></p>

<p>Flag lowering ceremony.</p>

<p>These two musicians had really cool outfits and were playing a long wind instrument as part of the flag lowering ceremony.</p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241114_034400202%7E2.jpg" alt="All dressed up!" /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241114_034400202%7E2.jpg" alt="All dressed up!" /></p>

<p>All dressed up!</p>

<p>Sangay is on the left and Jigme is on the right. And behind us is the photo of the royal family that you can find in almost every single institution in Bhutan.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_376.jpg" alt="Tashichhoe Dzong" /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_376.jpg" alt="Tashichhoe Dzong" /></p>

<p>Tashichhoe Dzong</p>

<p>This is where the King, the Chief Abbot, and government officials conduct their work. The Chief Abbot also lives here.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_390.jpg" alt="Tashichhoe Dzong at night" /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_390.jpg" alt="Tashichhoe Dzong at night" /></p>

<p>Tashichhoe Dzong at night</p>

<p><img src="images/20241114_112203.jpg" alt="Students learning to slate carve." /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241114_112203.jpg" alt="Students learning to slate carve." /></p>

<p>Students learning to slate carve.</p>

<p><img src="images/20241114_141220.jpg" alt="Dried yak and cow milk cheese." /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241114_141220.jpg" alt="Dried yak and cow milk cheese." /></p>

<p>Dried yak and cow milk cheese.</p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_225.jpg" alt="108 stupas at Dochula Pass." /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241112_111124.jpg" alt="A Tibitan Mastiff, napping in front of a monastery." /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241113_130416.jpg" alt="View of Punakha Dzong." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_282.jpg" alt="The exterior of one of the monasteries we visited." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_265.jpg" alt="River that runs through Punakha." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_263.jpg" alt="A random store." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_245.jpg" alt="Paddy fields in Thimphu, getting cleaned up." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_330.jpg" alt="Takins!" /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_375.jpg" alt="Carrying the flag down after lowering." /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_374.jpg" alt="Flag lowering ceremony." /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241114_034400202%7E2.jpg" alt="All dressed up!" /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_376.jpg" alt="Tashichhoe Dzong" /></p>

<p><img src="images/bhutan_390.jpg" alt="Tashichhoe Dzong at night" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241114_112203.jpg" alt="Students learning to slate carve." /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241114_141220.jpg" alt="Dried yak and cow milk cheese." /></p>

<p>Bhutan is the only country in the world that has not a single traffic light. We were amused by this traffic police regulating traffic in an intricately designed pavilion.</p>

<p>The flag lowering ceremony was also fun. This was the last thing we did in Bhutan. The actual area where the flag is lowered is closed off so tourists get to the fence surrounding the area very early to get a good spot to spy through the bushes. Sangay was quite the expert in getting us there at a good time and finding us a nice place. After the flag lowering ceremony is completed, the dzong opens up for a short period of time each day to tourists but the guides need to register each person first. As the ceremony finished, I found it amusing how all the guides started sprinting towards the registration office so that they could register first. We made our way to the entrance and soon enough, Sangay called our names to wave us into the dzong where we visited another monastery that is more frequently used by government officials and the Chief Abbot. Bhutan has an interesting split leadership at the top in having both a king and a chief abbot. The king is ultimately responsible for the more secular and political side of the leadership responsibilities while the abbot takes on the religious. The current king and his dad appear to be quite well loved in Bhutan and while we were there, the country celebrated the king’s father’s 69th birthday which was a day off for everyone. It was really interesting to see many of the Bhutanese people wear pins in commemoration of the birthday with the king’s dad’s face on it. The current king is known for trying to turn Bhutan into more of a democracy. Sangay said that so far, they’ve had the ability to vote four times after the king decided that members of the National Assembly (their parliament) should be voted in by the public every five years. So in 2008, Bhutan held their first elections. The current king is also working on a new project to create a “megacity” in the south of Bhutan called <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/duncanmadden/2024/01/30/land-of-the-thunder-dragon-bhutan-announces-new-mindfulness-megacity/">Gelephu</a>. It’s going to have the second international airport that won’t require special training to land and take-off (so that wealthy business folks can more easily conduct business in Bhutan) and new railways to connect the city with the rest of the country. It sounds really ambitious and the work has already started so it’ll be interesting to see if Bhutan manages to pull it off. Sangay said that the king is currently spending a bunch of his time trying to make sure they raise enough funds to complete the project. For me, it’s really interesting to see how Bhutan handles their sometimes opposing desires to modernize and also retain their traditional culture. Bhutan will certainly become a really interesting place to visit again in another ten plus years, especially after their new city is constructed. Their culture is very beautiful and their country is really lovely to visit!</p>

<p>Dancing and singing after their teammate hit the target!</p>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Among the countries that we’ve visited to date, Bhutan was quite an unusual one. Bhutan is known for publicly saying that they prioritize their country’s “gross national happiness” and prefer to have “high value, low impact” tourism which means that all tourists (except those with an Indian passport) are required to pay a steep daily tariff of one hundred dollars on top of daily fees that cover a guide, driver, food, accommodation, and sightseeing fees. Over the years, the visa price has varied between fifty to two-hundred fifty dollars per day with the government deciding that fifty dollars per day ended up with too many tourists and two-hundred fifty was too steep and curbed tourism too much. I don’t know about any other country in the world that has this kind of tourism congestion pricing and it seems to be something the people of the country are proud of and also desire to keep long term. Because of this model of tourism, one thing that was sort of nice about planning for Bhutan is that the extent of planning on our end was very little; all we needed to do was message a few companies that are accredited by the Bhutan government for ten-day itineraries and pick which one we liked best. We decided to split our time in Bhutan into two parts: one part to visit more cultural aspects of the country and the other to do a trek in the Bhutanese Himalayas. It was nice to have a bit of a break from planning and be able to not worry about opening times of points of interest or where to eat or where to stay during our visit. Occasionally it’s nice to have everything just sorted out, even though we both like to explore things on our own generally.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/bhutan/bhutan_8.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/bhutan/bhutan_8.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Diwali and Dosas in Mumbai</title><link href="/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diwali and Dosas in Mumbai" /><published>2024-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai</id><content type="html" xml:base="/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai"><![CDATA[<p>Diwali is my favorite holiday. As a kid, I remember going to Phantom Fireworks in Ohio around the time of the fourth of July and purchasing extra sparklers and flower pots and fountains that were on sale (sadly, no aerials) and stashing them in our basement until October or November to light them for Diwali. As I got older, Phantom Fireworks picked up on the fact that there were a good number of Diwali celebraters in Ohio and started doing special Diwali sales in the fall as well so hoarding became less required. It was always a special time of the year, lighting up the driveway with rows of candles, setting off our stash with friends and family, eating delicious, special meals, and doning new outfits.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/PXL_20241031_110828704.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Shopping craziness in Mumbai before Diwali.

</figcaption>

<p>However, I have never celebrated Diwali in India. I’d heard stories from my parents about how crazy it used to be for them. A bit more unabashedly outrageously noisy and celebratory because you don’t need to be afraid of having the neighbors call the cops on you. You <em>do</em> need to be afraid of losing fingers and/or toes with rogue fireworks. At least that is what I heard from mom and dad. This year, as we finished our travel in Jordan and were looking at flights to Bhutan, I noticed that we would almost definitely need to fly through India. And it was about to be Diwali. So I enthusiastically declared that we would go and see the party for ourselves.</p>

<p>Traveling to India is always slightly stressful for me. Especially when I was younger, there were certain expectations around how to dress or behave to adapt to the environment which isn’t unusual for the world (e.g. wearing longer pants in Jordan) but somehow, with India, I felt like I should be able to be who I am without any modifications. Of course, that’s irrational. Culture takes a long time to change. I’m Indian but not really Indian. There’s a name used for people like me; I’m an ABCD. American Born Confused Desi. So now, either my visits to India are very short (my last trip to India was two years ago for about 72 hours) or I just accept that I might get some ogling because of my American brashness and “scandalous” outfits. Or both. So it goes. I like shorts more than pants which I like way more than skirts and dresses.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/20241030_123630.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Digging into dosas and idlis and “cutting chai” on our first full day. “Cutting chai” is half cups of chai (“cut” in half) so that one can drink more in a day.

</figcaption>

<p>I had heard that Mumbai was a bit different though. As the largest city in India and a hub for businesses (both international and domestic), I had heard that the people of Mumbai (“Mumbaikars”) have quite a different attitude and are a bit more progressive than other parts of India. I’ve never been to Mumbai so I was quite intrigued by this. Those rumors were not wrong. After arriving at Mumbai airport, I stared in confusion as not a single person chased after us to offer us a very expensive taxi to our hotel. We literally stood around for a second wondering where the hawkers were until we just simply ordered an Uber, went to the designated parking lot, and got in.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/mumbai_14.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Gorgeous stone reliefs at the Elephanta Caves. We took a ferry from Mumbai to get to the island with all the carved caves dating back to the 6th century.

</figcaption>

<p>The next day as we left our hotel, one man started talking to us as we were waiting to cross a street. I braced myself thinking that either a) he was going to eventually try to talk us into hiring him or a cousin or some other relation for the day for tourism or b) eventually was going to ask to take a picture with Kevin. Nope. He just told us that the street we were on was a great place for Diwali celebrations and that there was a big cricket match between India and New Zealand happening and wished us a good time in Mumbai. That’s it. What’s this hospitality?! It made me really happy to have this kind of experience in Mumbai. And just generally, our time in Mumbai was like this. No one bothered us. We only had our photo taken (with folks asking permission!) just a handful of times and we even used public transportation (buses and trains!) to get around which in many other parts of India would be a total no-no. I loved taking the trains. We would stand right next to the open doors and have the wind from the moving train cool us down since it was very hot and humid outside.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/20241031_160553.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Tons of black kites and other birds whirling around close to sunset on Marine Drive.

</figcaption>

<p>We really enjoyed our time in Mumbai beyond the Diwali celebrations. We both ate really well three times a day, indulging in <em>dosas</em>, <em>idlis</em>, <em>chole bhature</em> (Kevin’s favorite), <em>paneer parathas</em> (the paneer was SO soft and yummy!), the Spicy McPaneer at McDonald’s (I eat this without fail every time I visit India), Mumbai’s famous chaats including <em>pav bhaji</em>, <em>vada pav</em>, and <em>pani puri</em>. At one of the places we ate called Swati’s Snacks, one of the managers suggested that we try a Gujarati dish called <em>panki chatni</em> which is a rice pancake steamed in a banana leaf. We decided not to order it because we wanted to dig into other chaats but the owner came out with a pancake and insisted we try it on the house. He was right; it was unbelievably good. </p>

<p>We started out a little cautious with the water situation (on Kevin’s last visit to India, we all came down with Delhi Belly at the very end of our vacation) and avoided chutneys which could be made with tap water but became a bit more adventurous as time went on. We found out later that Mumbai is one of the only cities in all of India that supposedly has drinkable tap water (except during monsoon season). We weren’t so adventurous to drink it by the liter even after we found out but chutneys seemed to suit our stomachs just fine and we drank tap water at some restaurants without any issues. We also indulged in an exquisite meal at a fine dining restaurant called Masque. I cannot recommend it enough. All ten courses were incredibly inventive and delicious and I really believe that if Michelin decides to come to India at some point, this restaurant is getting at least one, maybe even two stars. Some of the dishes were Eleven Madison Park worthy. I’ve never eaten drumstick at a fancy restaurant before and I loved that all the dishes had distinctly Indian vibes with a story behind the ingredients sourced. We had the opportunity to visit the kitchen which was super cool and also much less chaotic than I imagined. We’re definitely coming to Masque again if we visit Mumbai again. Which I hope we will!</p>

<p>Mumbai also has some really beautiful museums and a vibrant art scene that was really fun to explore. The Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Vastu Sangrahalaya (even for me, that’s a mouthful) history museum is housed in a beautiful complex with many rooms packed with ancient sculptures, textiles, coins, and even an old snakes-and-ladders board from the 16th century. We were amused by some 12-13th century stone tablets in surprisingly good condition that had some pretty raunchy poems etched in. One poet wrote his poem in six different dialects so that everyone could read exactly how he felt about a particular woman who made “all other things lose their taste” and threw the royal household into a “state of agitation.” There were some other art galleries in the “Kala Ghoda” neighborhood that we explored which was super cool; it was nice to see the art of up and coming contemporary Indian artists displayed and it’s interesting to see subjects that are distinctly Indian painted or crafted in more of a European style. I guess that’s similar to the food at Masque: a blend of East and West.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/20241030_135246-2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

An old snakes and ladders board on cloth.

</figcaption>

<p>One fun visit we made was to Sabyasachi’s showroom, also in the Kala Ghoda district. It’s technically a boutique where one can actually buy his clothes but the three storied building also is jam packed with some of his most beautiful <em>lehenga</em> and <em>sari</em> designs, shoes (some in collaboration with Louboutin), men’s vests and <em>kurtas</em>, boisterous jewelry (this designer does <em>not</em> do “delicate” or “understated” and I’m here for it), and other household items like vases, sculptures, and paintings. Every inch of the showroom had gorgeous objects to admire. Although we didn’t buy anything, it was a super cool experience to be able to peruse through the boutique like a museum and the staff were really welcoming and polite to everyone even though it was clear most people weren’t going to purchase anything.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/20241101_151547.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Gorgeous bridal lehengas from Sabyasachi. There were more beautiful designs but we found out afterwards that we weren’t supposed to take photos. Oops!

</figcaption>

<p>We spent quite a bit of time walking around Mumbai which helped us get to know some parts of the city a bit better, more than other cities we’ve visited in the past where we dash between each sight. We bought <em>das</em> (ten) rupee tea from a guy with a big thermos of masala chai sitting on the sidewalk and got a hole in my backpack fixed for <em>bees</em> (twenty) rupees from a guy with a sewing machine under a stall at the corner of two busy roads. We visited Gandhi’s house which was surprisingly quiet, strolled around some parks, watched humongous flocks of black kites swirl around in the fading smoggy sunset light, and (mostly) confidently walked straight across roads in full seventeen-million-people-level traffic without getting smushed. We got sort of immune to honks in our faces and sweated our way through our clothes in the thirty plus degree weather. It’s worth noting though, we were in the posh part of town and the strong segregation between the rich and the poor in the city definitely colored our relatively smooth and calm experiences. One day, we took the train up to a neighborhood called Bandra which is known for its Portuguese influence and also seems to have more of a Christian population given how many churches and statues of Christ there are. When we exited the train and ascended to the bridge to take us to West Bandra, we could see that on the other side was a large slum. When we took off from the Mumbai Airport to New Delhi, we could also see another slum that bordered the runway. This particular slum called Dharavi is famous for having been featured in the movie <em>Slumdog Millionaire</em>. To give you a sense of how insane these places are, Dharavi houses around <em>one million</em> people in an area of less than <em>two and half square kilometers</em>. It has one toilet for every 1440 people. And around 40-50% of all Mumbaikars live in slums. Our experience in Mumbai was amazing in so many ways, but it’s privilege that enabled us to have it so.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/20241102_145647.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Murals in Bandra.

</figcaption>

<p>Eventually the sun would set, early because of the thickness of the smog that laid thickly across the city, and we’d hear the first pops go off. This was just the beginning of the Diwali nights that lasted for five days. Around 6:30 or so, we’d head out to grab some early dinner and around 8:30, make our way to Marine Drive which was a three kilometer long esplanade bordering the Arabian Sea. Holy macaroni. People did not come to just set off a few sparklers. We saw huge aerials and Roman Candles being lit up right on the sidewalk into the air. Sparklers were mostly just a tool to be able to light huge flower pots, firework wheels, other fireworks that I don’t know the name of that would cause bystanders to flee in every direction as sparks flew everywhere. They were everywhere and we (and probably at least another million of people) loved watching rival families set off firework after firework into the sky. We watched as parents would let their tiny tots light a firework and as soon as it caught, would grab their child and run to the edge since the kid wouldn’t know to get out of there. Kevin and I both got hit by a few sparks every now and again but no fingers or toes were lost! It was beautiful cacophony in every direction and for three nights in a row, we wandered up and down the promenade watching the party go on and on into the night. Apparently Mumbai city set a “rule” to end the fireworks by 10:30 and occasionally we’d watch as police whistled at people futilely to shut things down. As soon as the police turned their back, the people went straight back to setting off more. Every now and again, we’d watch as an aerial didn’t get quite enough height before it exploded and we’d all duck… as if that was going to help anything. Sometimes, one wouldn’t go straight up in the air and instead down a side street and I’d briefly wonder where that one ended up. Each night, the street would be a total mess with boxes and fireworks residue everywhere and the next day, it would be cleaned up, just in time for Diwali round 2. Or round 3. Or 4. 5. I think people here only buy fireworks in wholesale quantities. It really was a pretty special experience to see the entire city completely dotted in the sky with colorful peonies and willows.</p>

<p>PS: if you’re reading this on email, there are three videos following this paragraph that will only be viewable on the website.</p>

<p>“Ooh, I just got hit by something.”</p>

<p>So many different fireworks!</p>

<p>This one was often used as a “finale” firework. And we learned would require bystanders to be larger distance away from the flinging flames.</p>

<p>I am grateful that I was able to visit India to experience this and I hope it won’t be the last time. I actually really owe both my parents and the manager of the last hotel we stayed at in Jordan for being able to come to India and it’s something I won’t forget. I left my Overseas Citizenship of India document and my old passport with my lifelong Indian visa in the States thinking that I wasn’t going to visit India this year. My parents managed to ship the documents over to me in Jordan but there were some complications with the address because it was written in English, not Arabic, and the DHL folks in Amman had no idea where to deliver the passport. It’s because of the kindness of the hotel’s manager who called DHL, explained where the building was, and when the driver <em>still</em> missed the location, drove out to meet the delivery person to get the documents himself and hold on to them until I returned to Amman (I was out in the middle of the Jordan Trail trek without internet when this all happened) that I was able to visit India. I was told that I couldn’t apply for an eVisa since I have an OCI (this turned out to be false) so I was panicking a bit, but everything ended up fine in the end because of a lot of generosity from a lot of people who cared. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/mumbai_34.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A hazy sunset from Elephanta Island.

</figcaption>

<p>I’ve resolved to try to be more kind moving forward. During our year of travel, we have been on the receiving end of so many kindnesses that continuously show me that the world is more caring than perhaps we are led to believe. From the lady who bought me a cup of chai in Mumbai because I was struggling to find the small coin in my bag to pay, our Airbnb host in Santiago who gifted me a box of acetazolamide that I’ve now used to safely visit high altitude locations in both Bolivia and Bhutan, the Russian tourist in Kazakhstan who carefully translated my dietary restrictions to the hotel chef who then prepared a special off-the-menu meal for me to eat, to the countless travelers and locals who have provided us with mountains of knowledge to help us plan our travel, there is a lot of goodness in the world.</p>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Diwali is my favorite holiday. As a kid, I remember going to Phantom Fireworks in Ohio around the time of the fourth of July and purchasing extra sparklers and flower pots and fountains that were on sale (sadly, no aerials) and stashing them in our basement until October or November to light them for Diwali. As I got older, Phantom Fireworks picked up on the fact that there were a good number of Diwali celebraters in Ohio and started doing special Diwali sales in the fall as well so hoarding became less required. It was always a special time of the year, lighting up the driveway with rows of candles, setting off our stash with friends and family, eating delicious, special meals, and doning new outfits.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/mumbai_3.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/diwali-and-dosas-in-mumbai/mumbai_3.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Petra through the Backdoor</title><link href="/petra-through-the-backdoor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Petra through the Backdoor" /><published>2024-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/petra-through-the-backdoor</id><content type="html" xml:base="/petra-through-the-backdoor"><![CDATA[<p>I’m currently sitting in a large tent that looks like the Bedouin tent that we stopped by earlier for tea. We’re on the third day of our trek from Dana to Petra which will take us a total of five days. We ended up at our camp a little earlier than the previous two nights which has allowed me some time to hang out at the tent, having had a fresh shower (and I washed my hair!). As per Jordanian custom, I’ve been offered tea twice in the time I have written these last few words by two different people. I finally feel comfortable declining at least just with the folks who are part of our trek; it is black tea sweetened with as much sugar as pop and I’ve already had about five cups today as well as about two tablespoons of Arabic coffee and I am hoping to sleep tonight (and now that I write that, I realize how futile this hope might be). Jordanian hospitality is on another level; I’ve really loved how welcoming everyone has been and how each camp eagerly says “welcome to Jordan” and “please feel like this is your home.” I am going to definitely miss Jordan once we leave in a few days!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_3.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A pretty Tristram's Starling we saw on our first day of hiking.

</figcaption>

<p>Kevin and I found out about this trek through a <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/adventure/article/world-hikes">National Geographic site</a> that listed the top 15 original treks in the world. The full Jordan Trail actually runs from the top of the country to the bottom and takes forty-two days to complete. We’re doing just a portion of it that begins in the Dana Biosphere Reserve, where we were briefly towards the end of our road trip, and ends by walking through the backdoor of Petra. We thought it would be a cool experience to walk into the Nabataean Kingdom’s capital, walking parts of the ancient routes that traders took to enter the city themselves, more than a thousand years ago.</p>

<p>With us, we have a wonderful group of trekking companions. Munthar is our trekking guide and absolutely loves geology but is amazingly well versed in botany, zoology, history, and so many other subjects. Maria and Christian are from the Seattle area and are also on a travel break though they’re a bit further along than us, having already finished one full year. For them, their travel break is coming to a close as they are planning on returning to Seattle to visit their families for the holidays. Esther is a wonderful woman who actually lives in Amman and has been there for one year. She is a statistician and has worked in many countries, including Tanzania and India. She is originally from the UK and her work is inspiring as she does data analysis on the Syrian refugees who live in Jordan to help the government make decisions. And finally, for one day, we had Vera. Vera lives in Switzerland and is Munthar’s girlfriend. They actually met about a year ago, doing the section of the Jordan Trail hike from Petra to Wadi Rum. When October 7th happened, everyone else who was scheduled for the trek dropped out except for Vera and since then, they’ve been in a long distance relationship. Unfortunately she ended up having to head back to Switzerland for work after one day but we really enjoyed having her on the trail and it’s amazing how quickly we all got along!</p>

<p>We all met each other at a hotel/camp that was coincidentally right next to the hotel/camp the first time Kevin and I stayed a couple nights in Dana. It had an equally beautiful view and we loved the home cooked spread they set out for us for dinner. The night was pretty uneventful as Munthar briefed us about the following day and handed us a really nice package of a canvas tote with the trail map, reusable sporks, a stainless steel cup, and a buff. Later on, I would realize exactly how much I appreciated those items (like the buff for the crazy winds we would experience later!) but in general, I really liked how much emphasis the trek already had on trying to be kind to the environment.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/WhatsApp+Image+2024-10-28+at+00.23.38.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Our trekking crew! From the left: Arathi, Kevin, Christian, Maria, Vera, Esther, Munthar, Mustafa, and Ayoub.

</figcaption>

<p><strong>Day 1</strong></p>

<p>The thing that I learned today is that tetra paks of hummus need to exist all over the world and I will figure out a way to a) make top tier hummus and b) find reusable packets that act like tetra paks. Munthar brought out a big stainless steel plate of things that we could pick and choose from to turn into a lunch including tetra paks of hummus, cucumbers, tomatoes, pita bread, cans of tuna, and maamouls (a sort of cookie with a date paste filling that amusingly called it “date pasta” on the ingredient list). Vera later showed us how to tear off a small corner of the tetra pak and squeeze the hummus directly on whatever vehicle we chose (i.e.  vegetable or bread). She said that every time she returns to Switzerland from Jordan, she fills her suitcase with hummus tetra paks and za’atar. </p>

<p>This hiking day was a nice easy start to the trek and there were some similarities to the hike we had previously done on our own. We descended directly down into the valley, passing by the white domes we had walked through earlier, and traced the dry riverbed of the wadi all the way to Feynan Ecolodge where we broke for lunch. Lunch was a challenge as the cats started swarming around all those tuna cans and we all spent equal amounts of time taking bites of food and swatting cats, especially one persistent one who would leap onto the table. </p>

<p>Munthar had endless information about the flora and fauna of the area, telling us about both the scientific knowledge of the plants and also how the Bedouins use various plants for medicinal purposes. I managed to get some beautiful shots of some birds this first day that I’m super proud of.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_19.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

An Arabian Green Bee-eater.

</figcaption>

<p>Munthar let us know that because of incoming strong winds, we had to abort our plans to camp for the night. He rerouted us to a small sheltered area where there were stone cabins set up and a separate sheltered area for the kitchen, dining, and sleeping for the staff. As we approached camp, a small boy met us with a huge grin on his face. His name was Ayoub and he was the young son of the cook, Mustafa, who was eagerly waiting to see Munthar. I really enjoyed watching Munthar toss Ayoub onto his shoulder and walk into camp as the sun slowly started to set. After quickly dropping our bags, we climbed a small nearby hill to sit and watch the sun fully go down. I always find it funny how it looks like the sun has set when you’re low and there are hills in the distance and suddenly, the sun appears to be rising as you quickly go up a hill. And then you get a second sunset!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_22.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Off into the sunset!

</figcaption>

<p>The cabins were pretty basic (just two mattresses on the floor), but the highlight was just being around such friendly company. We loved sharing a meal with the rest of our trekking group and the food was absolutely delicious. I could barely hold in my laughter as Ayoub tried to keep up with the adults with tea drinking and on his second glass, he would take a big gulp and look around a bit helplessly before spitting it back into the cup and trying again. He eventually succeeded! That boy had endless energy (even besides the caffeinated beverages), running up and down the sunset hill and between the valleys before running back to camp upon his dad’s summon. </p>

<p>They weren’t wrong about the wind. It definitely picked up by the time dinner rolled around with us having to fight the door from swinging wildly open. I was impressed; when we passed by our initial planned campsite earlier, I thought that the wind wasn’t too bad, but the crew was spot on with the wind howling as the night progressed. We were all very grateful that Munthar was able to arrange concrete cabins for us to sleep in and bonus, there were showers (though cold) available so I was able to have a quick wash before bed.</p>

<p><strong>Day 2</strong></p>

<p>We crawled out of our bunkers with a light dusting of sand on everything. It was hard to keep absolutely everything sand tight but, so it goes with sandstorms. As Munthar bemoaned the high winds coming from the neighbors to the south, he joked “nothing good comes from Saudi Arabia.”</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_29.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The dusty, sandy desert.

</figcaption>

<p>We had a really interesting breakfast. Two other women joined us who were also doing the Dana to Petra trek, though with a different company. Last night, they also aborted their original camping plans and sheltered in the camp with walls, but we only briefly chatted with them to ask where they were from and otherwise had dined separately. This morning, we all huddled around one area of the walled dining area that was more protected from the wind and we got to know them a bit better. These two women were from Europe. They had come to Jordan many years ago and fell in love with Bedouin men. One was married to a Bedouin and another was “close.” It was so interesting to hear their experiences with maintaining a long distance relationship with people who have such a different culture. The French woman talked about how she had just been able to communicate to him that not disappearing without a word for weeks on end didn’t work for her and he was now starting to send messages to her daily while they were apart. She said that while it sounds crazy to celebrate something as simple as that, it’s a big deal for her partner whose culture is not like that at all and much more carefree. We found her honesty about how difficult it was at times to be really self-reflective as she talked about how on her first trip, she was naive and really also fell for the Bedouin nomadic and carefree lifestyle, but it isn’t necessarily so easy and carefree all the time, especially bridging cultures. I think we all found her commitment to maintaining and nurturing the relationship over five plus years to be extraordinary; any relationship, whether romantic or not, requires a commitment from both ends to trust in each other and commit to bridging across differences. But when the river that must be bridged is so wide, in my eyes, that seems to require a more extraordinary sense of will.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_32.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Hiking through some super cool dark rock formations.

</figcaption>

<p>We parted ways after we loaded up on our hummus packs and maamouls (I need to figure out if I can import or make the cardamom maamoul which was so so yummy. More cardamom than date if I’m honest, but I liked it that way). Sadly they were taking a slightly different route to get to Petra (where their Bedouin partners are from) so that they ended up there a day faster than us so we didn’t cross paths again. We continued our journey through the desert, with some wind but not as much as overnight. The views this day were better than the last.We passed through some gorgeous desert lands where we could really see all the sand that the winds had kicked up. We passed through some rocky passages that snaked between tall black stone walls that looked shiny in the fuzzy sunny sky. We had some beautiful views of some domed stone structures, similar to the white domes of Dana but larger and with clearly stratified layers. There was a small waterfall and pool where we lunched, where Kevin and Christian also went in for a dip. We also saw some of the first signs of the Nabataeans’ water control structures as we walked through a carved aqueduct running through the walls of stone.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_53.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A lovely sunset towards the end of our day 2.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/20241024_164308.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A Nabataean aqueduct.

</figcaption>

<p>Sadly, we couldn’t camp this night either as the Saudi winds continued to batter our planned camp site. This time, we ended our trek at a 4x4 road a little past where we would have camped and one of our hosts came by in his pickup truck to pick us up. We crammed (four butts in the back row of seats) into the pickup with Munthar wrapping himself in five blankets and chucking himself into the bed. We rattled our way up a large hill for about forty-five minutes until we reached a large rectangular shelter that was nestled into the ridge like a port-a-ledge. We got ourselves comfortable into the single large room for the evening.</p>

<p>This was probably one of my favorite evenings. We had such a wonderful set of folks with us for the evening. One was a young boy (different from Ayoub… I accidentally called him Ayoub and he looked at me quizzically when I realized my mistake) who could not get enough of playing a cups game with all of us. He had two cups, a plate and a rock. He would put the rock in one of the cups and shake it back and forth and then slam the cups onto the plate. His opponent would have to guess which cup it was underneath. And so it went on and on until one of us would get a little tired, which didn’t matter to him because he would move on to the next person. He was endlessly entertained by the game and only paused to eat and eventually sleep.</p>

<p>We also had, joining us, a 97-year old man. Munthar and Mustafa and some of the other hosts had a great time chatting away with the man who was a bit hard of hearing so the room was pleasantly shout-y as the men yelled at each other enthusiastically. Among the English speakers, we talked about random things like “third tier superpowers.” This is something Maria and Christian brought up and I will have to steal it. A first tier superpower is something that is truly extraordinarily supernatural, like being able to teleport or become invisible. A second tier superpower is still a supernatural power, but less exciting, like being able to levitate something if it’s less than a few grams in weight. A third tier superpower is something that is distinctly human but is quite exciting and enviable. Mine is being able to sleep on planes.</p>

<p>After dinner (again, a spectacular feast by Mustafa and his older son), we started to roll out our sleeping bags around the perimeter of the room. This room, like most of the other Jordanian dining/kitchen/hang out rooms, had cushions lining the perimeter that acted like natural sleeping mats for our sleeping bags. We all really enjoyed our adult sleepover and funny enough, Munthar and one of the other hosts tried to hang a “privacy curtain” between us and the hosts. The gesture was appreciated but it definitely shielded very little and as we watched them try to hang it on some electrical cables, we all chimed that it wasn’t really necessary. Someone getting electrocuted in the name of privacy definitely doesn’t seem worthwhile. And off to bed we went! I slept surprisingly well given the circumstances and was very grateful not to be out camping while the wind, once again, howled as predicted outside.</p>

<p><strong>Day 3</strong></p>

<p>This might be the first time that I have not heard the extremely jarring iPhone alarm go off in a group sleeping situation (e.g. hostel, crazy packed ski trip, etc.). It seems our Jordanian hosts and our hiking buddies have gentle, quiet phone alarms. I genuinely woke up thinking, ahhh, “what a nice way to wake up” and felt great, even though I didn’t sleep very soundly all night. Weirdly, my toes were cold even though the rest of my body was warm enough.</p>

<p>I finished my morning ablutions first and hunkered down next to the 97-year old grandfather who was huddled near a small heater also with another older man, eating breakfast. I learned a new combination of food for breakfast: pita with a triangle of soft cheese (like Laughing Cow). The men would first heat a circle of pita against the heater and after warmed, unwrap a cheese triangle, plop it on an edge of the pita and start dabbing away at it with bits of pita torn from the other edges. No plate needed! </p>

<p>Soon the larger breakfast was served and Munthar very effectively moved us all to the breakfast area on the floor by swinging the heater to point towards the plates of hummus, eggs, labneh, halva, and more. We were all crowded around the heater by this point and it didn’t take long before we were chowing down, this time Jordanian style, forgoing plates to dig into the dips and dishes family style. Honestly, my favorite might have been the olive oil and za’atar. I need to learn how to make this top tier level of za’atar. The scrambled eggs were shockingly good. We tend to avoid pre cooked scrambled eggs as they are usually pretty dry and rubbery but these were genuinely tasty and still soft. Jordanians are truly kitchen magicians. We had a fun time leisurely eating breakfast, watching as Munthar tried to get the 97-year old to recite some poetry for the camera (it took a couple of tries, but eventually he succeeded!). He really is unbelievably spry and full of energy for that age! </p>

<p>Eventually we were on our way (trucked back to the trailhead in the squished pickup again) and we slowly trekked through the blasting wind and sand. Man, this was some of the toughest winds I’ve had to hike though for such an extended period of time. It was a bit chilly so we had on a few layers and also my head was almost entirely covered. I had on a scarf on my head to cover my hair, sunglasses to protect my eyes, and another Buff to cover my nose and mouth and neck. I had to give up on the scarf quickly as it was too slick and was getting blown off. My sunglasses were nearly blown off a few times and I had to keep one hand on my face to prevent them from flying away. I was getting pushed around quite a bit and eventually took up leaning and walking slightly to the left (towards the east) to counteract the Easterly winds and accordingly walk roughly in a straight line. It was definitely an adventure!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/20241025_111252.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

We are extremely dusty.

</figcaption>

<p>Eventually, after a descent and ascent, the winds did calm down substantially. We had some really amazing views of the rock formations this day, including hiking across some fossilized corals, through some village ruins (the village was abandoned after a landslide buried their spring which was their sole water source) and a small niche carved into rock that the Nabateans used to use as a place to worship one of their gods. A few months ago, I read a book called The Control of Nature where one of the chapters talked about how the people near the San Gabriel mountains near Los Angeles live near mountains that are full of loose scree and every now and then, after a strong earthquake shake plus some strong rainfall, the scree turns into a dangerous landslide that destroys the homes in the area. This area of Jordan actually has the exact same feature; Munthar explained that sometimes, the loose rock will flow after a strong rainfall, wiping away everything in its path. It’s mostly Bedouins that live in the area who are really well connected with the land but definitely, every year there is some risk with spending the winter time in the lower valley. Unlike Los Angeles, there are no debris basins here to capture some of the rocks and protect the citizens (though as the book says, perhaps the residents who choose to build their houses up in the San Gabriel’s have overconfidence in those debris basins). </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_61.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

More cool rock formations with a wadi in the distance. And more sand and dust.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_72.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>We saw a bunch of juniper trees and learned how to say juniper in Arabic. Here’s how. There are two syllables. Syllable one: pretend you’re in a dentist office and you have your mouth open and the dentist hits a nerve. The sound you might make is syllable one. Syllable two: pretend you are a lion speaking Spanish. Say “rawr” and roll the r’s. AHR-RAR! Juniper. The more aggressive the better. Munthar taught us some tongue twisters that involved that word and everyone did not even attempt to have a go at it. Arabic is tricky! </p>

<p>A couple kilometers from camp, we stopped by a Bedouin tent. We’d seen a lot of the tents while on the hike and across Jordan while we were road tripping but this time, we were invited in for some coffee and tea. Munthar showed us how to accept the Arabic coffee, brewed very strongly with cardamom, but only thankfully served a couple tablespoons at a time in tiny paper cups. He said that a long time ago when the Bedouins were planning raids, coffee would be served by someone who was deaf so that they could not hear the plans and potentially tell them to an enemy tribe. Because of this, people would use signals to communicate with the person serving coffee. First, the cup had to be received with the right hand. After one cup, if you wanted more, then you would tilt the cup back and forth (sort of shaking it). If you didn’t want more, you would put the cup down. If you had a second cup of coffee, it meant you were a tribe mate. If you had a third cup, it meant that you were committing yourself to the protection of the tribe and were willing to stand up and defend the tribe or be there in times of need.</p>

<p>In addition to coffee, we were also served sweetened black tea (this time, extremely sweet, as the Bedouins prefer). We all sort of struggled through because we didn’t want to be rude, but it’s tricky since all of us drink far less caffeine typically, much less sweet, and almost never around four pm or later. After hanging out for a bit longer, we continued on our journey for the last couple of kilometers to our camp. We were treated to showers, our own cabins, and electricity! The shower was very welcome to soap off all the dust and sand from the day (though the shower did alternate between ice cold and boiling hot). And per usual, we were served a huge spread of amazing Jordanian food, including some of the yummiest, smokiest mutabal. It was such an incredible campsite to be at, flanked by towering limestone formations. We were told that tomorrow would be a hot day because the current spell of easterly winds were coming to an end which was a portend for hotter than usual days. My legs were actually a bit sore today so I was quite thankful for the mint tea that was served (without sugar to the horror and befuddlement of our host) for a good night’s sleep. </p>

<p>After dinner and playing some cards for a little while (Maria and Christian taught us a fun game called “Up and Down the River”), we were ushered outside towards a small fire that had been lit to watch “a dance.” Color me intrigued! We huddled around the fire and the men sang us a song while they rocked from side to side and clapped . We enthusiastically clapped along and my only regret was not joining them while attempting to enunciate the Arabic syllables. After the dance (not sure what the meaning of the dance was), we continued chatting away while Munthar translated. These hosts were really an absolute joy to hang out with. They got such a kick out of saying “AHR-RAR!” every time we were asked anything. What type of wood was burning in the fire? AHR-RAR! Though turns out that was the correct answer! They got a kick out of us being absolutely horrified by the amount of sugar they claimed to consume each month. It got wilder and wilder until one of the hosts claimed FIFTY KILOGRAMS A MONTH! He wins. I’m still petrified for their health. Eventually the fire gave out an almighty crackle that had us all scrambling so we called it a night and turned into our comfy individual cabins for a solid night’s rest. I think I’m getting pretty good at sleeping even with caffeine in my body.</p>

<p>A dance by the campfire.</p>

<p><strong>Day 4</strong></p>

<p>I was quite sad to leave this camp because of our wonderful, entertaining hosts but we did indeed have to leave. We packed up, grabbed our classic hummus tetra paks and maamouls and started our hike, now all clad in shorts and tees as the wind was indeed gone. This day, we walked into an area called Little Petra which is like the appetizer before the entree of Petra. Prior to walking into Little Petra, we started to see our first signs of civilization: cultivated pomegranate trees (unfortunately pom season was over and the remaining ones likely were rotten on the inside) and thick black pipes distributing water over the various farm areas. We saw some early signs of the Nabataeans’ former presence as we climbed up onto a rocky ledge and followed one of their aqueducts towards Little Petra. I was quite excited to see this because one of the things that the podcast highlighted was the Nabataeans’ prowess with water engineering. It had such a strong foothold in the area because unlike any other group, they were able to find ways to store and transport water making Petra itself an important stop for all merchants wishing to use the paths of the Silk Road for trade. In the middle of the desert, any group that could control water, controlled the land. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_79.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Starting out Day 4.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_95.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A Sinai Agama lizard with a beautiful blue-grey body. Munthar said that they’re tricky to find and especially rare to see one that has captured its lunch!

</figcaption>

<p>Arriving into Little Petra, we climbed up a small staircase into a small canyon between the walls where the first of shops offering tchotchkes were set up. While less interested in the shopkeeper’s offerings, we all took strong interest in the cats and dog (yep, singular dog) that were roaming the shops. The cutest little kitten was absolutely obsessed with Christian and I enjoyed watching it play and letting out the cutest soft purrs and mews. Once through the narrow gorge, we debouched out into a wider area where we started to see the famous carved façades, chiseled right into the canyon walls. Having been to Petra now, it seems less magnificent, but at the time, it was really impressive to see the columns and deep caverns bored into the stone, some with ceilings and walls blackened from when they (and more recent Bedouins) used to cook. We stopped at a I found the cutest cat with only one eye who originally was fighting with another cat, but as I crouched down, surprised me by leaping onto my lap, crawling right over my shoulder and settling its butt down on the top of my backpack while perching itself on my shoulder. I wanted to keep the cat but alas, we needed to continue on our journey to camp.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_100.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/WhatsApp+Image+2024-10-28+at+00.26.01.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Can I keep the cat?

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_114.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Little Petra sandstone façade carvings.

</figcaption>

<p>For our final night, we stayed at a larger and more modern camp just around the corner of the more common entrance to Little Petra. This place had a proper shower, individual cabins, and electricity inside the cabins! We arrived at the camp quite early so after lounging around/taking naps, we all hopped over the concrete wall around the camp to explore the nearby sand dunes. They were small dunes, but still really fun to run down. We watched the last rays of sun light up the drippy walls and finally dip below the stone ridge line, before trundling back over to camp for our showers. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_little_petra_5.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Watching the sun dip behind the rocks atop the sand dunes.

</figcaption>

<p>The winning feature of the camp was a large fireplace inside the communal dining tent that was raging when I went in after taking a hot shower. I plopped myself down with my laptop while waiting for the others and for dinner to be served. We ate another yummy meal, watched the hosts futilely shoo away the cats from the buffet area and spent some more time just chatting away with our trekking companions. Alas, Munthar wasn’t feeling so well so he tucked in early, but we stayed up a bit longer continuing to learn about our experiences and exchange stories. I think we all felt a little sad that this was our final night together but I’m sure we’ll see each other again sometime. </p>

<p><strong>Day 5</strong></p>

<p>Breakfast was more western style with every person getting their own plates but Christian made a communal plate of olive oil and za’atar for us to dig into which we did voraciously. As a shock to us all, there were two pots of tea: one with sugar and one without. We drank a lot of unsweetened tea. </p>

<p>Soon enough we were on our way to walk the last six kilometers that would deposit us at the backdoor of Petra at the Monastery. We were joined by another person today, Mahmoud, who was born in one of the caves in Petra and grew up playing in the city before the site was turned into a UNESCO World Heritage site and became a protected place for tourists. He was our cultural guide while we walked through Petra. It was probably really nice for Munthar to have someone else be the guide for the day because he still was struggling with his stomach a bit and Mahmoud was really a fantastic and knowledgeable guide. </p>

<p>Those last six kilometers to Petra are spectacular in and of itself with beautiful views of Wadi Araba that borders Petra. I still remember the first glimpse of the Monastery though; for a second, my brain thought I was looking at a trail cairn and I thought “huh, that’s a big cairn.” One more thought later and I realized it was the top of the largest carved building in Petra looming ahead. Funnily enough, I wasn’t the only one who thought it was a large cairn before realizing what it really was. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_final_day_petra_10.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The first glimpse of the Monastery through the backdoor of Petra.

</figcaption>

<p>Before we reached the Monastery, Mahmoud led us to some additional cavities in the walls that were situated right next door. Prime examples of the Nabatean prowess in water conservation, these were a series of water tanks where each one was placed slightly below the next so that overflow of water could be captured. Apparently there are still excavation projects in progress to continue to unearth these water tanks and we saw some construction zone areas.</p>

<p>Finally, we reached the Monastery. It really is spectacular. And huge. I was stunned by the sheer size of the façade.  There weren’t too many people at the Monastery because a) there aren’t many tourists in Jordan in the first place and b) in order to reach the Monastery the normal way, it’s a sizable and fairly relentless uphill climb from the usual entrance of Petra through the Siq. Most of the caverns that populate Petra have tombs underneath and the Monastery, likewise, contained tombs, though the upper level has no cavity and is just a façade. We learned that the façades that specifically had stairs carved into the rock right above the door was a giveaway that the cavern contained tombs as the stairs were a path for the deceased to climb their way to heaven. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_final_day_petra_14.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Monastery.

</figcaption>

<p>One of my favorite areas was the Royal Tombs. These were a set of very ornately decorated tombs with huge rooms inside that we could explore on our own. The Rainbow Tomb was especially special with the rock swirled into different colors. It reminded me of making a marbled icing cake. First you arbitrarily splotch on different coloured frosting on a cake, then you freeze it, then you use a tall bench scraper to scrape away thin layers of the frozen frosting until voila, a marble pattern appears. It’s very magical and I wondered if the Nabataeans’ also felt like that while carving the ornate tombs. Did they also know ahead of time the gorgeous colors that were just underneath what looked like plain red rock? </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_final_day_petra_45.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Royal Tombs.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_final_day_petra_56.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Rainbow Tomb.

</figcaption>

<p>We had some time by ourselves to explore and climb the tombs which was really fun and then per instruction by Mahmoud, we visited “the most beautiful toilet in the world.” These toilets were repurposed Nabataean caves and had the gorgeous swirled coloured ceiling which was indeed beautiful. The tombs continued on for quite a while though they weren’t as large or decorated as the Royal Tombs. Eventually, Mahmoud took us through the Siq, the narrow canyon that most visitors enter from and told us to look for some coins on the ground. It was a red herring that I totally bought into (and I think no one else did). He eventually told us to turn around as we were staring at the ground and we saw our first glimpse of the Treasury. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_final_day_petra_73.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Treasury through the Siq.

</figcaption>

<p>The Treasury is just absolutely stunning. That first glimpse that we got, through the Siq, showing a small fraction of the whole façade yet giving a clear sense of the majesty to come, is the same one that merchants would get as they entered the Nabataean capital. It must have been a sight to behold, especially after ages of slogging through the desert. The images that are carved in the rock represent Egyptian, Greek, and Nabataean gods and goddesses as an effort to make the first sight of the city welcoming to all people. One amusing story is that the Treasury is called such because there is an urn at the top that people believed contained valuable Egyptian treasures. While the Bedouins lived in Petra, they shot rifles at the urn to try to break it but of course, it’s just rock. So now there are bullet holes in the façade.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_final_day_petra_78.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Treasury.

</figcaption>

<p>After having our fill of Treasury views and pictures, we continued meandering through the Siq, taking more photos of more sandstone carvings until we finally reached the visitors’ center. Alas, it was time to part ways. Maria and Christian were off to Aqaba, Esther back to Amman, and we decided to spend the night in Petra to have one more day to explore the vast city.</p>

<p><strong>Bonus Petra Day</strong></p>

<p>Petra is actually a huge city with a bunch of hiking trails so on our second day, we decided to hike one of the paths to the High Place of Sacrifice. We had fun walking through the Siq again, visiting the Treasury again, which was on the way to the start of the trail, and then climbing up the many steps to reach the high vantage point of the High Place of Sacrifice. It was very fun to be up high and we had a bit of company with several military guys, posted on various peaks in the area. From above, we saw a small caravan of golf carts that were heavily protected with folks from the military who appeared to be doing some normal sightseeing, but we don’t know who was in the carts.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_petra_day_2_18.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

An obelisk and various structural ruins near the High Place of Sacrifice.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_petra_day_2_34.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A Roughtail Rock Agama (lizard) basking in the sun.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_petra_day_2_38.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Endless tombs carved into the sandstone.

</figcaption>

<p>We briefly visited the Petra Museum at the end of the day which we rushed a bit because we ended up spending too long in Petra and had to catch the bus back to Amman. They had some pretty cool pieces of jewelry from 6500-7000 BC that looked really cool. I wonder if there are jewelry artists that pull their designs from prehistoric times because some of the craftsmanship is truly astonishing and beautiful. That would be a cool concept.</p>

<p>And that was the end of our Dana to Petra trek! One day, we would love to go back to do the continuation of that trek from Petra to Wadi Rum which Munthar raved about with beautiful desert landscapes. But this was pretty amazing and we’re really glad we had such amazing company to do the hike with!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/petra-through-the-backdoor/WhatsApp+Image+2024-10-27+at+21.17.03+%281%29.jpeg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m currently sitting in a large tent that looks like the Bedouin tent that we stopped by earlier for tea. We’re on the third day of our trek from Dana to Petra which will take us a total of five days. We ended up at our camp a little earlier than the previous two nights which has allowed me some time to hang out at the tent, having had a fresh shower (and I washed my hair!). As per Jordanian custom, I’ve been offered tea twice in the time I have written these last few words by two different people. I finally feel comfortable declining at least just with the folks who are part of our trek; it is black tea sweetened with as much sugar as pop and I’ve already had about five cups today as well as about two tablespoons of Arabic coffee and I am hoping to sleep tonight (and now that I write that, I realize how futile this hope might be). Jordanian hospitality is on another level; I’ve really loved how welcoming everyone has been and how each camp eagerly says “welcome to Jordan” and “please feel like this is your home.” I am going to definitely miss Jordan once we leave in a few days!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_final_day_petra_14.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/petra-through-the-backdoor/jordan_trail_final_day_petra_14.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Road Tripping around Jordan</title><link href="/road-tripping-around-jordan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Road Tripping around Jordan" /><published>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/road-tripping-around-jordan</id><content type="html" xml:base="/road-tripping-around-jordan"><![CDATA[<p>We’re on our way to Mumbai now, having departed Jordan early in the morning. It’s not often that I feel a bit melancholy leaving a place because I’m so looking forward to the next one. But with Jordan, as our driver kept saying “welcome to Jordan!” each time we gushed about another sight we enjoyed seeing in Jordan, I felt a bit sad to be leaving even though I am bonkers excited to be spending Diwali in India (a first for me!). I’ll miss the Jordanian hospitality that’s really on another level. I’ll miss visiting Hashem’s restaurant in Amman for cloud-like falafels and olive oil drenched hummus and ful and fatteh, where we ate five times in fewer than that many days (we learned that the owner is now in Bolivian prison for smuggling cocaine so uhhh maybe there was some other special ingredients in that hummus. No wonder it tasted so good). I’ll miss the sassy cats that want attention, but not too much attention, and definitely want food. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/road-tripping-around-jordan/amman_jordan_19.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

View of Amman, Jordan from the Amman Citadel.

</figcaption>

<p>Our time in Jordan was broken up into two parts: for the first two weeks, we spent some time in Amman and then rented a car to drive around the country and visit other cities and sights. For the last week in Jordan, we trekked a section of the epic Jordan trail that began at the Dana Biosphere Reserve and ended by walking through the backdoor of Petra. I’ll cover the second part in a second post because it really deserves its own. Visiting Jordan wasn’t really on our plan for the year before we started, but like Türkiye, we ended up listening to another <em>Fall of Civilizations</em> <a href="https://open.spotify.com/episode/7Ho575TPrGODG5puISrAcx?si=6qST1mEmTFe1S2IDmcCklA">podcast on the Nabataeans</a> and decided that we wanted to see Petra, the capital of the Nabataeans and one of the most important trading cities, especially during the Iron Age. At the time, we were melting in Türkiye so we decided that hopping to another Middle Eastern country where temperatures top in the mid-forties during the summer was not the best idea so we skipped it for the summer. We were in the middle of our overlanding trip in Mangystau, just a couple days out from our flight to Amman, when our trip mate Betty managed to get some internet and let us know that Iran had launched missiles at Israel which were flying over Jordan. There were videos coming out from Amman showing the missiles across the night sky and we learned that the Jordan airspace was closed. However, by the time our trip ended in Mangystau, everything seemed like it was back to normal in Jordan with the airspace open. We had been keeping an eye out on any travel restrictions in Jordan from the US State Department but luckily, it continued to remain at Level 2 (where it has been for years) and so we continued our journey onwards. Our flight from Istanbul did take a “scenic route” to avoid flying over Israeli airspace so ended up a bit longer than scheduled, but otherwise, we didn’t have any issues.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/road-tripping-around-jordan/PXL_20241010_170429064.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

I thought I disliked kunefe. Habiba’s, serving hot kunefe (on the right) with a light layer of cheese convinced me that I simply had never tried real kunefe and in fact, real kunefe is delicious.

</figcaption>

<p>Visiting Jordan during this period of time was an interesting experience. From a tourism perspective, it’s very clear that the war has had a devastating impact on the industry. During our first night in Dana, Kevin and I were the only people staying at the hotel. Many other times, it felt like we were one of many two or three other total groups at the hotel. All the sites we visited felt really empty and many shops and restaurants were shut close to the popular sites. We learned from research online that Jordan’s tourism industry was especially booming before 2011 and then post Arab-spring, tourism plummeted by around 70 percent. It started to pick back up again towards the latter half of the decade before it was decimated again by COVID. And then started to recover again until October 7th, 2023 when once again, tourists fled. And since then, it hasn’t recovered. Our guide, Munthar, from our Dana to Petra trek grumbled that he had switched the dates of the trek from the 24th to the 22nd of October to accommodate a guy from Kuwait but as soon as the missiles flew overhead, the guy canceled the whole trip. Munthar joked that he didn’t understand why a Middle Eastern guy would cancel for some missiles as that’s just normal stuff around here. We laughed along, but that’s devastating to hear as a joke. We felt very safe during our time in Jordan and there were no obvious signs of disturbances in the country due to its neighbors except for one thing: the GPS had been spoofed by the Israeli military so that it looked like you were at the Queen Alia International Airport in Amman. This was especially true close to the border in the Aqaba and Dead Sea area. For some people, it would jump to Cairo. This had been ongoing since October 7th so people in Jordan were used to it to some extent, but it definitely threw off tourists who relied on GPS and Google Maps to get around. Luckily, there’s pretty much just three highways in Jordan that run north-south and there are enough signs to point you to how to get on one of the highways or major tourist sites so navigation was pretty easy even without GPS. I was also lucky that my phone, after a few restarts, would sometimes be able to overcome the spoofing at least long enough to get us on the highway so we were able to skirt having any problems without GPS. Also, when it was really bad, we reverted back to our MapQuest era (remember MapQuest?!) by looking up the directions from point to point beforehand, noting any important landmarks to signal turns, and then driving according to the pre-planned route.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/road-tripping-around-jordan/jerash_jordan_18.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A happy cat and a happy Kevin in Jerash.

</figcaption>

<p>Humans have been around in this area of the world for a <em>long</em> time. So have dinosaurs. It really didn’t register with me before we came to Jordan, exactly how crazy old some of the remains here are. Many of the places we visited in Jordan were ancient ruins that were built like baklava, layer upon layer of historical eras, each of which has left its imprint on the site until around 749 AD when a huge earthquake (~7-7.5) hit the area and decimated many freestanding structures (but not many of the Petra structures that were carved directly into the rock which is why it’s so spectacular!). Post-earthquake, some sites were rebuilt during the Umayyad period (start of the Islamic period) but many were abandoned. Stone, Bronze, Iron, Classical, and Middle ages – you can see them all here, and all within a single location. I never got tired of especially seeing the flint tools from TEN THOUSAND years ago or seeing ancient idols demonstrating very early forms of religion like the two-headed plaster bust that might be one of the earliest examples of a human-worshipped thing from 7500 BC (the Neolithic period) or seeing shards of beautifully preserved pottery and glass from thousands of years ago and seeing the craft develop and beautify over hundreds and thousands of years. Nearly all the museums we visited as an accompaniment to the ancient site itself had artifacts from up to 10,000 years ago, if not older. </p>

<p><img src="images/amman_jordan_39.jpg" alt="A Roman theater" /></p>

<p><img src="images/amman_jordan_39.jpg" alt="A Roman theater" /></p>

<p>A Roman theater</p>

<p>This Roman Theater is smack in the middle of the city of Amman.</p>

<p><img src="images/amman_jordan_9.jpg" alt="Amman Citadel" /></p>

<p><img src="images/amman_jordan_9.jpg" alt="Amman Citadel" /></p>

<p>Amman Citadel</p>

<p>The area where the citadel is located has been populated since Neolithic times.</p>

<p><img src="images/jerash_jordan_2.jpg" alt="The Arch of Hadrian in Jerash" /></p>

<p><img src="images/jerash_jordan_2.jpg" alt="The Arch of Hadrian in Jerash" /></p>

<p>The Arch of Hadrian in Jerash</p>

<p>Jerash is an ancient city about an hour’s drive outside of Amman. The city was founded by Alexander the Great and was originally called Gerasa. This gate was built to honor Emperor Hadrian’s visit to the city in 129 AD.</p>

<p><img src="images/pella_jordan_12.jpg" alt="Bronze Age ruins at Pella" /></p>

<p><img src="images/pella_jordan_12.jpg" alt="Bronze Age ruins at Pella" /></p>

<p>Bronze Age ruins at Pella</p>

<p>This may not look like much but this was some ruins below the ancient city of Pella from the Bronze Age!</p>

<p><img src="images/umm_qays_jordan_8.jpg" alt="Umm Qays" /></p>

<p><img src="images/umm_qays_jordan_8.jpg" alt="Umm Qays" /></p>

<p>Umm Qays</p>

<p>Umm Qais used to be known as Garada in ancient times. It is located on the northern border of Jordan close to Syria.</p>

<p><img src="images/pella_jordan_4.jpg" alt="The ancient city of Pella" /></p>

<p><img src="images/pella_jordan_4.jpg" alt="The ancient city of Pella" /></p>

<p>The ancient city of Pella</p>

<p><img src="images/amman_jordan_39.jpg" alt="A Roman theater" /></p>

<p><img src="images/amman_jordan_9.jpg" alt="Amman Citadel" /></p>

<p><img src="images/jerash_jordan_2.jpg" alt="The Arch of Hadrian in Jerash" /></p>

<p><img src="images/pella_jordan_12.jpg" alt="Bronze Age ruins at Pella" /></p>

<p><img src="images/umm_qays_jordan_8.jpg" alt="Umm Qays" /></p>

<p><img src="images/pella_jordan_4.jpg" alt="The ancient city of Pella" /></p>

<p>One rather interesting “museum” we went to in Amman was the Royal Automobile Museum. Apparently the father of the current king of Jordan was a huge car enthusiast and the huge warehouse showcased a bunch of his shiny expensive cars. I thought it might be a little cheesy, but it was genuinely a pretty cool museum with an impressive collection of vehicles plus vehicles from movies that were filmed in Wadi Rum like Star Wars and The Martian. The vast sandy landscape with red cliffs of Wadi Rum is a popular movie set location for any movie that involves desert landscapes or alien planets including the two previously mentioned, Dune, Transformers, and Star Trek. Of course there were some Bugattis and Ferraris as well. </p>

<p>On the subject of the king. In Jordan, one is technically not allowed to insult or be disrespectful of royalty in an offense that is called <em>lèse-majesté,</em> punishable by law usually with jail time. Because of this, it was really hard to get a read on how Jordanians thought about anything politics related. I ended up getting most of my information from our trekking companion, Esther, who had been living in Amman for the last year on a two-year work project, but originally from the UK. What I learned is that people in Jordan have mixed feelings; on one hand, people were frustrated by the level of poverty in the country and lack of support from the government but at the same time, observed the poorer quality of life in nearly every single one of their neighboring countries and felt grateful not to be a war zone. This law also meant that there were no demonstrations, no signs or displays, and hardly any graffiti (and trust me, there was a ton of graffiti other than declarations of love or just writing names or whatever else all over the parks) that were political in nature. I learned that about 25-30% of Jordan’s population are non-residents with the majority coming from either Palestine or Syria so I figured people might have some opinions, but they were definitely not shown.</p>

<p>One big highlight of our Jordan tour was the Dead Sea. Going into it, I thought it might be a cool experience but didn’t expect to be so fun that we made time to experience it twice. We stayed at a fancy-ish western hotel that had a private beach access and fresh water showers very close to the shore’s edge. My experience with the Dead Sea really begins on the first day that we arrived in the Dead Sea area, the day before we actually went into the Dead Sea. We had done a “hiking” trail which was more of a “wading” trail through a place called Wadi Mujib. A “wadi” is just a dry riverbed though seasonally, it can have running water. This “wadi” has at least a bit of water nearly year-round with the water levels starting to rise around November. It was super fun hiking up the river with some ropes and ladders set up to go up some waterfalls until at last you reach a larger waterfall that cannot be scaled (I think they used to have a canyoning program to scale that one too but it has been closed for at least one year). Then to come back down, you can float along the river whenever the water is deep enough and some of the waterfalls had some slippery rocks that you could use as a slide to plop yourself down. I, not very smartly, decided to continue to try to float down the river even when the water was very shallow so I got my butt scraped up quite a bit by some small rocks, though I didn’t really notice it at the time. It’s a gorgeous canyon with beautiful swirly walls and we went back a second time, just up to the first waterfall area with our camera to take photos because we couldn’t bring our camera the first time (it would have gotten drenched).</p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_3.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_3.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_3.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_3.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_28.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_28.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_28.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_28.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_42.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_42.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_42.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_42.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_21.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_21.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_21.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_21.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_3.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_3.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_28.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_28.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_42.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_42.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/siq_trail_jordan_21.jpg" alt="siq_trail_jordan_21.jpg" /></p>

<p>Well, the next day, as I waded into the 34% salinity lake, every single one of those tiny scrapes on my butt made itself known. Ouch! I learned about all the tiny cuts and nicks that were all over my body (as did Kevin) as I gritted my teeth and went in anyways. Where did all these come from?! Thankfully, in not too long, my body seemed to get used to the salty water and we had a great time trying to sink ourselves, a complete impossibility, and floating around. We learned that there used to be one company (more like a single person who runs a side hustle) that runs scuba dives in the Dead Sea and each diver needs around 100 pounds of weights to be able to sink below the surface. Not sinking is really an amazing feeling; especially for me who cannot tread water and had to cheat on my treading water portion of my swim test in order to take a sailing class in grad school. Tada! Now I can “tread water!” We both could basically stand straight up. Floating tummy-side down was, funnily enough, a challenge because my legs would shoot straight up into the air and nearly make me faceplant which was dangerous because getting even a single drop of salt water into the eyes would mean instant burning. We watched as one unsuspecting visitor decided to try to swim in the water and dove in with goggles and almost immediately lurched out and ran to the showers to flush out his eyes. Pro tip: have a bottle of fresh water right at the shore so that you can flush out your eyes immediately instead of running half-blindingly over to the showers which are at least one set of staircases away. The hotel also supplied Dead Sea mud that was sourced from the southern Dead Sea; there’s a north and south Dead Sea that are separated by land (they used to be connected) but the south Dead Sea is not a place where one can visit as it is primarily used by companies that harvest bromine and potash there for export. The excessive harvesting is also one of the reasons why the Dead Sea is rapidly disappearing, its shoreline receding by about one meter each year. The Dead Sea mud might be one of the first “beauty” products that we’ve used that really lives up to the hype: we both generously slathered on the mud and sat on the edge of the lake, waiting for it to dry. Then we went into the lake to rinse it off and voila, we were both baby butt smooth. Apparently the oiliness of the lake also helps with the effect. For those (including us) wishing to replicate the effect at home, we learned that all exported “Dead Sea” products simply take the <em>salt</em> harvested from the south Dead Sea and mix it with generic, mass produced mud. Easier to ship over just the salt, I guess. Alas, I guess we’ll have to come back to Jordan one day!</p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241013_145544817.jpg" alt="Sunset over the Dead Sea." /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241013_145544817.jpg" alt="Sunset over the Dead Sea." /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241013_115811708.jpg" alt="PXL_20241013_115811708.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241013_115811708.jpg" alt="PXL_20241013_115811708.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241013_125447156.jpg" alt="PXL_20241013_125447156.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241013_125447156.jpg" alt="PXL_20241013_125447156.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/dead_sea_jordan_4.jpg" alt="dead_sea_jordan_4.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/dead_sea_jordan_4.jpg" alt="dead_sea_jordan_4.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241013_145544817.jpg" alt="Sunset over the Dead Sea." /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241013_115811708.jpg" alt="PXL_20241013_115811708.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/PXL_20241013_125447156.jpg" alt="PXL_20241013_125447156.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/dead_sea_jordan_4.jpg" alt="dead_sea_jordan_4.jpg" /></p>

<p>Besides the Siq Trail in Wadi Mujib, we did a handful of other treks during our ten day road trip of Jordan. We did a gorgeous trek from Dana (our “amuse bouche” of the Jordan Trail) called Wadi Ghuweir that started in a town called Mansoura and ended in a small town called Feynan that used to be a hub for copper production and now has one of the most famous ecolodges in the world. The trail followed the shallow waters downstream and we enjoyed dipping into one of the natural pools where some of the river water congregated. We met a couple of women from Belgium in Wadi Rum earlier who suggested we take swimsuits and we ended up dipping into the wrong pool (there was a more obvious larger one later, but we didn’t know exactly which pool they were talking about at the time), but it was still delightful. This wadi was especially unique for having palm trees growing off the walls of the canyon, leaning across the span of the gorge. The greenery against the red walls was stunning!</p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_38.jpg" alt="A cool frog near the end of Wadi Ghuweir." /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_38.jpg" alt="A cool frog near the end of Wadi Ghuweir." /></p>

<p>A cool frog near the end of Wadi Ghuweir.</p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_27.jpg" alt="wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_27.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_27.jpg" alt="wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_27.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_29.jpg" alt="wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_29.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_29.jpg" alt="wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_29.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_12.jpg" alt="wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_12.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_12.jpg" alt="wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_12.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/shobak_castle_jordan_26.jpg" alt="Full moon in Dana on my birthday!" /></p>

<p><img src="images/shobak_castle_jordan_26.jpg" alt="Full moon in Dana on my birthday!" /></p>

<p>Full moon in Dana on my birthday!</p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_38.jpg" alt="A cool frog near the end of Wadi Ghuweir." /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_27.jpg" alt="wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_27.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_29.jpg" alt="wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_29.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_12.jpg" alt="wadi_ghweir_dana_jordan_12.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/shobak_castle_jordan_26.jpg" alt="Full moon in Dana on my birthday!" /></p>

<p>We also did another wadi hike, Wadi Al Hasa, on the way from the Dead Sea to Aqaba which was nearly completely deserted. We had a bit of a rough start as there were tons of flies and trash on the trail, but eventually we got far enough that the flies stopped bothering us. There were tons of flies near the Dead Sea (outside of the resort area) as well; we stopped to take some photos of the salt formations but I was sprinting both to and from the water’s edge, wildly swinging around my camera to both take photos and swat flies at the same time. I’ve had to delete a lot of those insane angle photos. It was punishingly hot near Wadi Al Hasa though so we didn’t end up spending too long. Fun fact: at 430 meters below sea level, it’s harder to get sunburned because of the thickness of the atmosphere! Probably good anyways because I’m sure standard sunscreen has not been manufactured to withstand a body of water that is nine times saltier than the ocean. I have one particular bone to pick with many of the hikes that we did in Jordan though; people throw their trash on the ground! I got stabbed in the toe by a piece of trash towards the end of the Wadi Ghuweir hike (hey, at least it’s not a needle) but in general, there’s tons of bottles, plastic, wrappers, everything just floating around. It’s so bad that Munthar, on seeing a plastic bag float through the air ahead of us, quipped “observe, our national bird of Jordan.” The floating plastic bags seem particularly egregious to me. Esther again provided some perspective here though (she’s a statistician) that once countries reach a certain threshold of GDP per capita, then putting trash into trash bins (and more generally, intentionally moving the country in a direction away from being a “pollution haven”) will become more of a citizen’s/government’s concern. Below that, people have more pressing concerns than where to place their trash, which does make sense. There’s been a lot of debate about this Environment’s Kuznets Curve, but I found a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-024-02639-9">2024 paper</a> that seemed to at least support the inverted U-shaped curve between economic growth and environmental degradation. Of course, as with a lot of stats, there are lots of nuances.</p>

<p>Wadi Rum is probably the second most famous place in Jordan after Petra and is known for its Mars-like landscapes with stunning red cliffs. We spent two nights in Wadi Rum with one of the days spent going around to different highlights of the desert while riding in the bed of a modified pickup truck. Here, we met two lovely Belgian women who gave us a bunch of excellent tips for our future Jordan plans. A Bedouin showed us around to different sites within Wadi Rum; he showed us a technique of scooching our butts up a narrow crack to climb up the walls to a nice shaded spot that <em>I think</em> usually has a pool but at the time we were there, was just a flat of mud. On this excursion, we learned about exactly how sweet Bedouin tea is: the first tent where we got tea, we thought “oh that’s pretty sweet, but tasty enough.” The second cup was “oh my god, it’s just sugar water.” I had not quite learned this at this point yet, but many cups of sugar water were about to be a staple in my future. The Bedouins drink their tea right into the night (my Westernized brain remains horrified about the level of caffeine and sugar that is in the body as folks turn in for bed… how do they sleep?!) and it feels a bit disrespectful to turn down tea so we sipped and sipped the sugar water as slowly as we could. We ended this evening by hanging out in the sand, watching the sun set as our Bedouin guide boiled water, sugar, and leaves again for some evening cups of <em>shai</em>.</p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_17.jpg" alt="Climbing up the crack in the canyon!" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_17.jpg" alt="Climbing up the crack in the canyon!" /></p>

<p>Climbing up the crack in the canyon!</p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_27.jpg" alt="wadi_rum_jordan_27.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_27.jpg" alt="wadi_rum_jordan_27.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_33.jpg" alt="wadi_rum_jordan_33.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_33.jpg" alt="wadi_rum_jordan_33.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_54.jpg" alt="A Bedouin and his camels" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_54.jpg" alt="A Bedouin and his camels" /></p>

<p>A Bedouin and his camels</p>

<p>This Bedouin milked the camel and we tried camel milk which was much better than the fermented camel milk we tried in Kazakhstan but quite fatty. A couple sips were plenty.</p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_94.jpg" alt="wadi_rum_jordan_94.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_94.jpg" alt="wadi_rum_jordan_94.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241016_153012.jpg" alt="20241016_153012.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241016_153012.jpg" alt="20241016_153012.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_17.jpg" alt="Climbing up the crack in the canyon!" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_27.jpg" alt="wadi_rum_jordan_27.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_33.jpg" alt="wadi_rum_jordan_33.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_54.jpg" alt="A Bedouin and his camels" /></p>

<p><img src="images/wadi_rum_jordan_94.jpg" alt="wadi_rum_jordan_94.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241016_153012.jpg" alt="20241016_153012.jpg" /></p>

<p>Before we visited Wadi Rum, we made a short one day stop at the southern tip of Jordan in a city called Aqaba. Or “Aghabeh” if you’re a man. In Arabic, words are pronounced differently based on your gender. Men pronounce the words more aggressively than women so the “k” sound becomes more like a “gh” and “a” becomes a grunt-like “eh.” Aqaba is famous for being a great place for snorkeling and diving and we found a company that did a boat trip out to the Red Sea where you had a choice between snorkeling or diving, but both could be done at the same site. In Türkiye, Kevin had injured his ear while cliff jumping (our guess is that it was some sort of barotrauma) and diving in Mozambique unfortunately aggravated the injury even though we thought it had healed so we were looking for places where I could potentially dive and Kevin could snorkel. Luckily Aqaba was just the perfect location; the water visibility is 20+ meters so both of us could see things really well in the water. We got on a boat that was, again, nearly empty and the whole time we were lounging on the deck, we thought, oh I’m sure another large snorkeling group will show up. Nope, never did. I think I now understand the appeal of private yachts! There was just one other person who had a diving license on the boat and two others who were diving for the first time so each pair got a Divemaster. I was very lucky to dive with a guy, who originally was from the UK but currently living in East Jerusalem, who had done hundreds of dives before. I let both the Divemaster and him know it was my first dive post Open Water license so they were able to give me some great advice after each dive on how to improve (I’m currently really bad at staying in one spot while doing a three minute safety stop which isn’t great because it sort of defeats the purpose of the safety stop) and were generally really encouraging. We got to snorkel/dive at two places: one which highlighted some amazing reefs that were actually teeming with wildlife and another which was a wreck site. The wreck site was a plane that people had intentionally sunk around thirty years ago after having a party. They had ripped out most of the interiors and picked a place where there was little reef to sink it. Since then, new reefs had started to grow on the plane and there were a bunch of lionfish hiding under the seats. I really enjoyed this wreck dive, especially swimming through the plane door and out one of the cavities where an engine used to be. A dummy skeleton had been placed in one of the bathrooms, which thankfully our Divemaster warned us about because I probably would have mildly freaked out and instead it was hilarious to see.</p>

<p><img src="images/GOPR7517+%281%29.jpg" alt="GOPR7517 (1).jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/GOPR7517+%281%29.jpg" alt="GOPR7517 (1).jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/GOPR7533.jpg" alt="GOPR7533.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/GOPR7533.jpg" alt="GOPR7533.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/GOPR7551.jpg" alt="GOPR7551.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/GOPR7551.jpg" alt="GOPR7551.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/GOPR7517+%281%29.jpg" alt="GOPR7517 (1).jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/GOPR7533.jpg" alt="GOPR7533.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/GOPR7551.jpg" alt="GOPR7551.jpg" /></p>

<p>Our last two days on our road trip were spent driving from the Dana Biosphere Reserve up to Madaba and visiting the various churches and sights in Madaba. Driving the King’s Highway was such a wonderful experience; the views are really stunning as the highway winds its way through the hills. Thankfully our car did well cruising up the mountains after the engine light came on on our first day with the car. One memorable stop was visiting the totally deserted Sela Castle which was populated as early as the Iron Age by Edomites. After visiting the ruins, we got a bit lost trying to figure out a way through what looked like a solid wall of rock and of course, there were no trails marked on Google Maps or Open Street Maps. Eventually, after some systematic depth first searching, we eventually found our way! </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/road-tripping-around-jordan/dana_to_madaba_kings_highway_5.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Sela Castle, where we briefly got lost!

</figcaption>

<p>In Madaba, we had a bit of a change of culture with the city peppered with tons of churches. The most famous one was St. George’s whose floor contains a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madaba_Map">mosaic</a> that is the oldest map of the Holy Land from the 6th century. Seeing that was very cool and also, we visited even more churches with larger and more stunning mosaics, including the Madaba Archeological Park, Apostles Church, St. John the Baptist Roman Catholic Church, and the Church of St. Steven’s (located not in Madaba, but in Umm ar-Rasas, another ancient Roman city). The mosaics are so beautiful! Too bad we don’t make beautiful floors like this anymore! Our last stop before heading back to Amman was to visit Mount Nebo, which is a place mentioned in the Bible as the location where Moses saw Jerusalem. The summit has a nice church, also with beautiful mosaics, and the top has really lovely views looking out to West Bank. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/road-tripping-around-jordan/madaba_34.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

One of the many mosaics we saw in gorgeous condition in an old Byzantine Church. This one was from the church atop Mount Nebo. Check out the depictions of “exotic” animals!

</figcaption>

<p>I actually really quite liked Madaba as a town. It felt a little more modern than Amman and we stayed at a great hotel with a young manager who was very easy to talk to and gave us a great recommendation for an amazing meal. We ate at the Carob House and had a meal with beer (gasp!) and had the most amazing <em>rashtayeh</em> (lentils, soft noodles, tamarind-pomegranate molasses, crispy onions, and sautéed garlic and coriander all in a delicious heap), and black seed tahini ice cream on a cookie crumble. Yum! Thinking about it is making me hungry again. And once we returned to Amman, we beelined straight back to Hashem’s for falafels and hummus and ful and to Habiba’s for hot kunefe which we ate right on the street as it should. I’ve sworn off falafels and hummus for the rest of the trip, if I can manage, because I think I’ll only have sad dry falafels from now on. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/road-tripping-around-jordan/wadi_rum_jordan_55.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

What I’ll look like when someone serves dry falafels.

</figcaption>

<p>Phew, this was a long one (and this is with me glossing over the half dozen or so ancient cities we visited) but it’s time to get this published since now we’re in Bhutan (yes, it’s taken me more than a week but I don’t write linearly so I’ve got a good chunk of the Dana to Petra post written up… to be published another time!). I’ll end by one last story which is that we had the cutest, clingiest cat at our last Airbnb in Amman. This cat showed up the day we arrived and would whine and whine at the door (but never came inside!) and so we fed the cat and gave it attention by sitting outside on a little table, doing planning and research outside. It didn’t really want pets but it just wanted us to be near. And occasionally would just plop itself right down on my laptop while I was doing something and decide that that was the moment to partake in some self-care grooming. I miss that kitty. And all the other kitties that I couldn’t resist petting and cuddling through my entire time in Amman. Kevin has <em>a lot</em> of photos now of me and cats. Probably too many :)</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/road-tripping-around-jordan/PXL_20241020_142154432.jpg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re on our way to Mumbai now, having departed Jordan early in the morning. It’s not often that I feel a bit melancholy leaving a place because I’m so looking forward to the next one. But with Jordan, as our driver kept saying “welcome to Jordan!” each time we gushed about another sight we enjoyed seeing in Jordan, I felt a bit sad to be leaving even though I am bonkers excited to be spending Diwali in India (a first for me!). I’ll miss the Jordanian hospitality that’s really on another level. I’ll miss visiting Hashem’s restaurant in Amman for cloud-like falafels and olive oil drenched hummus and ful and fatteh, where we ate five times in fewer than that many days (we learned that the owner is now in Bolivian prison for smuggling cocaine so uhhh maybe there was some other special ingredients in that hummus. No wonder it tasted so good). I’ll miss the sassy cats that want attention, but not too much attention, and definitely want food. ]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/road-tripping-around-jordan/wadi_rum_jordan_21.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/road-tripping-around-jordan/wadi_rum_jordan_21.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Istanbul, again!</title><link href="/istanbul-again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Istanbul, again!" /><published>2024-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/istanbul-again</id><content type="html" xml:base="/istanbul-again"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s (roughly) how our conversation went:</p>

<p>Arathi: “Hmm, it looks like the easiest way to get to Jordan is to fly through Istanbul. I see a flight that has a four hour layover which is pretty long, but it’s not bad.”</p>

<p>Kevin: “ICE CREAM! No, I’m just joking, obviously that would be crazy.”</p>

<p>… a beat passes… we stare at each other</p>

<p>Arathi: “There’s another flight later to Amman that gives us nine hours…”</p>

<p>And that is how we ended up spending another nine hours in Istanbul. Because we wanted to eat Turkish ice cream at <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/W7yQWWHFwsPKtXPS8">Bena Ice Cream</a> one more time, a joy that we were robbed off on our disastrous last day in Istanbul where everything was closed. If not on a full year of travel, when else can we arbitrarily decide that we want to revisit a city in a completely different country for one day just to eat ice cream?</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/istanbul-again/20241007_075225_001.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Hello again Hagia Sophia! At 7:30 in the morning!

</figcaption>

<p>We landed in Istanbul around 5:30 in the morning and made it into Sultanahmet, the old town with all the main sights of Istanbul, by 6:30am. We dropped off our bags at a hotel (<a href="https://www.nannybag.com/en">Nannybag</a> is a fantastic app for luggage storage!) and wandered into a börek cafe, one of the <em>very few</em> things open in Istanbul that early. A few locals were nursing cups of çay and a plate of chopped börek that had literally <em>just</em> been pulled out. We did the same. My goodness. Food. And tea. After some sad meals (for vegetarian me) in our last days in Kazakhstan, one bite and I was in complete and utter bliss. Also, how did we miss this place last time we were here?! Right smack dab in the middle of tourist central, but with local prices and quality! We’ve eaten a lot of börek now to know what good börek tastes like. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/istanbul-again/PXL_20241007_040152444.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

This is just what we need to kick our butts awake.

</figcaption>

<p>It was an odd feeling to be back in Istanbul. It felt akin to going back home after a trip; we knew where places were, we recalled the different mosques and monuments, we knew where the German Fountain was to fill up our water bottles for free. We didn’t feel any obligation to visit any famous tourist sites. We <em>did</em> feel obligated to pet as many cats as possible. We found the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/QkwrDzurmT7sCKdN8">Sleeping Dog</a>. Sleeping Dog woke up and followed us around for a bit. It was quiet with hardly a tourist around in front of Hagia Sophia at seven in the morning. We wandered into a park that we had previously visited and watched as a pack of dogs leaped around their favorite park security guard who had brought breakfast for them. We watched as a scuba diver emerged from the Bosphorus with a huge net of mussels to be sold at a stall later with stuffed rice. We watched as two men dove into the Bosphorus for a morning swim while a cat purred in our laps. It had just rained before we had arrived so the air felt cool, the benches a little damp, and the weather surprisingly brisk. Nothing that yet another çay from a cafe that hadn’t really even opened couldn’t fix.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/istanbul-again/PXL_20241007_053630890.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Kitty found a nice place to nap.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/istanbul-again/20241007_075949.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

We found the Sleeping Dog (who was not asleep) in front of the Blue Mosque.

</figcaption>

<p>We found an “arkeopark” randomly next to the cafe that we explored for a bit. An ancient city called Sarayburnu used to exist where this little park now exists and used to extend to where Topkapi Palace now stands. The whole area around the park is very modern with little shops, cafes and a boardwalk to walk along the water. But this little park was created to showcase some of the ancient building remnants that we found. Incredible that these ruins from early Byzantine times are just scattered in the middle of the city! And it’s not even reviewed on Google Maps!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/istanbul-again/20241007_092015.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>By this time, the museums and mosques were opening so we meandered back to the main tourist area. Here’s a pro tip: don’t go to a mosque when it opens. The lines to get into the Blue Mosque were <em>insane</em>. We saw a cruise ship docked nearby so maybe it was unusual and it looked like the line was made up of several smaller groups that belonged to the same tour company so maybe they were all from the boat. But thankfully, our destination was the much less visited Turkish and Islamic Arts Museum. </p>

<p>Some of these smaller museums really are wonderful gems. We had a similar experience visiting Paris and skipping the Louvre in favor of some of the smaller less-visited ones like the Fondation Louis Vuitton. The Turkish and Islamic Arts Museum was the same. The museum had a piece of the hippodrome that originally existed in the area but was almost entirely destroyed. Around it, they have a collection of arts, rugs, and my favorite, books from hundreds if not a thousand years ago. Why don’t we make rugs like these anymore? They are gorgeous and unique and tell a story. I have resolved to find some place to commission a rug like this one day when we have a home. Might need to start a savings plan to buy a rug like that though. I’ve been taking tons of photos of patterns and art to one day use as inspiration for our own home and also for cake decorating!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/istanbul-again/PXL_20241007_081447325.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Pages from an ornate Quran. 

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/istanbul-again/20241007_114014.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A rug replicating an oil painting of Constantinople. 

</figcaption>

<p>Last, but not least… the moment we’ve been waiting for. ICE CREAM! Yes, it’s a lot of enthusiasm for ice cream. We were both a bit nervous heading there because what if it wasn’t as good as we remembered?! It was. IT WAS SO GOOD. Worth every lira (not that it cost much lira at all). We got a scoop of caramel and a scoop of chocolate and also a plate of künefe (no cheese) with a scoop of vanilla. The locals know the trick; I dare say the künefe + vanilla was a revelation. My mouth is watering right now even as I’m typing these words. It was 1000% worth it to come back to Istanbul for this treat. I get it, Eric Adams.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/istanbul-again/PXL_20241007_090237199.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

What we came to Istanbul for.

</figcaption>

<p>We trundled back to fetch our bags (with the amount of sweet treats in our stomach, we were not managing any speed more than a trundle) and finally headed to the airport for our onward flight to Amman. In the end, we actually could have spent an additional few hours at the airport. We were flying with Jordan Aviation and when we arrived at the airport, our flight wasn’t listed at all on the board. I had a moment of panic thinking that we had gone to the wrong airport (and yes, I’ve done this before in Toronto so it was well warranted panic), but in reality, the airline had decided to move the flight to a later time and not notified anyone. Luckily we found an agent who was part of the airline who told us there was still a flight (and who disappeared shortly thereafter) and we waited along with the rest of the passengers in a line for a few hours, none of us knowing that our flight was delayed about five hours. You know, everyone was super relaxed for having to wait in line for hours. Usually I witness shouting and fist shaking and probably someone filming the whole thing to chuck on social media but I guess there really wasn’t anyone around to yell at. Most folks sat around and found some tea or coffee or snacks to munch on while we waited. <br />
We beelined for one of the best lounges in the world after we got through security and re-indulged on more Turkish mezzes and a glass of wine before heading to the gate. At the gate, we waited around a little bit longer, watching several of the men take their shoes off, one leading the group of strangers in prayer as it was <em>Maghrib</em>. A sign that we truly were about to step into the Middle East. But that’ll come in another post!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/istanbul-again/20241007_073928.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Istanbul truly is run by cats.

</figcaption>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here’s (roughly) how our conversation went:]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/istanbul-again/PXL_20241007_081447325.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/istanbul-again/PXL_20241007_081447325.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mangystau: Salt, Water and Oil</title><link href="/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mangystau: Salt, Water and Oil" /><published>2024-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil</id><content type="html" xml:base="/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil"><![CDATA[<p>The owner of the car rental business we used in Almaty said, when she learned of our plans to visit Aktau in Western Kazakhstan, “Aktau is not like Almaty. Be prepared. People are not as friendly.” She also warned us that people do not speak as much English in Aktau. After spending over a week in the Aktau and larger Mangystau region, I think only the part about English really stands. Kazakhstan continues to have some of the nicest and most friendly people we’ve met while traveling, and our five day overlanding trip was magnificent, showing off Kazakhstan’s truly striking and dramatic landscapes, unlike places we’ve been before.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20240926_193005.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The view of the Caspian Sea from the restaurant we ate at in Aktau. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p>The Mangystau region of Kazakhstan is a peculiar place. It used to be pretty much a dead zone (in modern times… there have always been some nomadic activity) until around the 18th century when Russia (the Soviet Union at the time) took a particular interest in the region because of its ambitions to expand into Central Asia. In the 20th century, the real treasure was found plentifully in the region: oil and gas. Bam. Cities like Aktau and Atyrau sprung up to shelter the growing population employed by oil companies. The locals call them “oil men.” During our visit to Aktau, we could see huge residential complexes actively being built that evinced continued growth of the region. Another signal: staring at vast expanses of land peppered with pumpjacks continuously lifting Kazakhstan’s 1.8 million barrels of oil every single day. This was the first time I’ve seen part of the physical process of harvesting the oil that the world so depends on. It wasn’t pretty and it looked really weird to see so many of these machines continuing bobbing up and down like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drinking_bird">drinking birds</a>.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/PXL_20241006_065233907+%281%29.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>We ended up spending much longer than planned in Aktau. Our original plan was to spend just a couple days in the city to visit the few sites there and then to do the overlanding trip ourselves across the Mangystau region. We ended up deciding not to do it because we’ve never planned and executed our own 4x4 trip and doing a multi-day tour in a country where we also cannot speak the language seemed like probably not the best idea. We were in the midst of planning how we might be able to do day trips to and from Aktau to visit some of the sites when we stumbled across one of the only companies in the area that does overlanding trips for tourists and they happened to be running a five day version several days after we were planning our own. After figuring out that we’d just need to make sure to fly out of the country the very next day because we would hit the thirty day stay limit in Kazakhstan, we signed up for the tour. And breathed perhaps a sigh of relief that we wouldn’t have to try to figure out everything from how to rent camping gear, where to camp, how much water to bring, how to do navigation in an area without roads, and more. </p>

<p>That gave us quite some time to kill in Aktau and it isn’t really a city with a ton of things to do so we ended up making significant progress on planning for Jordan instead. It’s worked out really well; as I write this, I’m in the middle of a desert in Jordan called Wadi Rum. We’ve had full days in Jordan because we haven’t had to spend too much time planning and it’s been nice to go from place to place with hotels/Airbnbs and excursions booked in advance. A bit of a departure from the seat-of-our-pants style planning we’ve done at times! The only real thing of note that we did in Aktau was visit a trail called the Rock Trail that was a long boardwalk that bordered the Caspian Sea coast. It was a really lovely walk on a very nicely made wooden path… except for certain parts where they decided to use some sort of tile that was <em>incredibly</em> slippery. Why on earth did they choose those plastic tiles?! Both Kevin and I slipped multiple times and we could literally skate on it in our flip flops. The sea cliffs were actually quite stunning as well; towering titanium white that reminded us of the chalky white cliffs of Møns Klint in Denmark.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20240929_163919.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Rock Trail along the Caspian Sea. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20240929_181716.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Caspian Sea. There wasn’t really a nice area to swim in, but we did walk through some of the super shallow waters (a bit sludge-y though!). PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p><strong>Day 1</strong></p>

<p>We got picked up from our apartments and driven to the office where we ended up having to pare down to one bag for the two of us. The car was <em>packed</em> to the brim with luggage and equipment for our adventure so we didn’t have space for spare luggage. We met our companions for the trip: Betty, a lovely woman from Vancouver, Baygazy, our driver, and Aars, our guide. The five of us were a tight fit in the car, but we settled in nicely and our adventure began! We met folks from a second car that also traveled with us: Fei and Moono from China, Igor from Poland, and their car’s driver, Ayan. I’ve mentioned this in a lot of past posts but having wonderful folks to travel with on these multi-day tours really knocks the experience up a level. We are really happy that we got to travel with these fantastic people who provided us with plenty of good company, chit chat and laughter.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241002_110937.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Baygazy and Betty in front. Us and Aars in the back. Packed in! PC: Betty.

</figcaption>

<p>It didn’t take too long before our cars left the perimeter of the city and suddenly we were out in the middle of nowhere with camels and horses wandering the lonely steppes of Kazakhstan. Because we had a bit of a slow start (partially our fault due to our luggage and also a miscommunication about when the car had arrived to pick us up), our first stop was lunch. Here, I learned exactly how unusually it is to be a vegetarian in Kazakhstan. I fielded questions about exactly what I ate and how I managed to be alive by our curious drivers and guide. As for what I ate for lunch: I got a plate of rice with the meat taken out, given away by the stray piece of meat that was hidden in the bottom of the plate. I think I might have been their first-ever vegetarian. I was also amused by how quickly we got into personal life details while passing around a glass of fermented camel milk to share. Very quickly, everyone has a dossier on every other person: where are you from (a nice tame start), what do you do (also tame), how old are you, are you married, how long have you been married, do you have children, how many children, how old are the children, are you going to have children, where are your parents from, and probably more questions that I’ve forgotten now, but by the end of lunch, lets just say that all ice was shattered to smithereens. And regarding the fermented camel’s milk – it tasted like soured yogurt. Not my favorite but I could certainly see how it could be an acquired taste. Our drivers warned us not to drink too much because it may cause some stomach issues for the untrained stomach but no one was voluntarily drinking quite enough for that to be a major concern. Not as bad as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kashk"><em>kurt</em></a> though (aside: in Jordan, I tried a version of this called <em>jameed</em> which was actually quite yummy, so I think preparation can make a difference).</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241002_121617.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Here we go! Plus a side of camels. PC: Betty.

</figcaption>

<p>After lunch, we headed out to the various sites for the day. Most days were pretty similar in that there were somewhere between three to four stops planned and at each stop, we’d get out of the vehicles to walk around and take pictures. Sometimes places would involve a small hike. Sometimes places would just be a panorama viewpoint to take pictures and perhaps have a meal. Our first day, we visited Torysh valley, also known as Valley of the Balls, a view point of Sherkala mountain, which is the mountain that apparently looks like a lion but I couldn’t really see it, hiked through Kok-kala tract, and set up camp around the Airakty Valley of Castles, a place that was named by a Ukrainian poet who was exiled to Kazakhstan who also made a bunch of drawings of the mountains in the mid-1800s.</p>

<p>I’m not sure if <em>ironic</em> is the word I’m looking for right now, but let’s use it; I find it ironic that the reason why Western Kazakhstan is rich with oil is the same reason why its landscape is so alien and <em>sui generis</em>. This land used to be covered by oceans (the <a href="https://www.britannica.com/place/Tethys-Sea">Tethys Sea</a>) millions of years ago. These oceans had microscopic organisms whose remains settled into the ocean floor between layers of sediment. These layers are starkly visible in many of the sites that we visited, either in the strata of towering cliffs or in the onion-like layers of the rock balls in <em>Torysh</em>. As the ocean vanished and wind and rain blasted through the area, the sandstone transformed into the stunning monuments that dot the former sea floor. As for the sea creatures’ remains, add heat, add pressure and these became hydrocarbons that accumulated in the sandstone, eventually drawn out by the pumpjacks. I can’t believe this never clicked before for me, but this process is why oil is considered to be a <em>fossil</em> fuel.</p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-222.jpg" alt="Torysh valley. Kevin for size." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-222.jpg" alt="Torysh valley. Kevin for size." /></p>

<p>Torysh valley. Kevin for size.</p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-194.jpg" alt="Sherkala Mountain" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-194.jpg" alt="Sherkala Mountain" /></p>

<p>Sherkala Mountain</p>

<p><img src="images/20241002-PA020067.jpg" alt="Kok-kala Tract." /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241002-PA020067.jpg" alt="Kok-kala Tract." /></p>

<p>Kok-kala Tract.</p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-208.jpg" alt="Kok-kala Tract." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-208.jpg" alt="Kok-kala Tract." /></p>

<p>Kok-kala Tract.</p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-214.jpg" alt="Torysh valley." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-214.jpg" alt="Torysh valley." /></p>

<p>Torysh valley.</p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-204.jpg" alt="Kok-kala Tract from the top." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-204.jpg" alt="Kok-kala Tract from the top." /></p>

<p>Kok-kala Tract from the top.</p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-194.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-194.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-194.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-194.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-221.jpg" alt="Torysh valley." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-221.jpg" alt="Torysh valley." /></p>

<p>Torysh valley.</p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-204.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-204.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-204.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-204.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-221.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-221.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-221.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-221.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-234.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-234.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-234.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-234.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-214.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-214.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-214.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-214.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-234.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-234.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-234.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-234.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-221.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-221.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-221.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-221.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-204.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-204.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-204.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-204.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-234.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-234.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-234.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-234.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241002-PA020067.jpg" alt="20241002-PA020067.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241002-PA020067.jpg" alt="20241002-PA020067.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-222.jpg" alt="Torysh valley. Kevin for size." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-194.jpg" alt="Sherkala Mountain" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241002-PA020067.jpg" alt="Kok-kala Tract." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-208.jpg" alt="Kok-kala Tract." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-214.jpg" alt="Torysh valley." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-204.jpg" alt="Kok-kala Tract from the top." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-194.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-194.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-221.jpg" alt="Torysh valley." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-204.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-204.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-221.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-221.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-234.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-234.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-214.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-214.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-234.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-234.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-221.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-221.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-204.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-204.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-234.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-234.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241002-PA020067.jpg" alt="20241002-PA020067.jpg" /></p>

<p>We ended this evening at the Valley of Castles, setting up our wild camp at the base of the hills. We weren’t sure if we were going to end up camping this evening because the weather was variable and if it started to rain, the whole area would turn into a mud pile which is not great for camping but even less great for the cars to drive out of the mud the next day. Thankfully, the weather held and after setting up camp, we had some dinner and went to bed. Apparently that night there were some distant thunderstorms and strong winds but both Kevin and I slept right through!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/mangystau_trip-175.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Valley of Castles.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/IMG_1787.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Dinner with everyone! PC: Igor.

</figcaption>

<p><strong>Day 2</strong></p>

<p>The second day was pretty relaxed. After each breakfast, Aars would gently kick us out of the camp so that they could pack up by saying “you can go for a walk [points in a random direction] that way.” We got the message so we’d start wandering around in random directions until the cars would honk to signal us to come back. If we were far enough, the cars would drive over to grab us. One thing that was really nice about this tour was that there was plenty of time for self-exploration. Each day wasn’t too packed and for each site, we got the freedom to explore the area on our own and go for some short hikes without getting babysat. Our first stop on day 2 at Ybykty Canyon was a good example. We walked together with Aars for a little bit as we peered down the sponge-looking canyon from the top. We then explored the chasm on our own, creating our own musical instrument of sorts by banging on the arachnoid walls. Aars told us that previous tourists likened the canyon patterns to “Italian lingerie.” If this is what Italian lingerie looks like, well, uhh, interesting. I’ve decided not to ruin my Google search history by searching on the internet.</p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-160.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-160.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-160.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-160.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-150.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-150.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-150.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-150.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241003-PA030157.jpg" alt="20241003-PA030157.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241003-PA030157.jpg" alt="20241003-PA030157.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-142.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-142.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-142.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-142.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-144.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-144.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-144.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-144.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-154.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-154.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-154.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-154.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-160.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-160.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-150.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-150.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241003-PA030157.jpg" alt="20241003-PA030157.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-142.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-142.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-144.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-144.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-154.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-154.jpg" /></p>

<p>We visited an underground mosque and the outside necropolis after this stop. The underground mosque is fairly new, dating back the 12th-13th century but the necropolis dates even earlier to around the 8th century. It was interesting to see the huge mausoleums that were constructed by some of the families. It was almost identical to the cemetery we saw in Recoleta, Bueno Aires (holy macaroni… Buenos Aires! The first city of this year of travel!) except that this was an Islamic cemetery and Recoleta was for Catholics. In both locations, the size and grandeur of the mausoleum indicated the wealth and prosperity of the family for which it was constructed.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241003_145856.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Necropolis. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p>We headed to a little “Ethno-village” afterwards for the evening. We were divided up into two yurts, one for females and one for males, although differently from when Kevin and I last slept in a yurt, there were small single beds set up inside. This was our one night with a shower, which was much appreciated. We went on a hike in the nearby hills and Fei found tons of fossilized ammonites (a now extinct species that was the predecessor of the modern squid and octopus and lived…. in the ancient oceans) scattered around in the hills. Once we started looking at the rocks more carefully, we all found some ourselves. I can’t believe all these fossils are just hanging out here! Moono found one that was very intact and embarked on a careful excavation project to remove the sandstone around it with a hammer. Fei and Moono also found a cool geode that was colored red, orange, and purple. Ancient ocean confirmed!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241003_174751.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

An ammonite fossil! PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p><strong>Day 3</strong></p>

<p>The third day was a longer driving day out to the Tuzbair Salt Marsh. It was like déja vu with the Uyuni salt flats! We drove down and into the salt expanse with the drivers expertly navigating the unmarked land to get us to a spot where the white cliffs had hollowed out to look like dragons’ eyes. I asked Baygazy how he had learned to drive in this area and he said that he grew up in the area and learned all the places to go over many many years. It was impressive navigation especially because the mirage effect was really strong here; it seriously looked like we were about to drive into a lake the whole time except there was no lake at all! Other times, they were careful not to drive in areas where the salt was too moist lest the wheels get stuck. Moono and Ayan both had drones that they were flying for some overhead shots and if I get some of the videos (it takes a long time to slowly process all the clips), I will update this blog post with some of the awesome footage that they got of our trip! I did taste some of the white stuff on the ground – yes, it was definitely salt.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/mangystau_trip-106.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

It looks like rocks are floating in a lake. There is no lake.

</figcaption>

<p>On the way there we stopped at a gorgeous viewpoint that had a bird’s eye view of the salt marsh. We tried our second adventurous drink of the trip: horse milk. At first, the drivers weren’t keen on letting the women try it because they said it was a drink for men for erm, improved performance in bed. “Kazakh viagra.” But with some cajoling and a promise not to drink too much (which would have been a bad idea anyways, because like camel milk, it’s a little hard on untrained stomachs), we all got to try some. Honestly, it wasn’t bad. It was sweetened with a bit of honey (which apparently helps performance <em>even more</em>!) and mostly tasted just like normal full fat milk with an unidentifiable aftertaste.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241004-PA040191.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A viewpoint of the salt marsh.

</figcaption>

<p>This was pretty much the only thing we did this day because of the long drive to get out here. We drove onwards to a place called the Kyzylkup tract, more affectionately known by the Italian tourists as “tiramisu” due to its striped red and white layers (I personally think “candy cane” would be better but I assume Italians know best when it comes to tiramisu!) Why are there so many Italian tourists? I still don’t know. By the time we got to Tiramisu it was pretty dark, but we were all expert camp setter-uppers by this point so all the shelters were up in no time. Moono cooked dinner this evening (with help from Fei and Igor) – a yummy simple Chinese tomato stew with egg that was eaten with bread that soaked up the delicious tomato juice. Dinner was an entertaining affair; I was on the verge of choking up my dinner in laughter with continued discussion about horse milk. Baygazy would say, “Kevin! Kevin! Kevin! Twenty liters horse milk. One liter one day. One month. [Smacks hands together]. Little Kevins!] Baygazy also prescribed horse milk as a way to solve China’s population decline to Fei and Moono. Who knew?! HORSE MILK!</p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_162935.jpg" alt="20241004_162935.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_162935.jpg" alt="20241004_162935.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_203050.jpg" alt="20241004_203050.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_203050.jpg" alt="20241004_203050.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_154354.jpg" alt="20241004_154354.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_154354.jpg" alt="20241004_154354.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_152232.jpg" alt="20241004_152232.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_152232.jpg" alt="20241004_152232.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-088.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-088.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-088.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-088.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004-PA040221.jpg" alt="20241004-PA040221.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004-PA040221.jpg" alt="20241004-PA040221.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_162935.jpg" alt="20241004_162935.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_203050.jpg" alt="20241004_203050.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_154354.jpg" alt="20241004_154354.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004_152232.jpg" alt="20241004_152232.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-088.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-088.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241004-PA040221.jpg" alt="20241004-PA040221.jpg" /></p>

<p><strong>Day 4</strong></p>

<p>We woke up before dawn to watch the sunrise from the ridges of Tiramisu. Kyzylkup was quite a fun landscape to walk across; after a short steep hike up, the crest of the landscape is pretty flat so you can traverse across the tract to any point. We kept walking until we found a spot that was unobstructed by other parts of the tract and waited until the sun slowly came up. The sun was a slow poke! Ok, obviously not really, but there was a hill in the distance that blocked the horizon and I wanted breakfast and tea and I was getting hangry at the sun for being slow to rise up and over the hills. Eventually the sun did rise and after a few more pictures, we meandered back down to tear down camp and eat breakfast. </p>

<p><img src="images/IMG_2176+%281%29.jpeg" alt="Kevin and I at sunrise. PC: Igor." /></p>

<p><img src="images/IMG_2176+%281%29.jpeg" alt="Kevin and I at sunrise. PC: Igor." /></p>

<p>Kevin and I at sunrise. PC: Igor.</p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-057.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-057.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-057.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-057.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241005-PA050264.jpg" alt="20241005-PA050264.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241005-PA050264.jpg" alt="20241005-PA050264.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241005-PA050261.jpg" alt="20241005-PA050261.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241005-PA050261.jpg" alt="20241005-PA050261.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/IMG_2176+%281%29.jpeg" alt="Kevin and I at sunrise. PC: Igor." /></p>

<p><img src="images/mangystau_trip-057.jpg" alt="mangystau_trip-057.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241005-PA050264.jpg" alt="20241005-PA050264.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20241005-PA050261.jpg" alt="20241005-PA050261.jpg" /></p>

<p>This was a full day! After tear-down, we headed to our first stop which was Beket-Ata, a famous underground mosque created by a Sufi scholar named Beket. It’s a place of pilgrimage for many Kazakh muslims and involves a descent down a long set of stairs to get to the mosque. The view from the hike is really beautiful with sweeping panoramas of the Ustyurt plateau. There’s a helicopter pad at the bottom of the stairs; the story goes that some sort of country leader tried to avoid having to do all the stairs to visit Beket-Ata and built a helipad but on their attempts to land there, the winds blew strongly and the chopper wasn’t able to land so they assumed Beket’s spirit was disallowing it. And now the helipads are in disrepair. We did the short hike in the morning so it wasn’t too bad but I had to cover my hair and I didn’t have a scarf so I chucked my raincoat on my head and hiking in the heat with a nonporous raincoat is definitely something I cannot recommend.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241005-PA050281.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/PA050292.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Afterwards we headed out to a couple of panorama viewpoints of the Bozzhyra tract. These viewpoints were spectacular! I really loved the first one of “Dragon’s Crest” where a mountain island in the plains jutted out, really in the shape of a dragon’s back. I also thought it sort of traced out the Angel’s Landing hike in Zion. Gorgeous. The second viewpoint, called “Martian’s Viewpoint” was also spectacular. We were lucky to dine on lunch with this background. We got bombarded by some more Kazakh tourists at this spot and took a bunch of photos with them, though this time, we remembered to take a photo for ourselves! This was probably the largest group that we’ve taken photos with and bonus, with the Kazakh flag. People love to bring the country flag into their photos so I’m glad we got one!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241005-PA050301.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Kevin at the Dragon’s Crest.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/mangystau_trip-021.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Martian Viewpoint.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241005_135356.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A photo with some other random Kazakh tourists! Finally, we got a picture ourselves!

</figcaption>

<p>The trip really saved the best for last though. We did one final spot at a viewpoint that required a short hike to get to, just as the sun was setting. Oh my gosh; the drivers were definitely quite comfortable with us at this point and started showing off a bit on what their vehicles and they could do. So they drove straight up the most narrow path on some mountains past the parking area of the place where we were hiking. Very obviously they were in full control, but I was holding on for dear life as the car seemed to teeter on the slender steep hills. Holy moly.</p>

<p>The short hike took us up onto one of the mountain islands we previously saw from the viewpoints and right onto its overhang. I only briefly stayed at the overhang to take some photos because it was a bit too precipitous for me, but hung a little further back to take in the unbelievable landscape and colors as the sun set. The view point had such a wonderful picture of the “fangs” that jutted out like Monument Valley in Colorado. The best for last indeed.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/mangystau_trip-015.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Fang’s Viewpoint.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/PA050332.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Baygazy and Ayan drove down the mountain (yes, I was mentally clinging as we descended) and right into the tract to set up camp very close to the base of the peak we had just hiked up. We had a lovely clear view of the night sky and Igor and Moono managed to take some outrageously good shots of the night sky on their phones. We stayed up quite late this evening with Baygazy and Ayan cooking a special meal: a stew called Beshbarmak with boiled horse meat and potatoes. Kevin said that it wasn’t too bad! Moono and I stuck to the salad and bread. We were quite sad that this last evening had come so quickly. We had an amazing time with all these people that we were lucky to cross paths with and it was hard to believe that we’d have to say goodbye so soon. After a few more cups of tea/hot water (I learned at this point to say no to more tea and instead just nurse cups of hot water because otherwise I didn’t have a chance of sleeping well with all the caffeine) we said our good nights and crawled back into our tents.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241005_201020.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

PC: Betty. Hilariously, both cars’ trunks stopped working this evening and it took at least an hour to figure out how to force it open. In the meantime, we were fishing out things through the window. Still not sure what happened!

</figcaption>

<p><strong>Day 5</strong></p>

<p>We didn’t really have any stops planned for this day, but we at least took the morning, post breakfast, to wander around the gorgeous plateau one last time before we headed out. It was a long drive back to Aktau. Moono, Fei, and Igor were actually continuing on for one more day in the Ustyurt plateau while Betty, Kevin and I were heading back to Aktau. We at least got to share one more meal together, stopping at a local cafeteria for a luxurious meal, eaten while seated on the floor. Honestly, I just really enjoyed having a real toilet with toilet paper and a sink with running water and hand soap and a hand dryer. Luxurious! Alas, after lunch we parted ways with the other car, taking one last group picture with some more random Kazakh folks outside of the cafe. We made good time driving back to Aktau and picking up the rest of our bags before saying goodbye one last time to Baygazy, Betty, and Aars before heading to our airport hotel for the evening. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/20241006-PA060347.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Fangs from our campsite.

</figcaption>

<p>And that was the end of our time in Kazakhstan! I can’t believe we spent a full thirty days in the country; we both thought we’d be there for maybe two or three weeks max, but we ended up seeing so much over the extended time. And we <em>still</em> didn’t cover it all; there is definitely more to see in the Turkestan region of Kazakhstan and even more hikes we could have done in the mountains that border Kyrgyzstan. We’ve added Uzbekistan, Kyrgyzstan, and Azerbaijan to our list of future travel destinations. Betty had traveled to the former two and had really positive things to say and on a tour in Cappadocia, another woman who we met had also traveled quite a bit in Central Asia and said very positive things about Azerbaijan. The whole Central Asia region seems like an untrodden place for tourists and it has made for an exceptional experience with some of the most welcoming people (who aren’t just welcoming so that you’ll come into their shop and buy things) and the ability to quietly observe some spectacular sites without another person around. We’ll definitely be coming back one day for more!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/PXL_20241020_142154432+%281%29.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

P.S. Writing this post was hard. I had the above situation to deal with :P

</figcaption>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The owner of the car rental business we used in Almaty said, when she learned of our plans to visit Aktau in Western Kazakhstan, “Aktau is not like Almaty. Be prepared. People are not as friendly.” She also warned us that people do not speak as much English in Aktau. After spending over a week in the Aktau and larger Mangystau region, I think only the part about English really stands. Kazakhstan continues to have some of the nicest and most friendly people we’ve met while traveling, and our five day overlanding trip was magnificent, showing off Kazakhstan’s truly striking and dramatic landscapes, unlike places we’ve been before.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/mangystau_trip-015.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/mangystau-salt-water-and-oil/mangystau_trip-015.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mostly Uganda, a bit of Rwanda</title><link href="/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mostly Uganda, a bit of Rwanda" /><published>2024-10-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda</id><content type="html" xml:base="/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been procrastinating a bit on writing this post because I’ve been slightly nervous about having to sort through all the pictures from our very brief visit to Rwanda and Uganda. We were really only there for about four days primarily to embark on our last of three safaris to visit the primates living in the densely forested mountains across the borders of Rwanda, Uganda, and Democratic Republic of Congo. I had set my camera to burst mode in order to try to improve the odds that some of my pictures of the zipping simians might actually turn out sharp. The result of that is that I had somewhere on the order of four hundred pictures from four days that I had to sort through and I was a bit intimidated by the slow process, especially when I was only using my iPad. I’ve made significant progress on the project now, mainly due to a) switching to my laptop and b) having plane time to do some of the processing in phases. Now my challenge will be not to upload too many to this blog post, especially now that I’ve realized I can create galleries in my blogs now that I can use the full web version of Squarespace. Ah, the double edged sword of technology. </p>

<p>We arrived in Kigali, Rwanda from Nairobi and honestly, I was surprised by how modern the city was. We spent the evening at a California-chic cafe where I was able to eat <em>tofu</em>, a food I have not seen, let alone eaten since we were in Western Europe. We saw that there were a few other groups at the cafe using the spot as a work cafe; there were two (perhaps Australian based on the accent?) ladies working on a work presentation whom we had to ask to borrow their Deet spray as we were seated in a gorgeous garden outside and mosquitoes were feasting on our exposed skin. The city of Kigali itself reminds me a lot of Medellin; it is sprawled across a mountainous area with modern skyscrapers dotting the crests of the hills. It’s a dense city with the roads filled with motorcycle taxis who carry extra helmets for their paying passengers. As we had heard, Kigali is in fact an extremely clean city with little to no trash resting on sidewalks or in the creases of curbs. There are sidewalks. Rwanda also has banned plastic bags since 2008; this was something we were quite nervous about because we heard that there are strict penalties for bringing in plastic bags and we have lots of them to carry spillable toiletries, dirtied hiking shoes, and other random things like a small plastic bag to keep all my jewelry together. We ended up getting rid of all of the extra Ziplocs we had on hand that we keep in case of emergency, but hoped for the best for the ones that we couldn’t figure out another method. Ultimately it was fine; I think as long as there isn’t an intention to <em>dispose</em> of the plastic bags you bring into the country, you’re free to bring them in and then take them out. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/PXL_20240818_100618429.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Kigali, Rwanda. The two motorcycles on the left are moto taxis. 

</figcaption>

<p>After one night in Kigali, we immediately set off for our four day safari with our Ugandan driver named Gard (*not sure about the spelling) showing up bright and early the next day. Our first stop was at the Kigali Genocide Memorial. I’m sitting here unsure about how to write about this awful awful thing that happened within my lifetime that resulted in the deaths of around 800,000 souls. I won’t be able to do the history of it justice but if you have time, I would recommend <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rwandan_genocide">learning</a> about this terrible atrocity. The memorial itself is very hard to visit. The stories of the people who perished and the stories told by survivors, the photos and videos, and visiting the graves that each hold around 100,000 people was a moving experience. There were some videos that I could not watch. I was constantly pinching myself to try to prevent myself from crying. There are a few things that stood out to me though. First, the exhibits did a good job of explaining how radicalism through fear became the powerful engine that eventually motivated and, for those who participated, <em>justified</em> such an atrocity. Those who are in positions of leadership, who choose to prey on and exploit human fear in order to push their agenda, are, in my mind, terrible humans. Second, the Western world watched and sat on their hands while this happened. There are many reasons why, including overcautiousness in getting involved in another country’s conflict after some backlash in an earlier conflict in Somalia, but none seem reasonable in retrospect. The memorial dedicates a portion of the memorial to installations that discuss other genocides including the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Holocaust">Holocaust</a>, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambodian_genocide">Cambodian Genocide</a>, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosnian_genocide">Bosnian Genocide</a>, and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herero_and_Nama_genocide">Herero and Namaqua Genocide</a> in Namibia. The memorial is much more than a memorial; it is the resting place for many of the victims of the genocide, but also does research to understand the commonalities between genocides over history, understand why they happened, and runs campaigns to prevent genocides from happening again. It also provides support for survivors and for communities that were destroyed by genocide. Visiting the memorial is a must if you happen to ever be in Rwanda. I think it gives some perspective on how impressively well the country is doing and how quickly it is making economic progress given the context of how recently they went through the lowest point in their country’s history. </p>

<p>The Genocide Memorial was pretty much the only major thing we did in Rwanda. From there, Gard drove us onwards to Uganda close to the Mgahinga Gorilla National Park where we would be trekking the following day to track and view Golden Monkeys. I was very impressed with Gard’s driving and his ability to easily switch from the right hand side driving in Rwanda to the left hand side driving in Uganda. In Rwanda, the roads are more like how one would drive in the US with speed limits that drivers are expected to adhere to. In Uganda, the drivers appear not to be trusted with speed limits so the roads are full of speed bumps that force a slow speed. Gard navigated the roads effortlessly (except one blip at the end when he got a bit lost on the last day driving us to the airport in Kigali, but nothing a quick navigation on Google Maps couldn’t fix!). The safaris in Uganda/Rwanda are interesting from a pricing standpoint; gorilla trekking permits costs seven hundred US dollars per person in Uganda (fifteen hundred if you decide to do it in Rwanda) so it naturally means that the average client doing this type of safari is well-off and so other aspects of the trip, including accommodation, tend to be quite nice. The permits are so expensive to help curb over tourism; of the thirty-six or so human-habituated gorilla families, eleven are visited by groups of eight tourists for one hour each day. Rwanda has fewer habituated gorilla families so their permits are even more expensive. It is also possible to do gorilla trekking in DRC at a much lower cost (~four hundred dollars per permit) but it also comes with a risk of <a href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/le-monde-africa/article/2024/03/28/drc-people-and-animals-threatened-by-fighting-in-virunga-park_6661928_124.html">getting kidnapped</a> so, you know, probably not the best choice.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.49+51.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Hiking towards the golden monkeys in Mgahinga.

</figcaption>

<p>Our first day in Uganda was spent tracking golden monkeys in the Mgahinga Gorilla National Park. Both golden monkey tracking and mountain gorilla tracking work the same way. We and the other clients arrive at the national park early in the morning. Before we arrive, a group of trackers employed by the National Park will head into the mountains to go and find the primate families. They typically have a good sense of where the families are because they keep track of where they were last seen the night before. From that location, they can track food remains, poop, and tracks to figure out what direction the families might have moved overnight. While the trackers are doing that, we first are greeted with song and dance by the local communities who used to live in the national park areas (once an area becomes a national park, people can no longer live there so the government will try their best to support the people who end up getting displaced). Then we get briefed about the rules around visiting the monkeys or gorillas. The rules are all obvious ones with the only slightly interesting one being that everyone needs to wear face masks once we actually see the primates. This is because it is easy to transfer diseases between us and them. Following the safety briefing, all the visitors are divided into groups of eight and each group is assigned a primate family to track, a lead employed by the national park as well as additional trackers who are in communication with the trackers out in the field to figure out where to hike. Then we start walking. I’ve heard that sometimes the primate families are assigned based on the estimated fitness level of the group so that more fit groups are asked to hike out to the further families but it seemed like it was pretty arbitrary. There’s an option of the “African helicopter” where one can be fully carried on a semi-seated-stretcher-like contraption the entirety of the trek and back; it’s cool that they’ve found a way to make the experience accessible for those with more limited mobility and the money goes directly back to the communities.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+188.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Gorgeous forested mountains in the distance.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.49+43.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Hiking through what looks like impenetrable brush!

</figcaption>

<p>We hiked about two hours to find the golden monkeys. The hike itself was really beautiful with lovely views of the Virunga Mountains, shared by Rwanda, Uganda, and DRC. There are also three inactive volcanoes in the park which our guide pointed out to us as we trekked. We didn’t have to do much bushwacking and rather stuck to well trodden trails for the hike which was pretty nice. In what felt like no time at all, we got to the golden monkeys and had a fantastic time watching them fly through the trees! The golden monkeys were really active and mostly high in the trees, nibbling away at something or other. They were really fun to watch and there were more than one hundred in our designated family! It’s really incredible to watch their interactions and see the similarities to us humans. Except they way they leap through the trees; that is most definitely very un-human. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+191.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+243.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Our hour passed in a snap and we headed back to the entrance. We passed through a really lovely bamboo forest area and managed to do a sort of a loop so that we didn’t have to go exactly back the way we came. Apparently finding the monkeys in about two hours was really fast and we were the first group back; all the safari drivers were off somewhere chilling and when we returned to the parking lot, we all were sort of wandering around trying to find our drivers and guides. Because we finished so quickly, we ended up having a fairly relaxed evening at our hotel which was good because we had an early start the next day.</p>

<p>Kevin took this amazing video of the golden monkeys leaping through the trees!</p>

<p>Both Kevin and I were very excited for mountain gorilla tracking. A few of the folks whom we hiked with for golden monkey tracking told us a bit about their experience with the gorillas (they were starting their safari from Kampala instead of Kigali) and it sounded just incredible. I really appreciated Gard’s attentiveness to making sure we always got to places either on time or early. We were some of the first ones ready to go at Bwindi Impenetrable Forest National Park. It made for a relaxing experience with plenty of time to prepare ourselves before we got started hiking. This hike ended up being kind of funny. We first drove to a different trailhead away from the national park entrance. We lingered around the trailhead for quite some time because there were two possible paths we could have taken but the trackers weren’t sure which one to take. Part of the reason was because there was poor cellphone connection between the trackers in the field and the trackers with us. Another was that (and we found this out later) the gorilla family was on the move so they were rapidly changing their position. We waited around so that we’d have more certainty about which direction to go instead of tracking down one path and then backtracking to go a different way. I’m not sure how long we waited but eventually, we started going up one of the paths. This trek was a bit more challenging; they don’t call it the “Impenetrable Forest” for nothing! There was still a visible trail but the leads out in front had to do a bit more whacking of the bushes and vines with their machetes. It was occasionally steep but at least it hadn’t rained too much so it wasn’t too muddy or slippery. We ended up not hiking very far before we paused again. Once again, the trackers with us were trying to figure out where the gorillas were headed. After another length of time, they had us turn back a few paces, take a right turn directly into the bushes and voila, there they were! We really only ended up actively hiking, maybe, around thirty minutes or less. </p>

<p>A welcoming song performed by a local Batwa pygmy group.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+183.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The Bwindi forest is really lush and beautiful. Impenetrable indeed!

</figcaption>

<p>It really was such a cool experience to view these mountain gorillas. We saw a family of eight: one silverback (the alpha male), three adult females, three adolescents, and one baby. Most of the time, the gorillas were on the ground eating. The baby was hilarious to watch as he was the most active of all the gorillas and Kevin managed to take a great video (below!) of the baby accidentally falling out of a tree! Also, Kevin got pushed by one of the gorillas! We were watching a small group in front of us feed and a little while later, we heard a voice saying “there’s a gorilla behind you.” I turned around just in time to see a female gorilla, who was feeding behind us, decide to join the main group that we were watching in front of us and I managed to step out of her path just in time. Kevin was a little more in front of me and turned around only just enough to see there was a gorilla on his tail without any time to react. The gorilla gave him a big shove and continued her direct path to the group! Boy, I wish I had my video setting on to capture the moment. I was laughing so hard and Kevin looked so startled for a second. She definitely gave him a good push! At least it wasn’t the silverback that shoved Kevin out of the way!</p>

<p>Baby gorillas falls out of the tree! PC: Kevin.</p>

<p>One interesting thing to watch was how the trackers communicated with the gorillas. Occasionally the silverback would grunt a bit and the trackers grunt back at an equal strength. My basic understanding is that it was a way to communicate in familiar terms to give a sense of security to the gorillas and prevent any aggression. To habituate a gorilla family for human visitors takes about two years and even after we left, a few trackers stayed behind and continued to track them over the course of the day. They even have veterinary centers to take care of gorillas in case they get hurt or ill. Because of their conservation efforts, the number of mountain gorillas is rising and moving in a positive direction away from the endangered species designation, now totalling more than one thousand.</p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+6.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 6.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+6.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 6.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+98.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 98.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+98.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 98.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+126.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 126.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+126.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 126.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+178.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 178.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+178.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 178.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+6.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 6.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+98.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 98.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+126.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 126.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+178.jpg" alt="rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27 at 14.52.48 178.jpg" /></p>

<p>After watching the gorillas, we headed to a gorgeous area of Uganda called Lake Bunyonyi. The drive to the lake itself was really beautiful. Uganda’s land is undulating and the road winds through its rolling hills. Gard said that the mountains in Uganda are very fertile compared to the mountains in Rwanda which are too rocky to farm. Because of this fertile land, Ugandans produce enough food to feed the entire country (though the challenge of making sure the food actually reaches all the people still remains). We saw the land being tilled for planting long beans and tons of cabbage patches. They also produce all sorts of sweet potatoes, Irish potatoes, and a particular grain called <em>sorghum</em>. I tried this grain with some barbecued tofu in Rwanda our first night; it’s a pretty hearty grain that requires some jaw strength to chew through but it was tasty. As we got closer to the lake, we also saw more quarry mining and brick manufacturing. People would sit near the rocky hills adjacent to the road and mine the rocks by hand, breaking them into small pieces. These stones are commonly bought by real estate developers in order to build buildings in the area. We also saw huge piles of bricks that had been shaped and stacked in order to be fired into actual usable bricks.</p>

<p>We arrived at the lake’s edge by car and hopped into a small boat that whisked us away to an island in the lake where our hotel was situated. The lake is incredibly peaceful and beautiful. We had a lovely evening spent on the terrace, staring at the lake while eating dinner with Gard. We exchanged stories about our lives and Gard told us how he’s saving up to buy twenty cows so that he can marry his girlfriend. We really enjoyed Gard’s company; he was closer to us in age than most other safari guides we’ve had in the past and I think that helped conversation flow easily. Gard himself is a very social and friendly person, offering to help anyone around (for example, since we had space in our car, he offered the gorilla trackers to hop into our car for a ride to the trail head).</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.47+9.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Lake Bunyonyi. 

</figcaption>

<p>The next day we did our final activity which was to canoe around the perimeter of the island in the lake in a Ugandan pirogue with oars that really looked more like spatulas. Gard took an embarrassing video of us completely failing at trying to paddle in a straight line and we nearly gave up getting around the lake when we got to the back side of the island and it felt like we were making zero forward progress against the wind. But we prevailed! We definitely provided some entertainment for the local folks who were either zipping around in their motor-powered boats or professionally handling their own canoe with ease. It was genuinely a lot of fun to paddle around and we got a good workout by the end. Afterwards, we packed up, piled our stuff back into a motor-powered boat that took us back to the mainland (with a brief stop to check out some zebras on a nearby island!). And then we headed to the airport! On the way, we did have one last stop to eat some “rolex” which was one Ugandan food I really wanted to try. This is something I will have to try to make for a quick lunch one day; it’s just a thin omelet (add whatever fillings you want) stacked on a chapati and rolled up. You can eat it with a sweet chili sauce or ketchup or just plain. Simple and yummy!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/20240821_091519.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Attempting to canoe with my spatula. PC: Kevin.

</figcaption>

<p>We headed back to the States after this last safari for a wedding and to visit some family which was really nice. A random note, our layover in Nairobi was <em>fantastic</em>; we’ve been heavy users of lounges this year and the Nairobi lounge was amazing. The food was so good and they had fantastic showers, each one cleaned after every person. I packed my own towel and toiletries assuming I’d have to provide my own, but they gave me fresh towels, slippers, and toiletries. After a full delicious meal and a hot shower, Kevin and I both passed out fantastically on the plane, skipping all the meals and waking only close to landing. We’ve both gotten to be very good plane sleepers!</p>

<p>And that’s it for our Africa leg! What a phenomenal time! I think it will be quite some time before we want to do another safari but we’re so thankful to have had such incredible experiences. I just learned yesterday that it was lucky that we were able to go at all because both Rwanda and Uganda have been upgraded to “Level 3: Reconsider Travel” designations by the US State Department due to an outbreak of Marburg virus disease. I hope that the countries are able to contain the virus quickly so that more people can visit these amazing lands.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/20240820_064013.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Kevin took this ethereal photo of the Ugandan mountains!

</figcaption>

<p>A fun side note: Chicago O’Hare is one of our favorite airports in the whole wide world. Why? Because they have a Sprinkles cupcake “ATM.” We <em>always</em> get a chocolate cupcake with chocolate frosting to share and the “I love Sprinkles” song gets stuck in our head for days thereafter. It was our special treat for all the red eyes we took when flying from SFO to Columbus, since we would almost always pass through O’Hare around 4 or 5 in the morning and the ATM is located between the main B/C terminals where the big birds fly in (SFO -&gt; ORD) and the dungeon terminals of E/F where the tiny planes get relegated (ORD -&gt; CMH). THEY CHANGED THE ATM LOCATION THOUGH! We didn’t get a cupcake :( But there’s a happy ending to the story which is that we flew through ORD again the following day when we traveled to Montreal after picking up our fancy clothes in Columbus and I hunted down that ATM and we got our cupcake. 10 out of 10.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/PXL_20240822_170844208.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

ORD's iconic underground tunnel never gets old. Oh how many memories I have of sprinting through this tunnel to catch a flight. It was nice to be back State side for a bit :) 

</figcaption>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been procrastinating a bit on writing this post because I’ve been slightly nervous about having to sort through all the pictures from our very brief visit to Rwanda and Uganda. We were really only there for about four days primarily to embark on our last of three safaris to visit the primates living in the densely forested mountains across the borders of Rwanda, Uganda, and Democratic Republic of Congo. I had set my camera to burst mode in order to try to improve the odds that some of my pictures of the zipping simians might actually turn out sharp. The result of that is that I had somewhere on the order of four hundred pictures from four days that I had to sort through and I was a bit intimidated by the slow process, especially when I was only using my iPad. I’ve made significant progress on the project now, mainly due to a) switching to my laptop and b) having plane time to do some of the processing in phases. Now my challenge will be not to upload too many to this blog post, especially now that I’ve realized I can create galleries in my blogs now that I can use the full web version of Squarespace. Ah, the double edged sword of technology. ]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+6-2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/mostly-uganda-a-bit-of-rwanda/rwanda_uganda_2024-08-27+at+14.52.48+6-2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ring Tour of Almaty</title><link href="/the-ring-tour-of-almaty" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ring Tour of Almaty" /><published>2024-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/the-ring-tour-of-almaty</id><content type="html" xml:base="/the-ring-tour-of-almaty"><![CDATA[<p>Per the owner’s request, yesterday we returned our trusty Geely Atlas SUV back to Almaty, directly into a car wash where the attendants immediately got to work scrubbing off the thick crusted layer of dust, dirt, and dung (primarily of the equestrian variety) that even a heavy downpour could not rinse away. I watched in amusement as the attendant repeatedly went over a particularly stubborn section on the back of the vehicle over and over with the power washer while we waited to meet the car rental owner to wrap up the paperwork. Yesterday, we returned back to Almaty after an eight day road trip covering several of the national parks in the Almaty region. I’m really proud of how well Kevin and I managed to piece together this road trip, pulling bits and pieces from various trip reports, blogs, lots of map tools (Yandex Maps, 2GIS, and Google Maps), and plenty of AI tools (I’m a particularly heavy user of Gemini and a bit less of Claude and Kevin uses Gemini, Claude, and a bit less of GPT and some others). The use of AI tools has been one noticeable difference in how we plan our travel from the start of the year to now. I have both the Gemini and Claude apps installed on my phone (though I only pay for Gemini) and use the tools very heavily, usually multiple times a day. Especially in countries where English resources aren’t as readily available or additional time is required to peruse through Google Search results to find an answer, I instead opt to use Gemini to ask things like “why isn’t it advisable to drink the tap water in Kazakhstan?” or “At Amboseli National Park, there was a particular kind of white bird that always trailed after elephants and ate food that would get unearthed when the elephants pawed at the earth. What type of bird is it?” Randomly, I learned that giving greeting cards is not popular throughout this planet; I wanted to send greeting cards for special occasions while we were in Turkey and most recently in Kazakhstan and in both countries, cards are not a thing. Gemini came to the rescue to help find places that sell something that is pretty close to a greeting card (in both cases, the “cards” don’t really open… it’s more like a glorified postcard) when Google Maps failed me. Watching us use these AI tools more and more makes me sort of wonder how working might be different when we re-enter the workforce in a few months. When we left our jobs, the tools we used were more for curiosity than for real purpose but in our current daily lives, that seems to already change. I’m sort of amazed by it because we’re changing even though we’re not in the middle of it all the way we used to be; I’d have assumed we would be a bit slower on the uptake given our distance from where it all is happening in the US and western Europe.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/20240914_211729.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Anyone want a MateBook Pro?

</figcaption>

<p>Anyways, I digress :) We flew to Almaty in the more central area of Kazakhstan after returning from Burabay. We spent the first three days doing a bit of road trip planning and also visiting sites in the city. The city of Almaty feels much more like a Western European city; it’s less intentionally symmetrical than Astana giving it a warmer feel, there are parks with playgrounds, art, and memorials dotted around the city. While we were there, just outside of our apartment, there was a “bookfest” ongoing where Kazakhstan literature was being celebrated. There were tons of small stalls selling/giving away books, lots of food stalls (including stalls that were spinning candy floss into spheres as large as both mine and Kevin’s heads put together), and live music. The festival was massive, spanning several blocks of the city with a few large stages set up in the middle of the roads. We saw one of the stages had a young English-speaking presenter who was talking about “life in America” to a swath of eager listeners, the majority of whom expressed interest in one day attending a US university. I found the presenter’s particular choices about what to describe as “American life” to be funny, ranging from the “ugly sweater” contests during Christmas time to “Field Day” in elementary school. I had honestly forgotten about “Field Day” altogether from my tiny-Arathi days!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/P9150024.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

We went to a museum in Almaty called the Museum of Musical Instruments. They had an amazing collection of instruments from Kazakhstan but also exhibits showcasing instruments from other regions of the world including Armenia, Georgia, Thailand, Japan, India, Turkiyë, and many more. These instruments are called Jew's Harps. [Here's](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5mdvajc9cHU) a video on what they sound like.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/PXL_20240915_131739411.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

It looks like a fairy tale castle with a fairy tale coach approaching it, but in the background in the Russian Orthodox Church.

</figcaption>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/PXL_20240915_104926699.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The book festival right outside our apartment.

</figcaption>

<p>We visited a few other sites around the city, including a beautiful Russian Orthodox Church. I’ve been inside other similar churches before but while we were there, a service was ongoing and it was really interesting to watch the rituals. It’s always interesting to me to watch different types of religious services and observe that many have similarities. In this particular one, the priests go behind closed doors and perform some rituals privately before opening the doors for the general patrons. A very similar sort of practice exists in Hinduism as well. Afterwards, the priests made a circuit around the church, blessing all the patrons standing around the different parts of the church (there is no seating), which also reminded me of an almost identical practice I watched as a kid in Hindu temples towards the end of a religious ceremony. In both this church and an earlier mosque we visited in Astana, I needed to cover my hair but as the majority of women who live in the cities don’t usually cover their hair as general practice (some do of course), scarves were freely provided for use. Not a religious thing, but I noticed that Kazakh people are very particular about not wearing shoes in the house and nearly every place has provided us with house slippers. Even though we both always take our shoes off anyways, even stepping more than one or two (yes, literally one or two) beyond the threshold in an apartment with shoes will elicit a request to take off our shoes straight away.</p>

<p><img src="images/P9150008.jpg" alt="P9150008.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150008.jpg" alt="P9150008.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150010.jpg" alt="P9150010.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150010.jpg" alt="P9150010.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150003.jpg" alt="P9150003.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150003.jpg" alt="P9150003.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150006.jpg" alt="P9150006.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150006.jpg" alt="P9150006.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150008.jpg" alt="P9150008.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150010.jpg" alt="P9150010.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150003.jpg" alt="P9150003.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9150006.jpg" alt="P9150006.jpg" /></p>

<p>Almaty is nestled at the foot of several mountains which means that a) we woke up to gorgeous views of the snow-capped mountains every morning and b) we got to go visit them! We visited a hill that is serviced by a long gondola ride that had stunning panoramic views of the mountains in the distance. The top of the hill is also a sort of kid “fun zone” with a ferris wheel, mini roller coaster, bumper cars, and more. We went on the rollercoaster! We visited a ski resort, Shymbulak, on our third day in Almaty where we took three gondolas to get to the topmost skiing area (there is no active skiing at the moment because it’s too early) and went out hiking further into the mountains. The trail was a bit trickier than we imagined with lots of scrambling and not very clearly marked trials. Part of the issue was that some parts of the trail were covered with snow which we tried to skirt around (no crampons on hand). Another bigger issue was that it started snowing pretty heavily. Before it got too bad though, we got some beautiful dramatic views of the mountains all around us. We met three guys from Holland towards the point when we decided to turn back who had hiked out with Kazakh hats and jackets. Those three guys turned around a bit earlier than us and it was helpful to be able to watch them descend because as we made progress, the snow got heavier and heavier and visibility massively decreased. By the time we reached the trailhead, we could barely see a hand out in front of us and we used the club-like Kazakh music blasting out from top of the gondola to help us identify the direction back to the gondola. We were both a bit wet and after two gondolas down, we stopped at a little French bakery/cafe to warm up with some hot cocoa.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/P9160057.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

The view of Almaty from the top of the gondola. 

</figcaption>

<p><img src="images/20240917_121025.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240917_121025.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p>Shymbulak</p>

<p><img src="images/20240917_134510.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240917_134510.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p>Shymbulak</p>

<p><img src="images/P9170013.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9170013.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p>Shymbulak</p>

<p><img src="images/P9170010.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9170010.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p>Shymbulak</p>

<p><img src="images/P9170008.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9170008.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p>Shymbulak</p>

<p><img src="images/P9170007.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9170007.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p>Shymbulak</p>

<p><img src="images/20240917_121025.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240917_134510.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9170013.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9170010.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9170008.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9170007.jpg" alt="Shymbulak" /></p>

<p><strong>Day 1: Almaty -&gt; Nomad movie set -&gt; Basshi</strong></p>

<p>And then we started on our trip! Day one was pretty relaxed. On our first pass of planning this road trip, we had scheduled a bunch of activities on this first day but thankfully revised to allow for more time with getting the car and groceries and whatnot. In one of my previous blog posts, I mentioned that we were planning on hiring a guide to drive us around because we thought that we couldn’t drive in Kazakhstan. Kazakhstan is one of the few countries that actually seems to require an International Driving Permit, sort of. The whole thing around an IDP is sort of weird; it’s essentially a glorified booklet that has your license translated into a bunch of languages and has been notarized. We tried getting our IDPs in New York but unfortunately were not able to because we have Canadian driving licenses and in the US, only US licenses can get the IDP. We briefly thought about traveling to Toronto from New York to get the IDPs instead but we had already booked our flights to Astana by the time we realized we couldn’t get our IDPs and we didn’t want to miss the Nomad Games. We found out through extensive searching on Reddit that it might be possible to instead have our licenses translated to Russian once we arrived in Kazakhstan and then have the translations notarized. We asked a few car rental companies whether that would be fine and most said yes and a few said no, we needed the IDP. So we picked a car rental company that said yes, got our translated and notarized licenses and proceeded. We found out later that there’s an online scam company that “makes IDPs” and apparently that’s totally fine too. Most police officers here have never seen an IDP before so can’t distinguish between what is a real thing and not, but the important element is that they need to be able to read your license and check that it is valid, thus the Russian translation. Police corruption is also rampant here so it’s not uncommon to get pulled over for a trivial/random thing and then be asked to pay a bribe. We were lucky not to ever have that issue at all. In any case, in the areas we were driving, it would be miles and miles before we’d even see another car.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/PXL_20240918_103952889.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Sometimes we saw more horses than humans. Look at these horse politely (almost) using the crosswalk!

</figcaption>

<p>Our first stop was a completely random stop at an old movie set in the middle of nowhere. This cardboard fortress was built for the 2005 box office bomb, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nomad_\(2005_film\)"><em>Nomad</em></a>, that boasts a Rotten Tomatoes rating of 6%. We had a great time being the only people on the site, wondering whether every step we’d take would result in the rickety boards sagging and splitting under our weight, crashing us back down to the ground. But no! It’s still upright! We’ve added the movie to our watch list but haven’t yet mustered up the motivation to sit through 112 minutes of dramaticized battles of the Kazakh-Dzungar wars.</p>

<p><img src="images/P9180034.jpg" alt="P9180034.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180034.jpg" alt="P9180034.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180032.jpg" alt="P9180032.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180032.jpg" alt="P9180032.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180028.jpg" alt="P9180028.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180028.jpg" alt="P9180028.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180026-2.jpg" alt="P9180026-2.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180026-2.jpg" alt="P9180026-2.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180020.jpg" alt="P9180020.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180020.jpg" alt="P9180020.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180017.jpg" alt="P9180017.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180017.jpg" alt="P9180017.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180034.jpg" alt="P9180034.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180032.jpg" alt="P9180032.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180028.jpg" alt="P9180028.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180026-2.jpg" alt="P9180026-2.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180020.jpg" alt="P9180020.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9180017.jpg" alt="P9180017.jpg" /></p>

<p>The movie set was situated on the bank of a reservoir and we wanted to get over to the other side to check out some petroglyphs but it turns out, getting to the other side would add a substantial amount of driving. Since getting the car and groceries took a bit longer than expected, we decided to go straight from the movie set to our first destination which was Baashi, a hamlet just outside of Altyn-Emel National Park. Here, we settled into our spacious yurt for the night. The campsite was really nice; the kitchen was well-stocked, the showers were very clean, hot, and had excellent shower pressure. They had some cats including one sad sick kitty who hung around for some cuddles. I melt a little every time a cat purrs.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/PXL_20240918_132538069.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Yurt!

</figcaption>

<p><strong>Day 2: Basshi -&gt; Altyn-Emel National Park (Aktau Mountains, Katutau Mountains) -&gt; Basshi</strong></p>

<p>Day two was the first real test of our car. We decided to go for an SUV rather than a true 4x4 and the road to the Aktau mountains was not paved (we knew this in advance). The driving was ultimately uneventful; at this point, both Kevin and I have quite a bit of experience driving on crappy, gravel-y roads so we were able to navigate the bumpy terrain just fine without blowing any tires.</p>

<p>It is totally deserted out here! It’s just miles and miles of gorgeous red and white candy cane mountains. We hiked along a ridge trail for some ways (no AllTrails here!) until it deposited us at a lovely viewpoint and we couldn’t see a way to hike any further. We did see a couple more cars but only one group of three people who we saw doing a sketchy-looking hike up one of the mountains (they had a guide with them). This area is definitely a place where you’re free to sort of explore as you wish and we were able to make a sort of loop trail from the viewpoint, connecting back to a dry streambed to get us back to the parking area. Just stunning, stunning landscapes!</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/P9190051.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A panorama of the Aktau Mountains.

</figcaption>

<p><img src="images/P9190061.jpg" alt="P9190061.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190061.jpg" alt="P9190061.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190065.jpg" alt="P9190065.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190065.jpg" alt="P9190065.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190043.jpg" alt="P9190043.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190043.jpg" alt="P9190043.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190041.jpg" alt="P9190041.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190041.jpg" alt="P9190041.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190039.jpg" alt="P9190039.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190039.jpg" alt="P9190039.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190036.jpg" alt="P9190036.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190036.jpg" alt="P9190036.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190061.jpg" alt="P9190061.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190065.jpg" alt="P9190065.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190043.jpg" alt="P9190043.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190041.jpg" alt="P9190041.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190039.jpg" alt="P9190039.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9190036.jpg" alt="P9190036.jpg" /></p>

<p>We drove next to the nearby Katutau mountains where there weren’t really any proper trails but instead we just wandered out a little to some nearby viewpoints to enjoy some homemade trail mix. Both the Aktau and Katutau mountains were formed by volcanic activities and at Katutau, we could see the weird amorphous shapes that the volcanic activity had created. Supposedly there were some petroglyphs there but we couldn’t find any and we knew from our time in Rapa Nui that sometimes it’s really hard to see faded petroglyphs without optimal lighting (usually sunrise light that shines on the petroglyphs at an angle).</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/P9190078.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Katutau.

</figcaption>

<p>We returned back to the campsite, with a stop at a seven hundred year old willow tree that was absolutely not worth it because we both got destroyed by mosquitoes that were in that wet area in the five minutes that we spent finding and looking at the tree. We switched to sleeping in an RV for the night (the yurt was booked) and chatted with another visitor from Malaysia who was vacationing with a couple other friends.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/PXL_20240919_123424946.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Got into a bit of a traffic jam on the way back to Basshi.

</figcaption>

<p><strong>Day 3: Basshi -&gt; Altyn-Emel National Park (Singing Dunes) -&gt; Chundzha Hot Springs</strong></p>

<p>We had a second day in Altyn-Emel visiting a different part of the park that is actually the more common tourist attraction because it has fewer kilometers of gravel roads to navigate. The Singing Dunes are huge quartz sand dunes that we hiked up and with some beautiful views of the Ili River beyond. These dunes are very similar to the ones we hiked up in Namibia, though much smaller. In a crazy coincidence, while we were hanging out at the top of the dune, a guy who had just climbed up said, “hey, you’re from Canada right?” Turns out, these were the same guys from Holland that we had met at in Shymbulak! I guess when the country has so few tourists, you’re bound to meet the same people at all the popular sights! We hung out with them for a bit and then decided to try exploring some of the other dunes so we continued to hike until we were tired of hiking in sand (sand hiking is tiring!) and the sand was getting too hot for our bare feet. And then, per usual, found the steepest slope and sprinted down to the bottom. One of my favorite things to do! </p>

<p><img src="images/20240920_111559.jpg" alt="20240920_111559.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240920_111559.jpg" alt="20240920_111559.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240920_104247.jpg" alt="20240920_104247.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240920_104247.jpg" alt="20240920_104247.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9200002.jpg" alt="P9200002.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9200002.jpg" alt="P9200002.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240920_111559.jpg" alt="20240920_111559.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240920_104247.jpg" alt="20240920_104247.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9200002.jpg" alt="P9200002.jpg" /></p>

<p>We made our way back to Basshi and from there, continued our ring tour to a resort to enjoy the Chundzha Hot Springs, where we found all the Kazakh and Russian tourists. Sort of similar to Albania, on the hiking trails in Altyn-Emel, we encountered few local hikers. They are almost all international visitors. I guess long hiking is not much of a pastime for Kazakh people, just as it wasn’t for Albanians, even with such beautiful (if arduous) trails around. The resort was <em>packed</em>. I thought they might have been lying when they told me they only had one room left when I WhatsApp’ed them earlier to book a place. But no, the place was full with tons of visitors (probably especially busy because it was the weekend). Kids and adults alike enjoyed the warm pools (they were more like large swimming pools with spring water piped in) and people brought half a house’s worth of supplies with them including groceries, hookahs, lots of alcohol, and boomboxes loud enough to rival the resort’s own. I swear, it seems like all Kazakh music is just club music. We had a great time at the pools though, floating and bobbing around. And dinner was delicious (a gracious Russian tourist helped translate my vegetarian dietary restriction to the befuddled chef).</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/20240921_092139.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

A very strange set of sculptures at the hot springs.

</figcaption>

<p><strong>Day 4: Chundzha Hot Springs -&gt; Charyn National Park</strong></p>

<p>We headed towards Charyn Canyon the next day which gives off Grand Canyon-esque vibes, though it is much much smaller. It has a similar reddish glow and was carved away by a tributary of the Charyn River. Some of the stone wall tops have been eroded away (my guess is wind erosion, but I’m not sure) to resemble the hoodoos in Bryce Canyon National Park. The most famous hike to do is the Valley of the Castles hike which runs through the floor of the canyon. We managed to do a hike along the rim of the canyon that descended down into the valley and then took the Valley of the Castles trail back to the visitor center to make a loop. We contemplated trying to see some of the other canyons in the area, but we realized that we would need a proper offroading vehicle to get to those areas; the paths are not paved and are loose gravel that descend straight down into the canyon. We weren’t worried about getting down to the canyon, but rather nervous about coming back out. I’m pretty confident we would have gotten our vehicle stuck in the bottom of a canyon if we had tried and that would have put a bit of a damper on the trip.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/P9210015.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Charyn Canyon.

</figcaption>

<p>Charyn Canyon had the most tourists out of any place we had been thus far. Once we were a ways out on the trail, the crowd all but disappeared and we were able to get some quality hiking time in. On the way back, we got caught in a bit of rain but after sheltering in a small man made cave for a few minutes, the rain dissipated and we continued our hike. Continuing along the theme of Kazakhstan being a really friendly and welcoming place, as we were hiking, a van sped by transporting some other visitors to the trailhead and a teenage girl stuck her head out the window and yelled at us, “WELCOME TO KAZAKHSTAN!” </p>

<p><img src="images/20240921_171341.jpg" alt="20240921_171341.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240921_171341.jpg" alt="20240921_171341.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240921_152509.jpg" alt="20240921_152509.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240921_152509.jpg" alt="20240921_152509.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210052.jpg" alt="P9210052.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210052.jpg" alt="P9210052.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210044.jpg" alt="P9210044.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210044.jpg" alt="P9210044.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210027.jpg" alt="P9210027.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210027.jpg" alt="P9210027.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210033.jpg" alt="P9210033.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210033.jpg" alt="P9210033.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210024.jpg" alt="P9210024.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210024.jpg" alt="P9210024.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240921_171341.jpg" alt="20240921_171341.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240921_152509.jpg" alt="20240921_152509.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210052.jpg" alt="P9210052.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210044.jpg" alt="P9210044.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210027.jpg" alt="P9210027.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210033.jpg" alt="P9210033.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/P9210024.jpg" alt="P9210024.jpg" /></p>

<p>A gorgeous rainbow came out just as we reached the end of our hike. A huge, full rainbow that made me wish for my wide angle lens again (ooh another aside: while I was briefly back in Ohio, I sent my lens back to Olympus for repair and I found out a few days ago that because it was under warranty, they just sent back a full replacement so I can use it again if I want. I might resell it though because having four lenses seems like a lot of lenses for someone who only recreationally photographs and the wide angle is very much a specialty lens). We splurged a little (well, splurged in terms of cost of things in Kazakhstan) on a cabin situated right at the base of the canyon for the night. It was a really spacious and comfortable cabin with a balcony looking out onto the beautiful national park lands.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/P9210056.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Day 5: Charyn National Park -&gt; Black Canyon -&gt; Lake Kaindy -&gt; Saty</strong></p>

<p>The primary reason we wanted to stay at the cabin inside the national park was to see the sunrise. The park doesn’t open until around 9 but staying at the cabin meant that we could stroll right into the canyon at any time and so we woke up around 4:45am to catch the 5:30am sunrise. An aside, the entire country of Kazakhstan is on one time zone so sunrise and sunset times have been wildly varying based on which longitudinal line we’re located at. Since we were quite far east, alas, sunrise is quite early.</p>

<p><img src="images/20240922_051110.jpg" alt="20240922_051110.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240922_051110.jpg" alt="20240922_051110.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240922-P9220027.jpg" alt="20240922-P9220027.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240922-P9220027.jpg" alt="20240922-P9220027.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240922-P9220021.jpg" alt="20240922-P9220021.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240922-P9220021.jpg" alt="20240922-P9220021.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240922_051110.jpg" alt="20240922_051110.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240922-P9220027.jpg" alt="20240922-P9220027.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240922-P9220021.jpg" alt="20240922-P9220021.jpg" /></p>

<p>We had an absolutely magical time walking out to the rim and onto some outcroppings before dawn, watching the canyon and landscape slowly lighten with not a single other human around. We heard some birds squawking enthusiastically, eager to get on with breakfast. It was a gorgeous sunrise. After the sun rose and a short while later, hide in some higher clouds, we decided to follow suit and head back to our cabin and hide for a couple more hours under a quilt.</p>

<p>After checking out, we continued our tour, taking a brief stop at the nearby Black Canyon. We pulled off on the side of the road where a couple other cars were parked and where Google Maps declared to be the viewpoint and had some lovely views of the canyon. It turns out, we were at the wrong place and a few hundred meters of driving later, we found a proper parking lot with food stalls and a washroom. Ironically, the view wasn’t as good here in my opinion. We also saw a <em>huge</em> youth group swarming around the view point. We pulled into this parking lot, but were more entertained by the youth group and their various chanting and photo taking and then the incessant honking of the eight or so giant motorcoaches to coax the teenagers back on the bus.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/20240922-P9220030.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Black Canyon.

</figcaption>

<p>We continued our road trip down to Lake Kaindy. We knew that we wouldn’t be able to get to the lake in our non-4x4 crossover car, so the common thing to do is to find a Soviet era van vehicle in the village of Saty (a UAZ-452 van) and pay the driver a sum to drive you to the lake, wait for some time (our driver waited for an hour and a half), and then drive you back down to the town. The van does not look like it can handle crazy cratered roads with stream crossings, but that thing crushed through the terrain. It has a nickname: “buhanka.” It means “loaf of bread.” If you check out the picture, the likeness is unmistakable.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/20240922-P9220051.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>We shared a van with another family who happened to reach the entrance to the gravel road at the same time as us. After reaching the main parking lot, we needed to take a second van to get to the actual lake which didn’t have any main parking. The lake is quite a unique one; it’s a very new lake created in 1911 that formed when a landslide created a natural dam and the water pooled together in the valley, submerging and killing the trees in the area. It’s really weird and cool to see the dead spruce trees jut out of the bright turquoise water. </p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/20240922-P9220046.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Lake Kaindy.

</figcaption>

<p>While we were there, it started to rain, then pour, then hail. Luckily, there was some shelter built where everyone huddled and the lake took on a very cool look with the hail pelting the lake. Also luckily, the precipitation abated after a few minutes and we were able to walk back to our rides relatively dry. We returned back to our car, and headed to our homestay in Saty village for the evening.</p>

<p><strong>Day 6: Saty -&gt; Lake Kolsay -&gt; Saty</strong></p>

<p>Lake Kolsay is actually a set of three (or four, if you count the one in nearby Kyrgyzstan) lakes that are connected by streams that are fed by melting glacier water from the Kungey Alatau Mountains. It gives it that milky white or green color that we also saw back in Patagonia. We had a pretty straightforward day on day 6; we drove out to the trailhead and hiked from the bottommost lake (Kolsay 1) to the second lake (Kolsay 2) and then returned. I think it’s possible to hike to Kolsay 3 but it’s a bit tricky to do in one day and wild camping is recommended. Also there are differing opinions about whether there is border control; a few posts mentioned that there might be a border control officer who holds onto your passport while you visit the third lake (because it is so close to Kyrgyzstan) and others said that they couldn’t go at all past a certain point. In any case, we didn’t try because the mileage was a bit too long for the amount of time we allocated for ourselves to hike.</p>

<p>The hike itself was pretty nice; the only sort of less nice thing about the trail is that it is a shared horse trail so there were swaths where the ground was pretty torn up and totally muddy. We were passed by two small groups who were riding on horseback to Kolsay 2 and otherwise only ran into a handful of other hikers, some of whom were carrying backpacking gear. Kolsay 2 looked like a lovely place to camp! Except for one burning trash pile that was completely unattended that at one point went off like a gunshot as something burned. Holy macaroni, that scared the pants off of me (and the horses) for a second.</p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230076.jpg" alt="Kevin and Kolsay 2" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230076.jpg" alt="Kevin and Kolsay 2" /></p>

<p>Kevin and Kolsay 2</p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230072.jpg" alt="Kolsay 2" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230072.jpg" alt="Kolsay 2" /></p>

<p>Kolsay 2</p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230068.jpg" alt="20240923-P9230068.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230068.jpg" alt="20240923-P9230068.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230065.jpg" alt="20240923-P9230065.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230065.jpg" alt="20240923-P9230065.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230054.jpg" alt="Kolsay 1" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230054.jpg" alt="Kolsay 1" /></p>

<p>Kolsay 1</p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230076.jpg" alt="Kevin and Kolsay 2" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230072.jpg" alt="Kolsay 2" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230068.jpg" alt="20240923-P9230068.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230065.jpg" alt="20240923-P9230065.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240923-P9230054.jpg" alt="Kolsay 1" /></p>

<p>We had a bit of a situation at the start of the hike though. There was an adorable dog roaming around the trail start who decided that he wanted to go on the hike with us. The only issue was that he was injured! He had a gnarly gash in one of his paws and was hopping on three feet trying to follow us. We didn’t want to continue to have him try to come along with us while he was in such a state. We tried to turn around and walk back but as soon as we thought we lost him, he’d come bounding back. At one point, he dashed into the lake for both a drink and to sooth his bleeding paw. We met another Russian couple a bit along the trail and with all of us we took him back to the trailhead to figure out who he belonged to. It was pretty clear he wasn’t a stray because he was quite clean and also looked well-fed. Eventually, while Kevin and the Russian couple went to hunt down the owner, I stayed with the dog and ran into another two tourists from India who started to feed him some of their extra food. Kevin came back and said that the Russian couple was able to communicate with some random folks who said that his owner is not around right now and the dog just hangs around the area and usually follows for about a half hour and then will turn around. He also mentioned that the dog has been injured for a little while but the owner doesn’t really want to do anything about it and there aren’t really any pet centers in the area. The poor dog! Thankfully, he was distracted enough by the food that we were able to sneak away and restart our hike without him following. He was lounging by the lake when we returned and gave him some cuddles before we headed back to our abode for the night.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/20240923_095930.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<figcaption>

Our doggo friend. You can sort of see that his front right paw is swollen and injured.

</figcaption>

<p><strong>Day 7: Saty -&gt; Lake Issyk -&gt; Turgen Gorge</strong></p>

<p>Originally, our plan was to drive to Turgen Gorge this day and then do a sixteen kilometer waterfall hike, but we somehow misjudged the length of driving time which was two hours longer than we had planned for so we swapped our plans for day seven and eight. We first drove to Lake Issyk (also created by a landslide though around 8000-10000 years ago) and wandered/hiked around the lake for a bit. The lake, I think, used to be quite a huge lake with lots of facilities and shops and recreational activities but after a mudslide in 1963, it shrunk and many of the facilities were destroyed and have not been rebuilt. We could see the weathered remains, sometimes just their foundations, of the buildings that used to rim the lake. It felt weirdly like we were in an ancient city, except this was only from a few decades ago. The lake itself is unbelievably gorgeous with the bright sun turning it into a still plate of Tiffany blue, edged with birch trees now shining with beautiful marigold colored leaves. I spent quite a bit of time trying to play around with my camera settings to capture the vivid colors. It was really a spectacular fall day!</p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_41.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_41.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_41.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_41.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_35.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_35.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_35.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_35.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_20.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_20.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_20.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_20.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_12.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_12.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_12.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_12.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_24.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_24.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_24.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_24.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240924_142952.jpg" alt="20240924_142952.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240924_142952.jpg" alt="20240924_142952.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_41.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_41.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_35.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_35.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_20.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_20.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_12.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_12.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_24.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_lake_issyk_24.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/20240924_142952.jpg" alt="20240924_142952.jpg" /></p>

<p>From the lake, we drove to our final homestay in Turgen Gorge. After being warmly welcomed by our lovely host Nataly, we explored the grounds which actually were really nice and peppered with apple trees. I ate some small tart apples. We befriended another animal, one of the lodge’s cats, who trailed us around, purring whenever we stooped to pet her. We eventually meandered back to our room (which was an excellently equipped small room with lots of thought put into all the basic items that folks like us would need… dish soap, a microwave, cutlery, two each of bowls, plates, and cups, and a sharp cutting knife and board) and turned in for the night.</p>

<p>&gt;</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/20240925_090304.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Day 8: Turgen Gorge -&gt; Almaty</strong></p>

<p>Last day! I have to mention a totally random thing; petrol. In general, we were careful to make sure that our car always had more than half a tank of gas because there were lots of stretches where there were no gas stations. However, once one got close enough to a town, there would be gas stations every few hundred meters or so. Filling up roughly three quarters of our SUV cost us… drumroll… TWENTY DOLLARS. What?! A liter of gas here was 205 tenge which is forty-two cents. I guess there are some benefits to being an oil country.</p>

<p>We started off our last day with a nice easy hike to Kairak waterfall. The hike was very quiet; we met just one other person on the way to the waterfall and a few more families while we were returning back to our car (one family wanted to take photos with us so we paused to take some photos with all sorts of configurations of the family. In retrospect, I wish we’d gotten some of our own too!). We walked a little ways past the waterfall to find a nice place to have our lunch and realized from AllTrails that there are <em>tons</em> of trails in the area. Some of them are even 4x4 trails. I think it is possible to do multi-day treks with a guide into the Tien Shan mountains that constitute as the border between Kazakhstan and Kyrgyzstan, but the weather was slated to turn to snow just two days after we finished our road trip and our visas are about to expire so we decided to continue on. We are perpetually using running away from weather as our primary decision maker for travel plans.</p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_37.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_37.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_37.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_37.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_15.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_15.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_15.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_15.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_10.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_10.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_10.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_10.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_36.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_36.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_36.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_36.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_25.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_25.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_25.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_25.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_20.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_20.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_20.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_20.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_37.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_37.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_15.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_15.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_10.JPG" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_10.JPG" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_36.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_36.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_25.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_25.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="images/almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_20.jpg" alt="almaty_roadtrip_turgen_gorge_20.jpg" /></p>

<p>It was around 3 or 4pm or so by the time we finished our hike so we headed back to Almaty from Turgen Gorge. Boy, we ran into quite a bit of traffic! I think the one and half hour trip ended up taking us closer to three hours but we finally got back and parked our car right at the “avtomoyka” (car wash). Our clothes needed a serious “moyka” as well after all the muddy hiking!</p>

<p>What a great trip! We are so glad that so many things fell into place nicely to be able to do this trip on our own. Kazakhstan really has some spectacular landscapes and hikes even if Kyrgyzstan is more well known for their outdoorsy activities. And now, we’re in the last leg of our Kazakhstan adventures! I can’t believe how quickly time is passing by. We’ve got our next two countries set after Kazakhstan which will be Jordan and Bhutan. We probably will only have one or two more after that before Christmas. Crazy!</p>

<p>All cats love Kevin.</p>]]></content><author><name>Arathi and Kevin</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Per the owner’s request, yesterday we returned our trusty Geely Atlas SUV back to Almaty, directly into a car wash where the attendants immediately got to work scrubbing off the thick crusted layer of dust, dirt, and dung (primarily of the equestrian variety) that even a heavy downpour could not rinse away. I watched in amusement as the attendant repeatedly went over a particularly stubborn section on the back of the vehicle over and over with the power washer while we waited to meet the car rental owner to wrap up the paperwork. Yesterday, we returned back to Almaty after an eight day road trip covering several of the national parks in the Almaty region. I’m really proud of how well Kevin and I managed to piece together this road trip, pulling bits and pieces from various trip reports, blogs, lots of map tools (Yandex Maps, 2GIS, and Google Maps), and plenty of AI tools (I’m a particularly heavy user of Gemini and a bit less of Claude and Kevin uses Gemini, Claude, and a bit less of GPT and some others). The use of AI tools has been one noticeable difference in how we plan our travel from the start of the year to now. I have both the Gemini and Claude apps installed on my phone (though I only pay for Gemini) and use the tools very heavily, usually multiple times a day. Especially in countries where English resources aren’t as readily available or additional time is required to peruse through Google Search results to find an answer, I instead opt to use Gemini to ask things like “why isn’t it advisable to drink the tap water in Kazakhstan?” or “At Amboseli National Park, there was a particular kind of white bird that always trailed after elephants and ate food that would get unearthed when the elephants pawed at the earth. What type of bird is it?” Randomly, I learned that giving greeting cards is not popular throughout this planet; I wanted to send greeting cards for special occasions while we were in Turkey and most recently in Kazakhstan and in both countries, cards are not a thing. Gemini came to the rescue to help find places that sell something that is pretty close to a greeting card (in both cases, the “cards” don’t really open… it’s more like a glorified postcard) when Google Maps failed me. Watching us use these AI tools more and more makes me sort of wonder how working might be different when we re-enter the workforce in a few months. When we left our jobs, the tools we used were more for curiosity than for real purpose but in our current daily lives, that seems to already change. I’m sort of amazed by it because we’re changing even though we’re not in the middle of it all the way we used to be; I’d have assumed we would be a bit slower on the uptake given our distance from where it all is happening in the US and western Europe.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/P9220046.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/the-ring-tour-of-almaty/P9220046.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>